<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000254" titleName="AMR, Adaptive Multi-Rate Speech Codec" shortName="AMR" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>sound</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>telephony</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2012-02-09</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Partial</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>AMR, Adaptive Multi-Rate Speech Codec</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>AMR</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Audio data compression scheme optimized for speech coding, adopted in October 1998 as the standard speech codec by 3GPP (3d Generation Partnership Project) and now widely used in GSM (Global System for Mobile Communications). In its evolved form, GSM is also known as UMTS (Universal Mobile Telecommunications System).</p>
			<p>The AMR bit rates of 12.2, 10.2, 7.95, 7.40, 6.70, 5.90, 5.15 and 4.75 kb/s are based on frames that contain 160 samples and are 20 milliseconds long. AMR uses different techniques, including Algebraic Code Excited Linear Prediction (ACELP) compression, Discontinuous Transmission (DTX), voice activity detection (VAD) and comfort noise generation (CNG). The usage of AMR requires optimized link adaptation that selects the best codec mode to meet the local radio channel and capacity requirements. AMR is also a file format for storing spoken audio; many modern mobile telephone handsets will store short recordings in the AMR format, and commercial programs exist to convert between this and other formats such as MP3. (Preceding adapted from the Wikipedia <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_multi-rate_compression">Adaptive_multi-rate_compression</a> entry.)</p>
			<p>At this Web site, <fddLink id="fdd000253">AMR-WB+</fddLink> is treated as a subtype of AMR and, in turn, <fddLink id="fdd000255">AMR-WB</fddLink> is treated as a subtype of AMR-WB+ since AMR-WB is more constrained. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Audio data compression scheme optimized for speech coding, adopted in October 1998 as the standard speech codec by 3GPP (3d Generation Partnership Project) and now widely used in GSM (Global System for Mobile Communications). The AMR bit rates of 12.2, 10.2, 7.95, 7.40, 6.70, 5.90, 5.15 and 4.75 kb/s are based on frames that contain 160 samples and are 20 milliseconds long. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Final-state for end-user delivery.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000253</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>AMR-WB+</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>AMR-WB+, Extended Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband Speech Codec</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>QuickTime File with AMR encoded audio, not documented at this Web site at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Other audio file formats not documented at this Web site.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The subtype <fddLink id="fdd000253">AMR-WB+</fddLink> has been selected as the audio codec for LC-produced <a href="http://www.loc.gov/nls/businessplan/businessplan2006.html">Digital Talking Books</a>; see also <fddLink id="fdd000256">DTB_Ext</fddLink>.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>None</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard.  Developed by <a href="http://www.3gpp.org/">3GPP</a>, the 3d Generation Partnership Project, a collaboration of telecommunications industry and standards groups in Europe, Asia, and North America. The key European organization is <a href="http://www.etsi.org">ETSI</a> (European Telecommunications Standards Institute).</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>3GPP TS 26.071, <i>Digital cellular telecommunications system (Phase 2+); Universal Mobile Telecommunications System (UMTS); AMR Speech Codec; General description</i>, and other specifications listed in <a href="#specs">Format specifications</a> below.  This Web page is intended to be somewhat generic regarding AMR; readers should note, however, that the December 2004 version of this specification is marked as Version 6.0.0 Release 6. The initial version was published in 1999.</p>
			<p>According to the <a href="http://www.voiceage.com/AMR-NB.AMR.html">VoiceAge</a> AMR Web page (consulted in April 2007), AMR was standardized by ETSI in 1999 and, in 2006, it was included in the CableLabs PacketCable 2.0 specification.  These specifications have not been investigated for this Web site at this time.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication to build tools.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>Low; this is a format to carry voices to telephones using reduced bandwidth. Higher quality is provided by the wideband variants of AMR: <fddLink id="fdd000255">AMR-WB</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000253">AMR-WB+</fddLink>.</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>None.</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:beyondSound>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:beyondSound>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>amr</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://filext.com/">The File Extension Source</a>. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>audio/AMR</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://filext.com/">The File Extension Source</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 0x2321414d520a</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: #!AMR\n </fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4867.txt">RFC 4867</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>3gp</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For files containing various forms of data associated with the 3GPP and 3GPP2 projects; from the <a href="http://filext.com/">File Extension Source</a>.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a> on the applicability of 3gp files to AMR data.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>audio/3gpp</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For files containing various forms of audio data associated with the 3GPP and 3GPP2 projects; from the <a href="http://filext.com/">File Extension Source</a>.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a> on the applicability of this MIME type to AMR data.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 00 00 00</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For files with the <i>3gp</i> extension; from <a href="http://filext.com/">The File Extension Source</a>.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a> on the applicability of 3gp files to AMR data.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>From the <a href="http://www.voiceage.com/AMR-NB.AMR.html">VoiceAge</a> Web site (consulted in April 2007): The proven, highly efficient and very robust AMR (Adaptive Multi-Rate) narrowband codec is the 3GPP mandatory standard codec for narrowband speech and multimedia messaging services over 2.5G/3G wireless systems based on evolved GSM core networks (WCDMA, EDGE, GPRS). . . .  AMR operating at various bit rates is built into every GSM and WCDMA phone, ensuring that content generated by AMR can be played by virtually any wireless phone in the world . . . . AMR operates on narrowband (200-3400 Hz) signals at variable bit rates in the range of 4.75 to 12.2 kbps. It provides toll quality speech starting at 7.4 kbps, with near-toll quality and better robustness at lower rates and better reproduction of non-speech sounds at higher rates. . . . AMR is the only narrowband speech codec offering eight different bit rates that can be adapted according to network congestion.</p>
			<p>Although there are file formats associated with AMR (see Signifiers above), the Library of Congress interest in AMR is related to the encoding aspects, since the subtype <fddLink id="fdd000253">AMR-WB+</fddLink> is used in <fddLink id="fdd000256">DTB_Ext</fddLink>, DTB (Digital Talking Book), Extension for AMR-WB+ Speech Codec.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_multi-rate_compression">Wikipedia AMR entry</a> states that 3GPP adoption occurred in 1998; the <a href="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/26071.htm">3GPP Web site</a> provides 1999 as the first publication date for the descriptive specification.  The <a href="http://www.voiceage.com/AMR-NB.AMR.html">VoiceAge</a> Web site (consulted in April 2007) included this information: "Initially developed for the GSM system, the single most deployed 2G mobile telecommunication system worldwide, AMR was also standardized by the European Telecommunications Standards Institute (ETSI) in 1999, and in 2006, it was included in the CableLabs PacketCable 2.0 specification."</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>RFC 4867 (RTP Payload Format and File Storage Format for the Adaptive Multi-Rate [AMR] and Adaptive Multi-Rate Wideband [AMR-WB] Audio Codecs) is available online from IETF at more than one site and in more than one format:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4867</link>
							<tag>RFC 4867 in various formats</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4867.txt</link>
							<tag>RFC 4867 in plain text</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:docGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Relevant specifications are provided at no cost to registered users of the 3GPP Web site from this menu: <a href="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/26-series.htm">http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/26-series.htm</a>.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:referenceList>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.071, AMR speech Codec; General description</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.073, AMR speech Codec; C-source code</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.074, AMR speech Codec; Test sequences</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.077, Minimum performance requirements for noise suppresser application to the Adaptive Multi-Rate (AMR) speech encoder</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.090, AMR speech Codec; Transcoding Functions</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.091, AMR speech Codec; Error concealment of lost frames</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.092, AMR speech Codec; comfort noise for AMR Speech Traffic Channels</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.093, Mandatory speech codec speech processing functions Adaptive Multi-Rate (AMR) speech codec; Source controlled rate operation</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.094, Mandatory speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate (AMR) speech codec; Voice Activity Detector (VAD)</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.101, Mandatory speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate (AMR) speech codec frame structure</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.102, Mandatory speech codec; Adaptive Multi-Rate (AMR) speech codec; Interface to Iu, Uu and Nb</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.104, ANSI-C code for the floating-point Adaptive Multi-Rate (AMR) speech codec</fdd:specReference>
					</fdd:referenceList>
				</fdd:docGroup>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_Multi-Rate_audio_codec</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia article Adaptive Multi-Rate audio codec</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.voiceage.com/AMR-WB.G.722.2.html</link>
					<tag>VoiceAge AMR Web page</tag>
					<comment/>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
