<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000621" titleName="WordPerfect Document Family" shortName="WPD" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>family</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>office/business</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2023-11-14</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>WordPerfect Document Family</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>word processing formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The WordPerfect Document (WPD) family is the <a href="https://product.corel.com/help/CorelDRAW/540223850/Main/EN/Documentation/wwhelp/wwhimpl/common/html/wwhelp.htm#href=CorelDRAW-WordPerfect-Document-WPD.html">native default file format</a> for textual content in the WordPerfect word-processing application. The WordPerfect application was developed in the 1970s, was very popular in the 1980s and 1990s, and is still available today. Throughout its history, the application has been available on many different operating systems including Mac, Windows, DOS and Linux. Unusually, the windows version was only released in 1991 for WordPerfect 5.1 for Windows. More recently, it is only available on Windows. See <a href="#sustainability">Adoption</a> for more information about use and <a href="#notes">History</a> for information about software versions and release dates.</p>
			<p>The structure of the WPD file format varies greatly depending on the version and the operating system. There have been many file format extensions throughout its history, such as .wp, .wpd, .wp4, .wp5, .wp6, .wp7 in which the number indicates the software version with which it is associated. See <a href="#sign">File Signifiers</a> for more information.  Some MacOS versions saved files without a file extension. The internal structure of the of the file differs depending on the operating system. See For <a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/WPMac4FileFormat.pdf">WordPerfect 4.0 for MacIntosh</a> (2011), for example, "A WordPerfect 4.0 file consists of a WordPerfect header immediately followed by the WordPerfect document.  All data associated with a WordPerfect file are stored in the data fork of a Macintosh file. The WordPerfect header consists of the WordPerfect prefix and the embedded Macintosh resource fork.  The WordPerfect document consists of ASCII text with embedded function codes. The creator type of 3.0/4.0 files is ‘WPC2’ and the file type is ‘WPD2.’  Other associated WordPerfect files that share the same creator type (WPC2) include libraries (WPLB), stationary files (sPD2), temporaries (WPTV), backups (WPBK), help (WP??), and defaults (WPDF).  4.0/3.0 dictionary (DICT) and thesaurus (THES) files have type ‘WPCU’ as their creator." The resource fork contains &quot;such resources as printer job (PJob), printer definition (PtPt), and page setup (PSet).  It may also contain macros (Wmac), temporary styles (TStl), styles (Styl), pictures (WBOX, Pict), overlays (WBFN), window definition (WDat), font maps (FNTD) and keyboards (WPkg, WPkr, WPkt, WPkx).&quot; Document formating, as such new line, new page, begin column and many more, is accomplished by embedding function codes in the ASCII text of a document, such as those detailed in <a href="https://archive.org/download/wordperfectsdkperfectfit1994/WordPerfect_SDK_PerfectFit1994.iso/51PCSDK%2FWP42FF.TXT">WordPerfect File Information version 4.2 (1984, 1985, 1986)</a>.  <a href="https://archive.org/download/wordperfectsdkperfectfit1994/WordPerfect_SDK_PerfectFit1994.iso/51PCSDK%2FWP42FF.TXT">WordPerfect File Information version 4.2 (1984, 1985, 1986)</a> also states that &quot;WordPerfect files are ASCII files.  The text is neither encrypted nor
compacted.&quot; However, &quot;locking&quot; or password protection is possible in some versions. See <a href="#sustainability">Technical Protection Mechanisms</a>.</p>
			<p>According to <a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/chronology.html">WordPerfect for DOS: Chronology of Versions</a>, "to determine the WordPerfect version used to create a document, you can open the document in a hex viewer. The identifying bytes for WordPerfect versions are byte 10 (File Type), byte 11 (Major Version number), and byte 12 (Minor Version number) within the file. Byte 12, the Minor Version, is 00 for the first release of WordPerfect for Mac 2.x and 3.x, as well as for WordPerfect for DOS 5.0 and 6.0. This changes to 01 for later releases, including WordPerfect for DOS 6.2 and all versions of WordPerfect for Windows."</p>
			<p>Detailed information about the file format for Windows and other operating systems is very limited. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>The WordPerfect Document (WPD) family is the native default file format for textual content in the WordPerfect word-processing application</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Can be used in any phase of production: Initial state (creating documents, middle state (editing and reviewing documents), and final distribution.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has extension</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000614</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MLM</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>GroupWise Email Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Affinity to</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>WordPerfect Graphics Format (WPG), primarily a vector graphic format, but it can store both bitmap and vector data in the WordPerfect application. The WPG files may contain up to 256 colors, chosen from a palette of more than 1 million colors. Not described separately at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Affinity to</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000392</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>CFB_4</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Microsoft Compound File Binary File Format, Version 4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>According to <a href="https://justsolve.archiveteam.org/wiki/WordPerfect">WPD</a> from Archiveteam.org, WordPerfect version 7 can also store documents known as &quot;WordPerfect Compound File&quot; using the Microsoft OLE Compound file format with the same WPD extensions. OLE embedded objects are stored inside a storage called PerfectOffice_OBJECT, whereas the real document part is now stored as stream PerfectOffice_MAIN. In principal the format of this internal document part is the same like in previous versions, but one difference is that the minor version number is raised from 1 to 2.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>As of late 2023, The Library of Congress has under 100,000 WordPerfect files with a variety of format extensions (wpd, wp4, wp5, wp6) mostly in the Manuscript Division collections.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See the Recommended Formats Statement for the Library of Congress format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/text.html">textual works</a>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>This is a closed, proprietary format from Novell and later, Corel, with scarce publicly available information. </fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>Documentation for this format is limited. In-depth documentation is not available online as it is <a href="https://www.wordperfect.com/static/wpo/product_content/wordperfect/2021/wpo2021-user-guide-en.pdf">linked from within the application</a>.
			</p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://archive.org/download/wordperfectsdkperfectfit1994/WordPerfect_SDK_PerfectFit1994.iso/51PCSDK%2FWP42FF.TXT">Version 4.2 WordPerfect File Format Specification</a>.  Link via the Internet Archive.</p>
			<p>There have been some efforts to reverse-engineer the WordPerfect formats. The research from this work is available online:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="https://libwpd.sourceforge.net/features.html">libwpd</a>: A C++ library designed to assist in processing WordPerfect documents.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://github.com/john-hern/wp_encrypt_crack">wp_encrypt_crack</a>: An encryption cracker designed specifically for WordPerfect 4.2, originally released in 1987. The source code for this tool can be found on GitHub.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://github.com/OneWingedShark/WordPerfect">WordPerfect Project</a>: A package intended for creating, reading, modifying, and saving documents in the WPD format. Note that the project's name, "WordPerfect," may appear confusing, as it aligns with the WordPerfect software. </li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>WordPerfect was widely utilized during the 1980s and 1990s.  It was the dominant word processing software for MS-DOS holding more than 50% of the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220714212727/https:/www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/technology/state-of-the-art-it-s-a-word-world-or-is-it.html?pagewanted=2">global market share</a> during this period and in direct competition with <fddLink id="fdd000522">WordStar</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>WordPerfect's adoption began to wane after Microsoft Office's release in the mid-1980s with Microsoft Word overtaking WordPerfect as the most popular word processor <a href="https://personal.utdallas.edu/~liebowit/book/wordprocessor/word.html">by 1992</a>.  However, WordPerfect still has many users today and is still actively maintained.  See the <a href="#notes">History</a> section for more details. </p>
			<p>WordPerfect is currently only available for the Windows operating system.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>Unknown. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Not transparent. This format is not easily interpreted with basic tools.
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>WordPerfect versions 5 and later self-identify with Magic Numbers. Earlier versions do not have this identifying information.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>WPD files are created by the WordPerfect application as the native format but can be converted to other formats, such as PDF, for use with other systems. </fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>Encryption is possible in some versions using the <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1424">“locking” feature</a>, specifically 4.2. Methods for "unlocking" these files are detailed in the <a href="https://github.com/john-hern/wp_encrypt_crack">wp_encrypt_crack</a> repository on GitHub. Files can also be <a href="https://www.wordperfect.com/en/pages/items/1500800.html">password protected</a>.
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>WordPerfect X4 allows Unicode pasting if performed in a <a href="https://www.wpuniverse.com/vb/forum/special-topics/news-views/30300-unicode-and-the-future-of-wordperfect?31119-Unicode-and-the-future-of-WordPerfect">specific way</a>.  Other than this one exception, WordPerfect does not support Unicode or UTF-8.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>
				<p>WordPerfect renders documents on screen to closely resemble their printed appearance, including page layout, margins, and justifications.</p>
				<p>WordPerfect documents commonly feature recognizable elements such as paragraphs, sections, headers, footers, and named styles (e.g., headings). The software provides excellent support for higher-level constructs, offering automatically generated tables of contents and indexes, as well as structured templates. It's important to note that while the use of these styles is available, it's not mandatory, and document structure may be conveyed solely through font usage and paragraph indenting.</p>
				<p>The structure of WordPerfect varies significantly between versions, with notable differences between the MS-DOS version and later Windows editions.  </p>
			</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>
				<p>Excellent support for layout choices. Represents the entire layout and formatting as intended by the user in mimicking a printed appearance. Bi-directional and vertical display of text can be specified. Differences in detail can occur on display if the original fonts used are not available in the system used for viewing or due to conversion from another word-processing format with different markup semantics.</p>
				<p>The structure of WordPerfect varies significantly between versions, with notable differences between the MS-DOS version and later Windows editions.</p>
			</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>
				<p>Mathematical operations related to document formatting, such as adjusting margin space, are accomplished using dot commands. These operations are saved within the file as executables. WordPerfect also includes a reasonably capable built-in calculator that supports scientific notation. However, it's important to note that all such calculations are performed locally and saved as plain ASCII characters alongside the text information.</p>
				<p>In earlier versions, the software exclusively accepted ASCII characters and did not support any other character sets.</p>
				<p>
					<a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.
				</p>
			</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>
				<a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.
			</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>wpd</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>wp</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>wp4</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>wp5</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>wp6</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>wp7</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>
					<p>WPD is the file extension declared by <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.wordperfect">IANA</a> in 2004. Numbered extensions are specific to the version of the WordPerfect application. See PRONOM PUIDs below.</p>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>doc</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Some sources state that WordPerfect utilized .doc.  See the Wikidata entry for <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62664770">WordPerfect version 6</a> and the PRONOM entry for <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/394">WordPerfect version 5.1</a>.					<a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.wordperfect</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From the <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.wordperfect">IANA Media Types</a> registry in 2004.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: FF 57 50 43 </fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: ÿWPC
					</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>
					WordPerfect versions 5 and later self-identify with Magic Numbers. From <a href="https://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html">GCK&apos;S File Signatures Table</a> for WordPerfect text and graphics files. See also <a href="http://justsolve.archiveteam.org/wiki/WordPerfect">WordPerfect</a> from ArchivesTeam.org.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Microsoft FOURCC</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>WPC2</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>From <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.wordperfect">IANA</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>NF00453</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID. WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document, version 5.1. See <a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00453.ttl">https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00453.ttl</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/892</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Compound WordPerfect for Windows Document. Versions 6 onwards. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/892">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/892</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/949</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect 4.0/4.1/4.2. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/949">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/949</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/1220</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for Macintosh Document. Version 2.x. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1220">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1220</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/1222</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for Macintosh Document  3.5-4.x. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1222">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1222</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/1221</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for Macintosh Document  3.x. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1221">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1221</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>x-fmt/393</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for MS-DOS Document  5.0. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/393">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/393</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>x-fmt/394</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document  5.1. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/394">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/394</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>x-fmt/44</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document  6.x. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/44">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/44</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>x-fmt/203</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for Windows Document 5.2. See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/203">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/203</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q62664770</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document file format, version 6. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62664770">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62664770</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q61641450</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for MS-DOS Document. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q61641450">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q61641450</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q50308743</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect file format, v4. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q50308743">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q50308743</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q73019664</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document, version 5.1. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q73019664">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q73019664</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q60628185</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect Secondary File, version 5. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60628185">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60628185</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q100377205</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect 4.2 Encrypted Document. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q100377205">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q100377205</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q109265681</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WordPerfect Document (family). See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q109265681">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q109265681</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>WordPerfect gained recognition for pioneering features, like <a href="https://archive.org/details/1985-08-compute-magazine/page/n41/mode/2up?view=theater">spellcheck</a>, that were considered groundbreaking at the time. BYTE magazine, in 1985, described these features as "<a href="https://archive.org/details/1985-08-compute-magazine/page/n39/mode/2up?view=theater">either rare or unique</a>". Moreover, during the MS-DOS era, WordPerfect gained popularity due to its innovative use of "macros." These macros allowed users to efficiently automate writing tasks, with <a href="https://archive.org/details/byte-magazine-1984-12/page/n281/mode/2up?view=theater">BYTE Magazine in 1984</a> stating, "WordPerfect can be taught to remember a series of keystrokes, file them, and retrieve them as needed".</p>
			<p>WordPerfect had specific file formats associated with it, including WPG (<a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q50419770">WordPerfect Graphics Metafile</a>), WPM and WCM (<a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q66424671">WordPerfect Macro File</a>), and SHW (<a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q105853195">WordPerfect Presentations</a>). These formats have their own Wikidata entries but are not within the scope of this discussion. WordPerfect had an affinity with the OLE Compound File format, making it compatible with both WordPerfect and Microsoft Word.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The WordPerfect application <a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/chronology.htm">was developed</a> in the late 1970s at Brigham Young University for use in Data General’s minicomputers.  The developers retained their rights to the program and formed Satellite Software International (SSI) in 1979 to sell their creation. In March 1980, the program made its debut under the name SSI*WP.</p>
			<p>In 1982, WordPerfect transitioned to the MS-DOS operating system, and by that time, it had adopted the name WordPerfect. The software quickly underwent significant updates and improvements. Notably, it stood out from its main competitor, WordStar, which was built for the CP/M operating system and struggled to transition to MS-DOS.</p>
			<p>In 1985, Satellite Software International changed its name to WordPerfect Corporation.</p>
			<p>WordPerfect gained recognition for its clean and uncluttered interface. It <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101126144940/https:/www.nytimes.com/1992/03/30/business/wordperfect-executive-is-forced-out.html">gained rapid popularity</a>, especially after the release of version 4.2 in 1986. By the time version 5.1 was released in 1989, it had become the standard in the DOS market. Its early success has been attributed to its availability across various computers and operating systems, as well as its robust, no-cost customer support.</p>
			<p>However, WordPerfect's dominant position <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101126144940/https:/www.nytimes.com/1992/03/30/business/wordperfect-executive-is-forced-out.html">eventually waned</a>, primarily due to a failed release for Microsoft Windows. The company attributed this failure to Microsoft's initial reluctance to share its Windows Application Programming Interface (API) specifications, resulting in a sluggish WordPerfect Windows application. Although they eventually received the Windows APIs and improved the software, Microsoft Word had already entered the market and gained an advantage due to its speed. Aggressive bundling deals that led to the creation of Microsoft Office further cemented Word's dominance. By the mid-1990s, WordPerfect was no longer the popular standard.</p>
			<p>In 1994, WordPerfect Corporation was sold to Novell, which subsequently sold the product to Corel in 1996. Corel <a href="https://www.alludo.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/20220913-corel-rebrands-as-alludo/">continues to release updates</a> and new versions under the WordPerfect name, often as part of office suites that include applications like Quattro Pro for spreadsheets and Presentations for slide formatting.</p>
			<p>For a detailed chronology of WordPerfect versions see <a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/chronology.html">WordPerfect for DOS: Chronology of Versions</a>.
			</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/WPMac4FileFormat.pdf</link>
					<tag>Macintosh WordPerfect 4.0 File Format Manual, January 4, 2011</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wordperfect.com/static/wpo/product_content/wordperfect/2021/wpo2021-user-guide-en.pdf</link>
					<tag>WordPerfect 2021 User Guide.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/chronology.html</link>
					<tag>WordPerfect Chronology.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/index.html</link>
					<tag>WordPerfect at Columbia University.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://archive.org/details/1985-08-compute-magazine/page/n39/mode/2up?view=theater</link>
					<tag>“WordPerfect for IBM”. Computer Magazine, August 1985.</tag>
					<comment>Link via the Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://archive.org/details/byte-magazine-1984-12/page/n281/mode/2up?view=theater</link>
					<tag>“Review: WordPerfect”. BYTE Magazine, December 1984. </tag>
					<comment>Link via the Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://archive.org/download/wordperfectsdkperfectfit1994/WordPerfect_SDK_PerfectFit1994.iso/51PCSDK%2FWP42FF.TXT</link>
					<tag>WordPerfect SDK PerfectFit 1994.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://gswv.apple2.org.za/a2zine/Sel/WordPerfectPD.html</link>
					<tag>WordPerfect for the Apple IIgs.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://personal.utdallas.edu/~liebowit/book/wordprocessor/word.html</link>
					<tag>Word Processing: The Early Years.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20101126144940/https:/www.nytimes.com/1992/03/30/business/wordperfect-executive-is-forced-out.html</link>
					<tag>“WordPerfect Executive Is Forced Out “. New York Times, March 30, 1992.</tag>
					<comment>Link via the Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20220714212727/https:/www.nytimes.com/2000/09/21/technology/state-of-the-art-it-s-a-word-world-or-is-it.html?pagewanted=2</link>
					<tag>“STATE OF THE ART; It's a Word World, Or Is It?”. New York Times, September 21, 2000. </tag>
					<comment>Link via the Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html</link>
					<tag>Gary Kessler's File Signatures.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wpuniverse.com/vb/</link>
					<tag>WordPerfect Universe Forum. An active, dedicated user forum.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wpuniverse.com/vb/forum/special-topics/news-views/30300-unicode-and-the-future-of-wordperfect?31119-Unicode-and-the-future-of-WordPerfect=&amp;postid=211149#post327674</link>
					<tag>Unicode and the Future of WordPerfect. </tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://libwpd.sourceforge.net/features.html</link>
					<tag>libwpd</tag>
					<comment>A C++ library designed to assist in processing WordPerfect documents.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/john-hern/wp_encrypt_crack</link>
					<tag>wp_encrypt_crack</tag>
					<comment>An encryption cracker designed specifically for WordPerfect 4.2, originally released in 1987. The source code for this tool can be found on GitHub.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/OneWingedShark/WordPerfect</link>
					<tag>WordPerfect Project</tag>
					<comment>A package intended for creating, reading, modifying, and saving documents in the WPD format. Note that the project's name, "WordPerfect," may appear confusing, as it aligns with the WordPerfect software.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>PRONOM entries</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1220</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for Macintosh Document. Version 2.x. </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1424</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect Document Format (Mac).</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1221</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for Macintosh Document  3.x.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1222</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for Macintosh Document  3.5-4.x.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/949</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect 4.0/4.1/4.2.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/393</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for MS-DOS Document 5.0.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/394</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document  5.1.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/203</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for Windows Document 5.2.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/44</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document  6.x.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/892</link>
							<tag>Compound WordPerfect for Windows Document. Versions 6 onwards.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Wikidata entries</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q174757</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect software application.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q100377205</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect 4.2 Encrypted Document. </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q109265681</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect Document (family).</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q50308743</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect file format, v4.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q61641450</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for MS-DOS Document.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62664770</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document file format, version 6.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q73019664</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect for MS-DOS/Windows Document, version 5.1.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60628185</link>
							<tag>WordPerfect Secondary File, version 5.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
