<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000520" titleName="GeoPackage Encoding Standard (OGC) Format Family" shortName="GeoPackage_family" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>dataset</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>gis</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-06-11</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>GeoPackage Encoding Standard (OGC) family of formats</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>vector graphic formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>raster image formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>georeferenced image formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>geospatial data formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>A GeoPackage is a platform-independent SQLite database file that contains data and
metadata tables with names and structures having definitions, integrity assertions, format limitations
and content constraints as described in the OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard from the Open Geospatial Consortium. The first version of this standard was published in February 2014.  All versions of the GeoPackage Encoding Standard are based on <fddLink id="fdd000461">version 3 of the SQLite file format</fddLink>. As described in <a href="https://www.ogc.org/blog/3148">#GeoPackageDay 2020 - what is GeoPackage? (February 2020)</a>, in addition to interoperability, GeoPackage was devised with three main goals in mind: to be a convenient, efficient container for geospatial information; to enable operations in all computing environments, including those with Disconnected, Degraded, Intermittent, or Limited (DDIL) network connectivity; and to be extensible, allowing it to evolve to meet future operational needs.</p>
			<p>The GeoPackage Encoding Standard specifies GeoPackages for exchange and GeoPackage SQLite Extensions that permit direct use, without
intermediate format translations, of vector geospatial features and/or tile matrix sets of earth images and raster maps at various
scales. GeoPackages are designed to be interoperable across enterprise and personal computing environments and
usable on mobile devices with
limited connectivity and bandwidth.  An important use case for the design of GeoPackage was for mobile device use, leading to an emphasis on compactness and computatonal efficiency. The SQLite database file format is a binary format and uses b-trees to store table data.  B-trees support rapid access to data within tables, and are a basic technique used for organizing data for sorting and searching.  The specification cites the particular b-tree algorithms used.  The algorithms are described in Donald Knuth&apos;s <i>The Art of Computer Programming</i> [<a href="http://lccn.loc.gov/97002147">LCCN: 97002147</a>], Volume 3, pages 471-479.</p>
			<p>A useful diagram of the database tables in a GeoPackage is <a href="https://www.geopackage.org/spec/#geopackage_tables_figure">Figure 1</a> in the Introduction to the standard.  A more detailed <a href="https://www.geopackage.org/spec121/#_geopackage_tables_detailed_diagram">diagram</a> is in Appendix B, clause B.11, as Figure 4. </p>
			<p>A GeoPackage has two required tables:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>The <i>gpkg_spatial_ref_sys</i> table documents coordinate reference systems used for data in the package.  It must include a record for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Geodetic_System">WGS-84</a>.</li>
				<li>The <i>gpkg_contents</i> table provides identifying and descriptive information for the tables containing data. It acts as a directory of the primary content in the file.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>A GeoPackage may incorporate data for vector features and/or for tiled raster images.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Vector feature data: A GeoPackage with vector feature data has a
<i>gpkg_geometry_columns</i> table that identifies the geometry columns in feature tables, which contain user
data representing features.  Geometries supported include, points, curves, lines, polygons, etc.  See GIS <a href="#factors">functionality factors</a> for a complete list.  Features are rows in a feature table. Feature attributes are
columns in a feature table.</li>
				<li>Raster image data: A GeoPackage can store multiple raster and tile pyramid data sets. In a standard GeoPackage, tiles may be in <fddLink id="fdd000018">JPEG</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink> encoding.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>A GeoPackage can also include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Attributes (non-spatial data):  Non-spatial attribute data are sets (or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuple">tuples</a> or rows) of observations that may not have an explicit geometry property.  This data is stored in user-defined attribute tables. These tables may contain properties such as an ID or geo-locatable address that allow them to be relationally linkable to rows in other attribute, feature or tile tables.  Note: this feature was introduced in Version 1.2, but had been available as a documented extension prior to that.</li>
				<li>Extensions: An SQLite database that uses constructs from the GeoPackage specification but also contains additional data elements (tables or columns)
or SQL constructs (data types, functions, indexes, constraints or triggers) that are not specified in the
GeoPackage Encoding Standard, is referred to as an Extended GeoPackage.<p>
						<fddLink id="fdd000419">GeoPackage Version 1.0</fddLink> documented a few registered extensions in individual annexes.  Since Version 1.1, Annex F of the Geopackage specification lists registered extensions, with a subclause for each.  All extensions are optional, but examples of recommended use of extensions include: (a) using the RTree Spatial Indexes extension, based on the <a href="https://www.sqlite.org/rtree.html">The SQLite R*Tree Module</a> for GeoPackages with a &quot;non-trivial amount of vector data&quot;; (b) using the <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/wkt-crs">WKT for Coordinate Reference Systems</a> extension, based on version 2.0.x of <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/wkt-crs">https://www.ogc.org/standards/wkt-crs</a>, which is strongly recommended
due to inherent weaknesses in the original GeoPackage standard for encoding coordinate reference systems.  Use of the Tiles Encoding WebP extension is required to allow representation of raster image tiles in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebP">WebP</a> format.  Since GeoPackage 1.1, there has been a registered Metadata extension, designed for incorporating metadata defined in accordance with any
authoritative metadata specifications, and relating it to the features, rasters, and tiles data in a GeoPackage. This is intended
to provide the support necessary to implement the hierarchical metadata models as defined in ISO 19115.</p>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The family of <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/geopackage">OGC GeoPackage format specifications</a> includes several chronological versions of the core standard and specifications for a few extensions.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for more detail.  Extensions are discussed in General Notes; chronological versions are listed in History.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Non-proprietary package format from the Open Geospatial Consortium for geospatial data that can contain vector feature data and/or tiled raster image sets in a platform-independent SQLite database file.  Designed to be interoperable across enterprise and personal computing environments and usable on mobile devices.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Primarily a middle-state format for a package of tiled raster images and/or vector features that can be transmitted between applications.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000461</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>SQLite_3</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>SQLite, Version 3</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000419</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>GeoPackage_1_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>GeoPackage Encoding Standard (OGC), version 1.0</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Deprecated on OGC website in October 2016. </fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Chronological versions not described separately on this website.  See list of published versions at <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/geopackage">https://www.ogc.org/standards/geopackage</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>GeoPDF files as produced by TerraGo software products may include an attachment in the GeoPackage format.  The <a href="https://terragotech.com/products/geopdf/toolbar/">TerraGo GeoPDF Toolbar</a> provides support for users of GeoPDF files, including extraction of the GeoPackage attachment.  The GeoPDF file format is not currently described on this website.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has extension</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Extensions documented in separate specifications and not described separately on this website.  See extensions listed at <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/geopackage">https://www.ogc.org/standards/geopackage</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>None directly.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) designates GeoPackage as a &quot;preferred&quot; format for GIS Vector and Raster Combined content for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/geo-carto.html">GIS, Geospatial and Non-GIS Cartographic</a> collections.  The RFS does not specify a version of GeoPackage.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard, documented in freely available specifications.  Developed and maintained by the Geopackage Standards Working Group (SWG) of the Open Geospatial Consortium (<a href="https://www.ogc.org/">OGC</a>).  See <a href="https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=59613&amp;version=1">Charter</a> for the GeoPackage SWG.  Information about the development work is available on the Geopackage.org website (<a href="https://www.geopackage.org/">https://www.geopackage.org/</a>), which provides access to the current working version as well as earlier versions approved by the OGC.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>The GeoPackage specifications can be downloaded from two locations:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/geopackage">OGC: GeoPackage Encoding Standard</a> on the OGC website.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://www.geopackage.org/">GeoPackage.org website</a>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>At any point, the current working version is available at <a href="https://www.geopackage.org/spec/">https://www.geopackage.org/spec/</a>.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>For information from OGC on support for GeoPackage in software, see <a href="http://www.geopackage.org/implementations.html">GeoPackage Implementations</a> and <a href="https://www.ogc.org/resource/products/byspec/?specid=872">Implementations by Specification for GeoPackage 1.2</a>.  The latter resource also lists support for particular extensions. OGC provides the <a href="http://cite.opengeospatial.org/teamengine/about/gpkg12/1.2/site/">GeoPackage 1.2 Conformance Test Suite</a> to verify the structure and content of a GeoPackage 1.2 data container file.</p>
			<p>As of June 2020, examples of GIS software tools that provide support for GeoPackage files include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>GDAL (Geospatial Data Abstraction Library), a driver library used by other GIS products.  Starting with GDAL 2.2, the driver has been able to create GeoPackage databases following the 1.0/1.0.1, 1.1 or 1.2 versions. For GDAL 2.2, it will automatically adjust to the minimum version required for the features of GeoPackage used. For GDAL 2.3 or later, it will default to 1.2. Explicit version choice is possible by specifying the VERSION dataset creation option.  GDAL also supports a number of the published extensions to GeoPackage. See <a href="https://gdal.org/drivers/vector/gpkg.html#vector-gpkg">GPKG – GeoPackage vector</a> and <a href="https://gdal.org/drivers/raster/gpkg.html#raster-gpkg">GPKG – GeoPackage raster</a> for details.  GDAL is used by many applications for import, export, and transformation of geospatial data, such as <a href="https://www.cadcorp.com/">Cadcorp SIS</a> and the open-source <a href="https://www.qgis.org/en/site/">QGIS</a>.  See <a href="https://gdal.org/software_using_gdal.html#software-using-gdal">Software using GDAL</a>.</li>
				<li>SAFE software&apos;s FME (Feature Manipulation Engine) has had a <a href="https://blog.safe.com/2015/01/whats-great-fme-2015/#new-formats">Reader and Writer for GeoPackage</a> since 2015.  See <a href="https://docs.safe.com/fme/html/FME_Desktop_Documentation/FME_ReadersWriters/ogcgeopackage/ogcgeopackage.htm">OGC GeoPackage Reader/Writer</a>.</li>
				<li>ESRI ArcGIS has had support for GeoPackage vector features since 2014.  See <a href="https://www.esri.com/about/newsroom/arcnews/esri-leads-in-supporting-ogc-standards/">Esri Leads in Supporting OGC Standards (2014)</a> and <a href="https://www.esri.com/arcgis-blog/products/product/data-management/how-to-use-ogc-geopackages-in-arcgis-pro/">How to Use OGC GeoPackages in ArcGIS Pro (2020)</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://ngageoint.github.io/GeoPackage/">GeoPackage Libraries</a>, made available by the U. S. National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGA).</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://www.bluemarblegeo.com/products/global-mapper-formats-raster.php#OGC_GeoPackage">Global Mapper</a> from Blue Marble Geographics.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://www.hexagongeospatial.com/products/luciad-portfolio">Luciad Portfolio</a> products from Hexagon, for example, <a href="https://www.hexagongeospatial.com/products/luciad-portfolio/luciadmobile">LuciadMobile</a>.  <a href="https://www.hexagongeospatial.com/products/power-portfolio/geomedia/geomedia-product-release-details">Hexagon GeoMedia</a> also has support for GeoPackage.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://www.envitia.com/technologies/products/maplink-pro/">MapLink Pro</a> from Envitia.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://carto.com/platform/">Carto</a> platform for developing applications based on geospatial data and analysis.  See 2018 blog post <a href="https://carto.com/blog/fgdb-gpkg/">Beyond the Shapefile with File Geodatabase and GeoPackage</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://docs.geotools.org/latest/userguide/geotools.html">GeoTools</a>, an open-source Java code library.  See <a href="http://docs.geotools.org/latest/userguide/library/data/geopackage.html">GeoPackage Plugin</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Since late 2014, TerraGo Technologies has used GeoPackage files for embedding feature data in its GeoPDF files rather than a proprietary implementation of Adobe&apos;s object data mechanism.  TerraGo Toolbar 6.6&apos;s Identify tool can display the feature attributes.  The GeoPackage file can be extracted and saved as a separate file.</p>
			<p>For providers distributing data in GeoPackage format, see  <a href="http://www.geopackage.org/data.html">GeoPackage Data</a> from the GeoPackage SWG.  As of June 2020, this page indicates that government entities in Australia, New Zealand, and the United Kingdom are using GeoPackage as a distribution format for important products.  For example, the U. K. Ordnance Survey is making a number of its OpenData products available in GeoPackage format.  See <a href="https://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/blog/2019/04/os-opendata-products-available-in-geopackage-format/">OS OpenData products now available in GeoPackage format</a> from April 2019. See also <a href="https://www.bgs.ac.uk/products/digitalmaps/dataInfo.html">BGS Geology | DiGMapGB</a>.  Layers from the <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a> are available (updated monthly) as GeoPackage files from <a href="https://download.osmdata.xyz/">https://download.osmdata.xyz/</a>.</p>
			<p>The United States Geological Survey (USGS) is beginning to make use of the GeoPackage format for distributing data, particularly for very large datasets.  In January 2018, the United States Geological Survey (USGS) National Geospatial program <a href="https://prd-wret.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/assets/palladium/production/atoms/files/NHDNewsletter_17_01_Jan18.pdf">announced</a> that it was investigating distributing spatial data in the open GeoPackage format to supplement and extend its FGDB (Esri File Geodatabase) and spatial web services deliveries.  The <a href="https://coast.noaa.gov/digitalcoast/data/inventory.html">U.S. Interagency Elevation Inventory</a> can be downloaded as a GeoPackage.  The inventory is a resource that identifies by geographic location in the United States and its territories the elevation-related data available from NOAA, U.S. Geological Survey, Federal Emergency Management Agency, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, U.S. Department of Agriculture - Natural Resources Conservation Service, U.S. Forest Service, and National Park Service.  For other examples of the use of GeoPackage for data distribution by governmental entities in the United States, see <a href="#useful">Useful References</a> below.</p>
			<p>In June 2020, the <a href="https://www.records.nsw.gov.au/recordkeeping/sustainable-file-formats">New South Wales State Archives</a> lists GeoPackage 1.0 in its list of sustainable formats.  The compilers of this resource would welcome information about other recommendations for the GeoPackage format from archival entities that collect and preserve geospatial datasets. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No apparent concerns.  SQLite, on which GeoPackage is built is a relational database software package for which source code and documentation is in the public domain.  The OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard document is made available on a royalty free,
non-discriminatory basis.  The document includes a boilerplate call for OGC to be notified of any patents that implementations of the specification might infringe.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>One intent of the GeoPackage format is to have a compact representation appropriate to use for applications on mobile devices.  Compact, binary representations of information are inherently less easy for human readers.  The .gpkg file is in the <a href="https://www.sqlite.org/fileformat.html">SQLite database file format</a>.  Open source software is available for viewing and manipulating SQLite files, for example, <a href="https://sqlitebrowser.org/">DB Browser for SQLite</a>.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>The format defines an optional table
<i>gpkg_data_columns</i>
to hold descriptions of the data field in a specified column, including: short name, title, description, and a link to descriptions of constraints (min/max, etc.) stored in a supplementary table, <i>gpkg_data_column_constraints</i>.</p>
			<p>The format also defines an optional <i>gpkg_metadata</i> table, which may contain
metadata in encodings for which MIME types exist (with a default of <i>text/xml</i>) based on any authoritative metadata
specification, such as ISO 19115, ISO 19115-2, ISO 19139, Dublin Core, CSDGM, DDMS, NMF/NMIS, etc. The GeoPackage interpretation of what constitutes <i>metadata</i> is broad. It also includes UML models encoded in XMI, GML Application Schemas, ISO 19110 feature catalogues, OWL and SKOS taxonomies, etc.  A GeoPackage that contains a <i>gpkg_metadata</i> table is required to have a <i>gpkg_metadata_reference</i> table to
associate metadata in the <i>gpkg_metadata</i> table with data in the feature, and tiles tables.  The two tables are intended to provide the
support necessary to implement the hierarchical metadata model defined in ISO 19115.  Metadata values can be associated with the entire geopackage or to a table, column, row, or table cell (row/col).</p>
			<p>In the specification for version 1.0, the tables to hold metadata were described in the main specification (clause 2.4).  Since version 1.1, this content has been described as an &quot;extension&quot; in Annex F.  The compilers of this resource are not aware of substantive changes in the structure of the tables. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None beyond software to unpack the data structures.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>The SQLite application has an extension that supports encryption.  However, the GeoPackage specification does not provide for any encryption within the package.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>Raster image tiles can be in <fddLink id="fdd000149">JPEG_DCT_BL</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink> encodings in the standard GeoPackage.</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>Limited to 8-bits per channel.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>See <fddLink id="fdd000149">JPEG_DCT_BL</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink>.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>Vector graphics and other features are supported through feature tables.  No support for vector graphics in raster tiles. See Dataset and GIS factors below.</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:multispectral>No support within a single raster image layer.</fdd:multispectral>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:datasetQF>
			<fdd:normalDataset>
				<p>Data types from SQLite supported are: boolean, tinyint (8 bits), smallint (16 bits), mediumint (32 bits), int/integer (64 bits), float (32 bits), double/real (64 bits), text (UTF-8 or UTF-16), blob, date (<i>YYYY-MM-DD</i>, stored as text), datetime (<i>YYYY-MM-DD</i>T<i>HH:MM:SSS</i>Z stored as text).  Also defined is a type for representing a geometry type, typically selected from a set defined in the standard but optionally user-defined.  The blob datatype appears to be usable in limited circumstances, either using a structure fully defined in the standard, or associated with a MIME type. </p>
			</fdd:normalDataset>
			<fdd:accessSoftware>
				<p>A package compliant with the encoding standard is intended to provide SQL access to its
contents via SQLite version 3 software APIs.</p>
			</fdd:accessSoftware>
			<fdd:dataDocumentation>
				<p>The format allows embedding of rich metadata of all types.  See Self-documentation in <a href="#sustainability">Sustainability Factors</a> above.</p>
			</fdd:dataDocumentation>
		</fdd:datasetQF>
		<fdd:gisQF>
			<fdd:normalGIS>
				<p>Each table for features or tiles must have an associated spatial reference system. If the <i>srs_id</i> column value references a geographic coordinate reference
system (CRS), then the min/max x/y values are in decimal degrees; otherwise, the srs_id
references a projected CRS and the min/max x/y values are in the units specified by that CRS.  The <i>gpkg_spatial_ref_sys</i> table in a GeoPackage is required to include a record for WGS-84.</p>
				<p>Geometry types supported in a GeoPackage include: Point,Curve, LineString, Surface, CurvePolygon, Polygon, GeometryCollection, MultiSurface, MultiPolygon, MultiCurve, MultiLineString, MultiPoint.  These are based on <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/53698.html">ISO/IEC 13249-3:11</a>, Information technology — Database languages — SQL Multimedia and application packages — Part 3: Spatial.  ISO/IEC 13249 is often referred to as SQL/MM.</p>
			</fdd:normalGIS>
			<fdd:metadataGIS>
				<p>The format allows embedding of rich metadata of all types.  See Self-documentation in <a href="#sustainability">Sustainability Factors</a> above.</p>
			</fdd:metadataGIS>
		</fdd:gisQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>gpkg</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Specified in all versions of the standard.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/geopackage+sqlite3</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Registered at IANA by OGC in 2018 for GeoPackage Version 1.2.  See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/geopackage+sqlite3">https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/geopackage+sqlite3</a>.  The compilers of this resource have not determined the degree to which this media type has been adopted and whether it is used with files in other versions of the GeoPackage Encoding Standard.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex:  53 51 4c 69 74 65 20 66 6f 72 6d 61 74 20 33 00</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII:  SQLite format 3</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>In first 16 bytes of the file. Specified in all versions of the standard.  Applies to all SQLite database files.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 47 50 4B 47</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: GKPG</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>In the <i>application_id</i> field (byte offset 68) of the SQLite database header.  Specific to GeoPackage files.  Applies to Version 1.2 and greater Version 1.0 has value &quot;GP10&quot;.  Version 1.1 has value &quot;GP11&quot;.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Indicator for profile, level, version, etc.</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>A GeoPackage contains a value in the <i>user_version</i> field of the SQLite database header to indicate its version. The value is a 5-digit integer with a one-digit major version, two-digit minor version, and two-digit bug-fix.  For example, for Version 1.2, this is 10200 (Hex: 00 00 27 D8).</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>No corresponding match as of June 2020.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>No corresponding match as of June 2020.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>The standard requires that a Geopackage satisfy two integrity checks that are optional for SQLite database files in general, but supported by SQLite PRAGMA software. The SQLite PRAGMA integrity_check SQL command must return <i>ok</i> for a
GeoPackage.  The SQLite PRAGMA foreign_key_check SQL with no parameter value must
return an empty result set indicating no invalid foreign key values.</p>
			<p>The standard defines a StandardGeoPackageBinary subformat used to record feature table geometries with or without optional
elevation (Z) and/or measure (M) values in SQL blobs.  This subformat is based on Well-Known Binary as defined in ISO/IEC 13249-3:2011 [<a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/53698.html">Information Technology -- Database languages -- SQL multimedia and application packages -- Part 3: Spatial</a>] clause 5.1.46, with the addition of an explicit encoding for an empty point set, which is not defined in ISO/IEC 13249-3.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Extensibility of GeoPackage format</b>: Clause 2.3 of the specification defines an extension mechanism using an optional <i>gpkg_extensions</i> table and provides guidance on development of extensions.  Registered extensions are documented in Annex F of the specification and include additional
geometry types, additional SQL geometry functions, and WebP as an additional tile image format.   Extensions documented in separate OGC specifications include <a href="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/is/17-066r1/17-066r1.html">OGC GeoPackage Extension for Tiled Gridded Coverage Data</a> and <a href="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/is/18-000/18-000.html">OGC GeoPackage Related Tables Extension</a>.  See <a href="https://www.geopackage.org/extensions.html">GeoPackage Extensions</a> on GeoPackage.org for a list of extensions that have been considered in testbeds or by a particular community. Examples include extensions for <a href="https://www.compusult.com/html/OGC/3DTile_GeoPackage_Ext_Draft.html">3D Tiles</a> and for <a href="https://gitlab.com/imagemattersllc/geopackage-metadata-profiles/blob/master/extensions/8-metadata-dataset-provenance.adoc">Dataset Provenance Metadata</a>. The compilers of this resource have not attempted to determine whether any of the extensions not endorsed by OGC as of June 2020 are being used in practice. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>Some history and influences on the format development are described by Even Rouault (a GDAL developer) in a 2014 <a href="http://erouault.blogspot.com/2014/12/gdal-geopackage-raster-support.html">blog post</a>.</p>
			<p>The family of GeoPackage format specifications includes several chronological versions of the core standard. </p>
			<ul>
				<li>Version 1.0 of the GeoPackage Encoding Standard was approved on January 19, 2014 and published on February 12, 2014.  A corrigendum was published in April 2015. By October 2016, versions 1.0 and 1.0.1 had been marked as deprecated.</li>
				<li>Version 1.1 (originally expected to be version 1.0.2) was published in September or October 2016.  GeoPackage 1.1 was described as a technical amendment to version 1.0.1 because a number of substantive changes altered conformance requirements.  Many changes were corrections to the Tiles portion of the specification.  Other changes were re-organization, particularly for documentation of existing extensions, for improved readability and usability.  See <a href="https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=67120">Revision Notes for OGC Implementation Standard GeoPackage v1.1</a>.</li>
				<li>Version 1.2 was published in August 2017, with a corrigendum published in September 2018 as version 1.2.1.  An important addition was the addition of support for tables of non-spatial attributes. Other changes included: updated versioning mechanism, to allow for version increments in SQLite header; and deprecation of some extensions related to user-defined geometry types because they were not sufficently definied to ensure interoperability.  See <a href="https://portal.ogc.org/files/72233">Release Notes for OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard v1.2</a> and <a href="https://portal.ogc.org/files/18-024r1">Release Notes for OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard v1.2.1</a>. </li>
				<li>Version 1.3 was <a href="https://www.ogc.org/pressroom/pressreleases/3204">available for public comment</a> in May 2020.  Described as a minor revision to the current version 1.2.1.  Substantive changes included: clarifying use of views in user-defined tables; requiring IDs for Spatial Reference Systems (SRS) to be consistent between <i>gpkg_contents</i> and the two dependent tables, <i>gpkg_geometry_columns</i> and <i>gpkg_tile_matrix_set</i>; allowing metadata scopes to be extended; loosening the restriction on user-supplied schemas for applicability to attributes and extensions; enforcing consistent encoding for empty geometries.  See <a href="https://portal.ogc.org/files/92744">Release Notes for OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard v1.3.0</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The <a href="https://geopackage.blogspot.com/">GeoPackage blog</a> provides more insight on issues concerning changes between versions.</p>
			<p>At any point, the current working version is available at <a href="https://www.geopackage.org/spec/">https://www.geopackage.org/spec/</a>.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Adopted versions of the GeoPackage Encoding Standard are accessible from <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/geopackage">https://www.ogc.org/standards/geopackage</a>.  If corrigenda have been approved, the version listed below is the corrected document.  The links to ndividual specifications are to PDF files.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/geopackage</link>
							<tag>OGC: GeoPackage Encoding Standard</tag>
							<comment>Introductory page that provides access to approved specifications and related documents.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.opengis.net/doc/IS/geopackage/1.2.1</link>
							<tag>OGC Geopackage Encoding Standard 1.2 (12-128r15) with corrigendum | Originally published 2017-08-25. Corrigendum 2018-09-06</tag>
							<comment>Alternative URL is https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/12-128r15</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.opengis.net/doc/IS/geopackage/1.1 </link>
							<tag>OGC Geopackage Encoding Standard 1.1 (12-128r12) | Published 2015-08-04</tag>
							<comment>Alternative URL: https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=64506</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=56357&amp;version=1</link>
							<tag>OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard 1.0 (12-128r1) with corrigendum</tag>
							<comment>Deprecated in 2016.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/?artifact_id=56357&amp;version=1</link>
							<tag>OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard 1.0 (12-128r1) with corrigendum</tag>
							<comment>Now deprecated.  Deprecation was noted on the OGC website between 2016-09-13 and 2016-10-07 as recorded by Internet Archive captures</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>An alternative source for the GeoPackage specifications is the separate Geopackage.org website used by the GeoPackage Standard Working Group (SWG).  The versions on this site are link-rich HTML versions.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.geopackage.org/spec121/</link>
							<tag>OGC® GeoPackage Encoding Standard (version 1.2.1 )</tag>
							<comment>Link-rich online version of latest adopted specification as of June 2020.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.geopackage.org/spec</link>
							<tag>Latest working version of the GeoPackage specification</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The GeoPackage specification depends heavily on the 2011 version of ISO/IEC 13249-3 (aka SQL/MM).</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/53698.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 13249-3:2011, Information technology -- Database languages -- SQL multimedia and application packages -- Part 3: Spatial</tag>
							<comment>GeoPackage specification depends heavily on the 2011 version of this ISO standard, often referred to as SQL/MM Spatial</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160121180513/http://jtc1sc32.org/doc/N2251-2300/32N2279-text_for_ballot-CD_13249-3.pdf</link>
							<tag>Draft text for ISO/IEC 13249-3:2011 (aka SQL/MM Part 3: Spatial)</tag>
							<comment>Link via Internet Archive</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources from or related to the OGC GeoPackage Standards Working Group (SWG)</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.geopackage.org/</link>
							<tag>GeoPackage SWG website</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ogc.org/projects/groups/geopackageswg</link>
							<tag>OGC GeoPackage SWG web page</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ogc.org/blog/3148</link>
							<tag>#GeoPackageDay 2020 - what is GeoPackage? | blog post from 12 February 2020</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://lists.opengeospatial.org/pipermail/geopackage/</link>
							<tag>OGC GeoPackage SWG mailing list archives</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.ogc.org/files/?artifact_id=91644#PartGeoPackage</link>
							<tag>GeoPackage in OGC Testbed-16 (2016) | pilot use cases</tag>
							<comment>Focus on metadata profiles and large vector datasets</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Captures of OGC web page for GeoPackage standard relating to publication of GeoPackage 1.1 and deprecation of GeoPackage 1.0.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160913223143/http://www.opengeospatial.org:80/standards/geopackage</link>
							<tag>Last capture of OGC page for GeoPackage standard before publication on OGC website of GeoPackage 1.1 and deprecation of GeoPackage 1.0 (archived by Internet Archive on September 13, 2016)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20161007210536/http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/geopackage</link>
							<tag>First capture of OGC page for GeoPackage standard after publication of GeoPackage 1.1 and deprecation of GeoPackage 1.0 (archived by Internet Archive on October 7, 2016)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to introduction of GeoPackage 1.2 and 1.2.1.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ogc.org/pressroom/pressreleases/2529</link>
							<tag>OGC seeks public comment on candidate GeoPackage 1.2 standard (February 3, 2017)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/16-126r8</link>
							<tag>Release Notes for GeoPackage v1.2</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.opengeospatial.org/files/18-024r1</link>
							<tag>Release Notes for OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard v1.2.1</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www2.unb.ca/~estef/papers/go_geomatics_stefanakis_may_2017.pdf</link>
							<tag>GeoPackage: A format with database capabilities (May 2017)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to introduction of GeoPackage 1.3:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ogc.org/pressroom/pressreleases/3204</link>
							<tag>OGC seeks public comment on Version 1.3 of GeoPackage Standard (May 5, 2020)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.ogc.org/files/92744</link>
							<tag>Release Notes for OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard v1.3.0</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources from OGC related to adoption of the GeoPackage format:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ogc.org/resource/products/byspec/?specid=872</link>
							<tag>OGC Implementations by Specification | for OGC GeoPackage Encoding Standard 1.2</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.geopackage.org/implementations.html</link>
							<tag>GeoPackage Implementations | lists software packages that implement the GeoPackage Encoding Standard</tag>
							<comment>From GeoPackage SWG.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.geopackage.org/data.html</link>
							<tag>GeoPackage Data | lists data providers that publish geospatial data in the GeoPackage format.</tag>
							<comment>From GeoPackage SWG.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>GDAL (Geospatial Data Abstraction Library) is very widely used as the basis for data input, output, and transformation in other applications.  See <a href="https://gdal.org/software_using_gdal.html#software-using-gdal">Software using GDAL</a>.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://gdal.org/drivers/vector/gpkg.html</link>
							<tag>GDAL:  GeoPackage vector driver</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://gdal.org/drivers/raster/gpkg.html</link>
							<tag>GDAL:  GeoPackage raster driver</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Esri blog posts on support for GeoPackage in Esri products</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://blogs.esri.com/esri/arcgis/2014/04/14/support-for-ogc-geopackages-in-arcgis/</link>
							<tag>Support for OGC GeoPackage specification in ArcGIS. (April 14, 2014)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.esri.com/arcgis-blog/products/arcgis-desktop/analytics/support-for-ogc-geopackage-specification-in-arcgis/</link>
							<tag>Support for OGC GeoPackage specification in ArcGIS</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to distribution of geospatial data in GeoPackage format by U. S. government entities:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://prd-wret.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/assets/palladium/production/atoms/files/NHDNewsletter_17_01_Jan18.pdf</link>
							<tag>USGS National Hydrography Dataset Newsletter, Vol. 17, No. 1, January 2018</tag>
							<comment>Introduces the possibility of &quot;GeoPackage as a Potential Non-Proprietary Dataset Download Solution&quot; for hydrography data that is often too large for a Shapefile.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/324718650_USGS_Hydrography_Data_Distribution_Formats_-_including_GeoPackage</link>
							<tag>USGS Hydrography Data Distribution Formats - including GeoPackage (April 2018)</tag>
							<comment>Slide show from April 2018 conference paper by Greg Cocks and Phil Rufe</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.usgs.gov/centers/asc/science/alaska-resource-data-file</link>
							<tag>The Alaska Resource Data File (ARDF) | available in several formats, including GeoPackage</tag>
							<comment>From USGS.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.usgs.gov/core-science-systems/ngp/3dep/3dep-national-indexing-scheme</link>
							<tag>3DEP National Indexing Scheme | available for download in several formats, including GeoPackage</tag>
							<comment>From USGS.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://coast.noaa.gov/digitalcoast/data/inventory.html</link>
							<tag>U.S. Interagency Elevation Inventory </tag>
							<comment>Aggregates elevation-related information from NOAA, U.S. Geological Survey, Federal Emergency Management Agency, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, U.S. Department of Agriculture - Natural Resources Conservation Service, U.S. Forest Service, and National Park Service.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://worldwind.arc.nasa.gov/android/tutorials/geopackage/</link>
							<tag>WorldWind Android: GeoPackage |  NASA 3D virtual globe API for Android</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SWW-iZCK48c</link>
							<tag>GeoPackage: GIS File Format of the Future? | 2019 presentation from Vermont Center for Geographic Information(VCGI)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources about announcements of the use of GeoPackage in TerraGo&apos;s GeoPDF files.  At this point, TerraGo used the term &quot;OpenGeoPDF.&quot;</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://lists.opengeospatial.org/pipermail/geopackage/2014-November/000083.html</link>
							<tag>[Geopackage] &quot;OpenGeoPDF&quot; linkage to geopackage?</tag>
							<comment>Thread on listserv from November 2014</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www10.giscafe.com/blogs/gissusan/2014/11/25/terrago-releases-opengeopdf-technology/</link>
							<tag>TerraGo releases OpenGeoPDF technology.  Nov 25, 2014</tag>
							<comment>Post by Susan Smith at GISCafe</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://mundogeo.com/en/2015/04/10/terrago-delivers-lightweight-gis-applications-from-arcmap%C2%AE-with-opengeopdf/</link>
							<tag>TerraGo Delivers Lightweight GIS Applications from ArcMap with OpenGeoPDF (October 4, 2015)</tag>
							<comment>Press release from TerraGo.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20200901203444/https://www.directionsmag.com/pressrelease/5386</link>
							<tag>New Release of TerraGo GeoPDF Unlocks Geospatial Platforms for the Masses (September 8, 2016)</tag>
							<comment>TerraGo Press Release about version 7 of the TerraGo GeoPDF software suite.  Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to early history of the GeoPackage format:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20180315111013/http://www.ogcnetwork.net:80/geopackage</link>
							<tag>Geopackage page on OGC Network site (dated January 16, 2013). Link via Internet Archive.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://erouault.blogspot.com/2014/12/gdal-geopackage-raster-support.html</link>
							<tag>GDAL GeoPackage raster support</tag>
							<comment>Post by Even Rouault, December 15, 2014</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to SQLite:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.sqlite.org/fileformat.html</link>
							<tag>The SQLite Database File Format</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.sqlite.org/src/artifact?ci=trunk&amp;filename=magic.txt</link>
							<tag>SQLite magic.txt file</tag>
							<comment>Lists registered values for SQLite application ID, including &quot;gp10&quot; for GeoPackage 1.0.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://sqlite.org/copyright.html</link>
							<tag>SQLite Copyright</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160119114216/http://www.fit.vutbr.cz/~rychly/public/docs/slides-iso-iec-13249/slides-iso-iec-13249.print.pdf</link>
							<tag>Slideshow on SQL multimedia and application packages: 
ISO/IEC 13249 SQL/MM</tag>
							<comment>By Marek Rychlý.  3rd April 2014.  Illustrates geometry types.  Link now via Internet Archive</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://doesen0.informatik.uni-leipzig.de/proceedings/paper/68.pdf</link>
							<tag>SQL/MM Spatial: The Standard to Manage Spatial Data in Relational Database Systems (2003)</tag>
							<comment>Conference Paper given by Knut Stolze at BTW 2003 in Leipzig (10th Conference on Database Systems for Business, Technology and Web)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
