<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000382" titleName="GeoJSON, Version 1.0 (2008)" shortName="GeoJSON_2008" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>dataset</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>gis</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-06-07</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Partial</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>GeoJSON, Version 1.0 (2008)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>geospatial data formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>vector image formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>georeferenced image formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>This format description is for the first version of GeoSON, published by a group of individuals in January 2008 and describing itself as GeoJSON, Version 1.0.  GeoJSON was steadily adopted and implemented and soon played an important role in many spatial database products,
web APIs, and open data platforms.  Implementers demanded formal standardization and improvements in the specification.  In 2015, an IETF (Internet Engineering Task Force) Working Group was chartered to specify the format more precisely and serve as a better guide for implementers.  See <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-geojson/">IETF Geographic JSON Working Group Charter</a>.  The working group published <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7946/">RFC 7946</a> in August 2016 as an IETF Proposed Standard.  At the same time, the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160827120507/http://geojson.org/geojson-spec.html">2008 GeoJSON specification</a> was declared obsolete. The format defined in RFC 7946, which is not yet described separately on this website, is based closely on the 2008 version, but does have a few changes aimed at more reliable interoperability.  In this description, any statement that applies only to the 2008 version, will use the name GeoJSON_2008 to make that explicit.</p>
			<p>GeoJSON is a geospatial data interchange format based on JavaScript Object Notation (<fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink>).  GeoJSON is a format for representing a variety of geographic data structures. A GeoJSON object may represent a geometry (a region of space), a feature (a spatially bounded or located entity), or a collection of features. GeoJSON supports the geometry types listed below as object types. A GeoJSON feature contains a geometry object and additional properties; a feature collection represents a list of features.</p>
			<p>A complete GeoJSON data structure is always a single JSON object consisting of a collection of name/value pairs, known as members.   The GeoJSON specification imposes additional constraints to define a GeoJSON object:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>The GeoJSON object must have a member with the name &quot;type&quot;.  The value of the type member must be one of: <i>Point</i>, <i>MultiPoint</i>, <i>LineString</i>, <i>MultiLineString</i>, <i>Polygon</i>, <i>MultiPolygon</i>, <i>GeometryCollection</i>, <i>Feature</i>, or <i>FeatureCollection</i>.</li>
				<li>A GeoJSON_2008 object may have a &quot;crs&quot; member, the value of which must be a coordinate reference system object.</li>
				<li>A GeoJSON object may have a &quot;bbox&quot; member, the value of which must be a bounding box array</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>A geospatial data interchange format based on JavaScript Object Notation (JSON). </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>A JSON-based interchange format for geospatial data, typically used during data collection or to transmit selected structured data to a system that will further manipulate the data and/or present it to end users.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000381</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>JSON</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>JSON (JavaScript Object Notation)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has extension</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>TopoJSON, describes lines and polygons in terms of shared arcs.  Not described separately on this resource at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>GeoJSON Format as specified in RFC 7946, not separately described on this website.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) includes GeoJSON as an acceptable format for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/data.html#geospatial">geospatial</a> resources.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Openly documented.  Developed by a group of individuals in 2008 and published at geojson.org.  Published as an Internet Draft in January 2014.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<ul>
				<li>Specification for Version 1.0 of <a href="https://geojson.org/geojson-spec.html">The GeoJSON Format</a> (from 2008) at geojson.org.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-butler-geojson-00.txt">The GeoGSON Format - draft-butler-geojson-00</a> (from January 2014) submitted to IETF.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The GeoJSON format was rapidly adopted for web applications involving mapping.  The GeoJSON wiki had a <a href="http://wiki.geojson.org/Users">page listing GeoJSON users</a> (last updated in 2013).  The remaining discussion of adoption here dates from 2014.  The compilers of this resource have not attempted to determine the relative adoption of the different versions of GeoJSON.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>GeoJSON was used for defining geographic coverage for apps that used Apple&apos;s MapKit, starting with iOS 7 (released in September 2013).  See instructions for <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/archive/documentation/UserExperience/Conceptual/LocationAwarenessPG/ProvidingDirections/ProvidingDirections.html">Providing Directions</a> in OS X v10.9 and iOS 7.0.  The GeoJSON_2008 format was used by the Maps app and the App
Store, to look up apps on the App Store that are capable of
providing directions in a target region.  See <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/archive/documentation/UserExperience/Conceptual/LocationAwarenessPG/ProvidingDirections/ProvidingDirections.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40009497-CH8-SW1">Declaring the Supported Geographic Coverage for Directions</a>.</p>
			<p>Although ESRI supports a more complex JSON-based format in its GeoServices REST Specification, various open source projects, including projects by ESRI are developing conversion tools.  See <a href="#useful">Useful References</a> below.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No licensing concerns.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>GeoJSON is based on text using UNICODE and uses a very simple structure.  The names used for object types defined in the specification are common English words.  GeoJSON is easy for humans to read and write and for machines to parse and generate.  UTF-8 is most commonly used, but UTF-16 and UTF-32 are also permitted.</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>See <fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:datasetQF>
			<fdd:normalDataset>
				<p>GeoJSON is based on <fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink> and inherits the same limitations.</p>
				<p>JSON is intended for data interchange and does not employ strong data-typing for numbers or have explicit support for dates.  All data is represented as text, with numbers being in base 10 as sequences of digits (including the common exponent notation to express very small or very large numbers).  JSON is not appropriate for applications requiring
binary data.  Boolean values <i>true</i> and <i>false</i> are allowed as values.  There is minimal support for coding missing data, using the <i>null</i> value.</p>
			</fdd:normalDataset>
			<fdd:accessSoftware>GeoJSON is sufficiently simple that support for reading or writing it has been integrated into almost every GIS system or tool used for applications on the Web.</fdd:accessSoftware>
			<fdd:dataDocumentation>GeoJSON has no built-in support for embedding rich metadata about the dataset as a whole.  The Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) has developed a standard encoding for metadata based on the OGC&apos;s Earth Observation Metadata Profile of Observations and Measurements.  See <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/eo-geojson">https://www.ogc.org/standards/eo-geojson</a>.</fdd:dataDocumentation>
			<fdd:beyondDataset>None.</fdd:beyondDataset>
		</fdd:datasetQF>
		<fdd:gisQF>
			<fdd:normalGIS>
				<p>The purpose of GeoJSON is to support map generation by providing georeferencing information for features through geospatial positions, and geometry objects constructed from positions.  Positions are represented in longitude, latitude, and, optionally altitude, as decimal numbers.  The default (strongly recommended but not required in GeoJSON_2008) Coordinate Reference System is WGS84, but alternative systems can be specified.  The recommended nomenclature for CRS systems is to use OGC (Open Geospatial Consortium) URNs, for example urn:ogc:def:crs:OGC::CRS84 (for WGS84).  EPSG identifiers, originally from the European Petroleum Survey Group and now maintained by the International Association of Oil and Gas Producers (OGP) can also be used.  Alternatively, the parameters for a CRS can be linked to by URL.</p>
			</fdd:normalGIS>
			<fdd:metadataGIS>There are no special provisions within GeoJSON for representing richer GIS metadata as defined by FGDC or ISO 19115.</fdd:metadataGIS>
		</fdd:gisQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>json</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20131019221208/https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GeoJSON">Wikipedia entry for GeoJSON as of October 19, 2013</a> indicated that the file extension used for JSON was used for GeoJSON. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/json</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20131019221208/https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GeoJSON">Wikipedia entry for GeoJSON as of October 19, 2013</a> indicated that the MIME type registered with IANA for JSON was used for GeoJSON.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM has no entry for GeoJSON as of May 2020</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata has no Title ID specific to GeoJSON_2008.  See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q5533904">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q5533904</a> for Wikidata information for GeoJSON in general.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes/>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://geojson.org/geojson-spec.html</link>
					<tag>The GeoJSON Format Specification, Version 1.0 (now declared obsolete)</tag>
					<comment>Dated 16 June 2008</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-butler-geojson-00.txt</link>
					<tag>Equivalent specification for GeoJSON Format published as Internet Draft, January 8, 2014</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://geojson.org/</link>
					<tag>Home page for GeoJSON format</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GeoJSON</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for GeoJSON</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://gdal.org/drivers/vector/geojson.html</link>
					<tag>GeoJSON Driver information from GDAL</tag>
					<comment>Implementation based on GeoJSON Version 1.0 (GeoJSON_2008)</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://developer.apple.com/library/archive/documentation/UserExperience/Conceptual/LocationAwarenessPG/ProvidingDirections/ProvidingDirections.html</link>
					<tag>Providing Directions (in Apple&apos;s iOS, for location-aware applications)</tag>
					<comment>GeoJSON is used for defining geographic coverage of Apps in Apple&apos;s iTunes catalog.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TopoJSON</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for TopoJSON</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/Esri/geojson-utils</link>
					<tag>GeoJSON Utils</tag>
					<comment>Scripts and utilities for converting between GeoJSON and Esri JSON.  Deprecated in 2016 in favor of new utilities.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://terraformer-js.github.io/arcgis-parser/</link>
					<tag>ArcGIS JSON Parser</tag>
					<comment>A plugin that handles 2-way conversion between GeoJSON and the JSON-based geometry format used by Esri in its GeoServices REST specification.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://blog.geomusings.com/2013/06/10/geojson-from-arcgis-server/</link>
					<tag>GeoJSON From ArcGIS Server</tag>
					<comment>Blog posting from June 2013, that describes a server extension to ArcGIS to support GeoJSON retrieval from the server. </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Captures of GeoJSON version 1.0 (dated June 16, 2008) from geojson.org.  </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080704015108/http://geojson.org:80/geojson-spec.html</link>
							<tag>The GeoJSON Format Specification on geojson.org as of July 4, 2008</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160820215743/http://geojson.org:80/geojson-spec.html</link>
							<tag>The GeoJSON Format Specification on geojson.org as of August 20, 2016 </tag>
							<comment>Shortly after publication of RFC 7946.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160827120507/http://geojson.org:80/geojson-spec.html</link>
							<tag>The GeoJSON Format Specification on geojson.org as of August 27, 2016 | Declared obsolete</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>On January 8, 2014, an Internet Draft with the GeoJSON specification was released. This document was equivalent to the specification published as Version 1.0 of GeoJSON (dated June 16, 2008) at geojson.org but used IETF style and conventions. In October 2015, an IETF working group was chartered to turn the initial draft into an RFC.  RFC 7946 was published in August 2016.  As of May 2020, this is still the latest published edition.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc7946/</link>
							<tag>The GeoJSON Format (RFC 7946) | published as Proposed Standard in August 2016</tag>
							<comment>Includes complete Internet Draft and RFC history.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/charter-ietf-geojson/</link>
							<tag>IETF Geographic JSON WG Charter (October 14, 2015)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-butler-geojson-00.txt</link>
							<tag>The GeoJSON Format (Internet Draft, January 8, 2014)</tag>
							<comment>First draft of GeoJSON specification at IETF.  Equivalent to specification published as Version 1.0 of GeoJSON (dated June 16, 2008) at geojson.org but using IETF style and conventions.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q5533904</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q5533904</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about GeoJSON, no version declared. Wikidata Title ID: Q5533904</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
