<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000456" titleName="AOL Personal Filing Cabinet" shortName="PFC" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>database</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>email</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2018-11-18</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>AOL Personal Filing Cabinet</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>America Online's (AOL) Personal Filing Cabinet or PFC is a proprietary database file that stores data from the AOL Desktop Software application to a local user-defined location for offline use. Stored data in PFC files can include stored email messages from AOL Mail (but not attachments to email), Internet bookmarks or Favorites, Away Messages, Newsgroup Postings and preferences such as user language and other configuration data. Because email attachments are not stored along with the message and instead are stored as 64-bit encoding, they can not be opened manually.</p>
			<p>Each Username or AOL account has its own PFC file in the Organize folder.  Because the file storage is local to the computer and to the Username, the stored files are not accessible if using a different computer, signing into a different account or signing in as a guest on the local computer. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160603061516/https://help.aol.com/articles/Personal-Filing-Cabinet-USF2127">AOL Version 9</a> introduced the option to save email to AOL servers instead of &quot;Save to My PC&quot; which would provide access when signing in from another computer or as a guest from the local computer.  Nonetheless, users often export their PFC data out of AOL to other platforms to improve accessibility and usability. </p>
			<p>There is no published specification for PFC files; informal documentation comes from work done by Franz v. Gordon in 2002 through a reverse-engineering process and now available through the <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20070827223915/http://members.aol.com/fvongordon/pfc/PFC-Details.zip">Internet Archive</a>. <a href="http://xi6.com/hacks/aolmacfc.html">Bruce Tomlin</a> created partial documentation for the MacOS version of PFC which differs from the Windows version explored by Gordon. This document focuses on the Windows version. According to Gordon, PFC database files start with a header that includes the magic number file signifier, followed by an index table that contains pointers to all the data within the PFC.  Each line in the index table starts with 52 53 00 00 (“RS”) and describes, among other values, the content type of the stored data object to which it’s pointing.  The data could be a folder (including a system folder) or other coded values to identify the content type as a Favorite (bookmarked URL), a file that&apos;s been prepared for download or completely downloaded, email messages written or received, address book, email signature or availability status information (&quot;Buddy away&quot;,&quot;Buddy preferences&quot; and &quot;Buddy icons&quot;). Email messages are prefaced with 52 53 5c 30 5c 30 (“RS\0\0”) and then split into several subrecords starting with &quot;AOLH&quot; and ending with &quot;AOLF&quot;. These subrecords include fields for the date/time, to, cc, bcc, subject, reply to, recipient, date/time as well as a flag to indicate if the message originated from inside or outside AOL. 
Other flag (at offset 0x16) indicates if the email message read (value 0), has an attachment (value 1), self written (value 2) and if the message has an embedded picture (value 3). Since they are not stored with the message, the name (which cannot include special characters) and length of <a href="https://help.aol.com/articles/Send-and-download-attachments-in-AOL-Mail">attachments</a> are recorded along with its stored location which varies for each browser. AOL 8.0 or 9.0 introduced a new option to send an email message as plain text so a value was added to the PFC to indicate text formatting preference as <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML</fddLink> or plain text. Content types other than email have different specific sets of relevant fields in the index tables.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>America Online's (AOL) Personal Filing Cabinet or PFC is a database file that stores data such as email messages, contacts, web bookmarks or favorites, as well as user preferences and configuration data from the AOL Desktop Software application on the user's local computer. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Archived middle state.</fdd:productionPhase>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Manuscripts Division at the Library of Congress has received PFC files with personal papers collections that included AOL email data.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress has not yet expressed any format preference for email collections in its <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/">Recommended Formats Statement</a>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Format is closed and proprietary.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>There is no available specification document from AOL. Franz V. Gordon in 2002 reverse-engineered <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20070827223915/http://members.aol.com/fvongordon/pfc/PFC-Details.zip">informal documentation</a> about the technical structure of the format. </fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Highly adopted thanks to the AOL Desktop market share. According to the <a href="https://www.comscore.com/Insights/Market-Rankings/comScore-Ranks-the-Top-50-US-Digital-Media-Properties-for-October-2015">Comscore Media Metrix Multi-Platform</a>, AOL had 174,791	million monthly users in 2015.  Because of the reliance on access to local data store, users often export PFC files to other formats including <fddLink id="fdd000383">MBOX</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000388">EML</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000378">PST</fddLink>. Software tools such as <a href="https://weirdkid.com/emailchemy/">Emailchemy</a> can migrate PFC files to other email formats.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>PFC files are intended for use only with AOL Desktop software. The compilers of this resource have not identified specific patents related to this software&apos;s functionality but assume that AOL does have patents that would prevent replication of the full functionality of the software. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>According to <a href="https://www.digital-detective.net/recovery-of-aol-pfc-personal-filing-cabinet-email-messages/">Wilson</a>, email messages from AOL version 7.00 and later are compressed via <a href="https://zlib.net/">zlib</a>, a lossless data-compression library. This inhibits keyword searching because the data needs to be decompressed before such actions. The PFC file itself is binary and therefore not human readable. Email attachments are stored as 64-bit encoding.   </fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>PFC files are highly structured thanks to the index table which points to the address location of all data in both open and closed folders. </fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>Active use of the PFC format requires the AOL Desktop application. However a number of PFC viewer tools exist including <a href="https://github.com/ernieyu/pfcviewer">pfcviewer</a> and <a href="https://www.systoolsgroup.com/aol-pfc-viewer/">SysTools AOL PFC Viewer</a>.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>
			<p>According to <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20050420101922/http://members.aol.com/fvongordon/pfc/documentation.htm">Gordon</a>, email messages received with AOL 7.0 are stored in the PFC in encrypted form.</p>
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors/>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>pfc</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>According to <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20050420101922/http://members.aol.com/fvongordon/pfc/documentation.htm">Gordon</a>, the .pfc extension may be used for &quot;formerly stored folders&quot; which the writers of this resource take to mean older versions of the PFC file. Most resources however report that it is more common for the PFC file not to have any extension. <a href="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.  </fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>Each Username has its own PFC file in the Organize folder and the filename is the Username with no extension. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 41 4F 4C 56 4D 31 30 30</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: AOLVM100</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html">Gary Kessler&apos;s Signature File Table</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>No PUID as of November 2018.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q25110402</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q25110402">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q25110402</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>In November 2018, <a href="https://help.aol.com/articles/Send-and-download-attachments-in-AOL-Mail">AOL</a> stated that there&apos;s a total file size limit of 25MB per email, which includes both incoming and outgoing messages as well as attachments. </fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>According to <a href="https://www.brighthub.com/office/collaboration/articles/4107.aspx">Bright Hub</a>, the first release of AOL for DOS was February 1991 and by 1993, AOL introduced its own email addresses and a Windows version. Other milestone releases include AOL 2.0 for Windows 3.x in September 1994, AOL 3.0 for Windows 95 in June 1996,
AOL 6.0 for Windows XP in September 2001, AOL 9.0 for Vista November 2006, and AOL 10.0 (AOL Desktop) in December 2007. <a href="https://linustechtips.com/main/topic/751011-aol-desktop-software-to-end-free-access-plan/">AOL Gold</a> debuted on April 10th, 2017 which includes new features including two step authentication, encryption of personal information stored in AOL Desktop software, server side storage of favorites as well as contacts and automatic updating of the software. AOL 10.0 for Mac was released in May 2008. The first recorded use of PFCs are in <a href="https://linustechtips.com/main/topic/751011-aol-desktop-software-to-end-free-access-plan/">AOL 3.0</a> from 1996 but PFC may go back even earlier. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>. </fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20070827223915/http://members.aol.com/fvongordon/pfc/PFC-Details.zip</link>
					<tag>File Format of the PFC by Franz V. Gordon available through the Internet Archive</tag>
					<comment>Informal documentation about the structure of the PFC format</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q25110402</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q25110402</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about PFC. Wikidata Title ID: Q25110402.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://fileformats.archiveteam.org/wiki/AOL_Personal_Filing_Cabinet</link>
					<tag>AOL Personal Filing Cabinet entry from Just Solve the Format Problem</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://astroblahhh.com/software/tips/aol-pfc-files-and-how-to-convert-them-for-free.shtml </link>
					<tag>America Online Personal Filing Cabinet (PFC) Files
and How to Convert Them For Free </tag>
					<comment>Helpful discussions on exporting PFC files to other formats. Last updated Oct. 1, 2014.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20050420101922/http://members.aol.com/fvongordon/pfc/documentation.htm</link>
					<tag>Some documentation about Export PFC. Link via Internet Archive</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://xi6.com/hacks/aolmacfc.html </link>
					<tag>AOL Mac File Cabinet format by Bruce Tomlin, 2004</tag>
					<comment>Partial documentation of PFC format for MacOS version of AOL</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_Filing_Cabinet</link>
					<tag>Personal Filing Cabinet</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikipedia about PFC.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.digital-detective.net/recovery-of-aol-pfc-personal-filing-cabinet-email-messages/</link>
					<tag>Recovery of AOL PFC (Personal Filing Cabinet) Email Messages</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html</link>
					<tag>Gary Kessler&apos;s Signature File Table</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://file-extension.net/info/pfc-aol-preferences-personal-filing-cabinet-file.html</link>
					<tag>File Extension: PFC</tag>
					<comment>Includes sample hex dump of PFC header detail</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.forensicswiki.org/wiki/AOL_PFC</link>
					<tag>AOL PFC from Forensics Wiki</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160603061516/https://help.aol.com/articles/Personal-Filing-Cabinet-USF2127</link>
					<tag>Personal Filing Cabinet, AOL 9.0. Available from Internet Archive.</tag>
					<comment/>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20051226070800/http://members.aol.com:80/fvongordon/pfc/</link>
					<tag>Introduction to the Project Personal Filing Cabinet Converter by Franz V. Gordon available through Internet Archive</tag>
					<comment>Includes mention of the option to send mail as HTML or plain text.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.comscore.com/Insights/Market-Rankings/comScore-Ranks-the-Top-50-US-Digital-Media-Properties-for-October-2015</link>
					<tag>Comscore Ranks the Top 50 U.S. Digital Media Properties for October 2015</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://zlib.net/</link>
					<tag>Homepage for zlib open source compression library</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://help.aol.com/articles/Send-and-download-attachments-in-AOL-Mail</link>
					<tag>Send and download attachments in AOL Mail from AOL Help, updated November 13, 2018</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.brighthub.com/office/collaboration/articles/4107.aspx</link>
					<tag>Brief History of AOL and its Instant Messenger Program by Bright Hub</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://linustechtips.com/main/topic/751011-aol-desktop-software-to-end-free-access-plan/</link>
					<tag>AOL Desktop Software to end free access plan from linustechtip forum</tag>
					<comment>Discussion about roll out of AOL Gold from March 12, 2017</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://weirdkid.com/emailchemy/</link>
					<tag>Emailchemy, software tool to convert email formats</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
