<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000476" titleName="HyperText Markup Language (HTML), versions prior to 2.0" shortName="HTML_early" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2018-02-02</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>HyperText Markup Language (HTML), versions prior to 2.0</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>markup languages</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Hypertext Markup Language (HTML) is the standard markup language for creating web pages and web applications. This format description applies to early HTML files, created before the adoption of the first formal specification for HTML, published in November 1995 as <a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1866.txt">IETF RFC 1866: HTML 2.0</a>.  See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink> for a description that provides context for the entire family of HTML formats and <fddLink id="fdd000477">HTML_2_0</fddLink> for a description for HTML 2.0</p>
			<p>HTML was originally developed at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CERN">CERN</a> (Conseil Européen pour la Recherche Nucléaire; European Organization for Nuclear Research) by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee">Tim Berners-Lee</a> around 1990.  In 1989, Berners-Lee wrote a <a href="https://www.w3.org/History/1989/proposal.html">proposal</a> to his boss.  It was &quot;an attempt to persuade CERN management that a global hypertext system was in CERN&apos;s interests.&quot; He was given the go-ahead and started to build what became the World Wide Web.  HTML, as a syntax for marking up online documents, was a key component of the World Wide Web.  A statement about <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/Future.html">HTML directions</a> (from CERN, around 1992) stated, &quot;The HTML language has been in use in the field since 1990.&quot;  Between 1992 and 1995, Berners-Lee and <a href="https://www.w3.org/People/Connolly/">Dan Connolly</a> published several drafts of documentation for HTML.  Initial specifications were distributed on the <a href="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-talk/">www-talk</a> mailing list and on the incipient World Wide Web at CERN (see <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/TheProject.html">World Wide Web: The Project</a> from December 1992).   In mid-1993, a specification for the &quot;Hypertext Markup Language (HTML)&quot; was <a href="https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/draft-ietf-iiir-html-01.txt">published as an IETF (Internet Engineering Task Force) Internet Draft</a>. In 1994, the IETF formed an HTML Working Group, which issued several updates to the HTML Internet Draft.  See <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/wg/html/">Status pages for HTML Working Group</a> from the IETF.</p>
			<p>The original HTML was based on <fddLink id="fdd000465">SGML</fddLink> (ISO 8879:1986, Standard Generalized Markup Language), an international standard for a system-independent approach for marking up text into structural units such as paragraphs, headings, and list items.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below on SGML as the basis for HTML.  One innovative aspect of HTML was support for hypertext, by using the &lt;A&gt; (anchor) element with the HREF attribute to link to other resources.</p>
			<p>HTML documents are plain text documents.  Early HTML files typically began with an &lt;HTML&gt; tag and were encoded as 7-bit <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII">ASCII</a> or its 8-bit extension <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO/IEC_8859-1">ISO/IEC 8859-1</a>, also known as ISO Latin-1.   A list of <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/Tags.html">HTML Tags</a> from 1992 shows some tags (i.e., elements) that are still used today and others that have been dropped.  For example, the &lt;NEXTID&gt; tag was specific to the Next computer and was already deprecated in the 1995 HTML 2.0 specification.  The &lt;ISINDEX&gt; tag was deprecated in HTML 4.01, and is no longer supported by browsers.  The &lt;HEAD&gt; section was apparently not used in 1992 to wrap the elements &lt;TITLE&gt;, &lt;LINK&gt;, etc., but was included in the <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-iiir-html-00">first Internet Draft for an HTML specification (June 1993)</a>.  The 1993 draft also introduced the use of a DOCTYPE declaration, with the aim of making an HTML document a valid SGML document.  For a more specific proposal for the DOCTYPE declaration, see <a href="https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/html-spec/html-direction.html">Towards Closure on HTML (1994)</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>primary markup language used for creating pages and applications on the World Wide Web.  Originating in the early 1990s, several versions were described and used for creating Web pages prior to the formally documented HTML 2.0 (published in November 1995 as RFC 1866 by IETF).</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>The primary use of HTML is as a final-state format for web pages made available on the Internet. Early HTML files were often created directly in a text editor.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000475</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HTML_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>HTML File Format Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000477</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HTML_2_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 2.0</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000465</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>SGML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Standard Generalized Markup Language (SGML). ISO 8879:1986</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Early versions of HTML were defined by an SGML DTD (Document Type Definition).</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>HTML has been an openly documented specification since its origin in the early 1990s. Initially it was developed and documented at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CERN">CERN</a> and via the <a href="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-talk/">www-talk</a> mailing list.</p>
			<p>In 1994, the Internet Engineering Task Force formed an HTML working group, which published several Internet Drafts of a specification for HTML. In November 1995, the first formal standard for HTML was published by the IETF as &quot;RFC 1866: Hypertext Markup Language - 2.0.&quot;  See <fddLink id="fdd000477">HTML_2_0</fddLink> for a description of HTML 2.0.</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>Dan Connolly distributed an SGML DTD for HTML in <a href="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-talk/1992JulAug/0020.html">a July 15, 1992 message on the www-talk mailing list</a>.  This linked to an informal description of <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/Tags.html">HTML tags (i.e., elements) used at that time</a>, part of more extensive early documentation on <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/MarkUp.html">HTML</a> from CERN. From 1993 through 1995, Berners-Lee and Connolly wrote a sequence of Internet Drafts.  See <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/wg/html/">IETF HTML WG Status Pages</a> and <a href="#specs">Format Specifications</a> below.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>Between 1990 and 1992, the copyright in documentation at CERN for HTML and other aspects of the World Wide Web was <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/Copyright.html">claimed by CERN</a>, but made available on the following terms that encouraged use: &quot;The information (of all forms) in these directories is the intellectual property of the European Particle Physics Laboratory (known as CERN). It is freely available for non-commercial use in collaborating non-military academic institutes. Commercial organisations wishing to use this code should apply to CERN for conditions. Any modifications, improvements or extensions made to this code, or ports to other systems, must be made available under the same terms.&quot;</p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://home.cern/topics/birth-web">The Birth of the Web</a>, from CERN, states, &quot;On 30 April 1993 CERN put the World Wide Web software in the public domain. CERN made the next release available with an open licence, as a more sure way to maximise its dissemination.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>All HTML files can be opened and viewed in text editors.  Since early HTML files do not include style markup (e.g., in <fddLink id="fdd000482">CSS</fddLink>) or scripts (e.g., Javascript), their contents are easily read and understood using a plain text editor.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>The earliest versions of HTML documentation did not include a mechanism for embedding metadata in a web page.  The &lt;META&gt; element was included in a 1994 <a href="https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/htmlplus_paper/htmlplus.dtd">Document Type Definition for the HyperText Markup Language Plus</a> from Dave Raggett.  This allowed the inclusion of name/value pairs in the &lt;HEAD&gt; section of an HTML document.  A primary purpose was to support indexing of documents on a server.  By mid-1995, a <a href="https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/html-spec/html-spec.txt">draft specification for HTML 2.0</a> described two main functions for  &quot;meta-information&quot;: to provide a means to discover that the data set exists
 and how it might be obtained or accessed; and
to document the content, quality, and features of a data set, indicating its fitness for use.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>Early HTML documents were encoded as plain text, either in 7-bit <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII">ASCII</a> or or its 8-bit extension <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO/IEC_8859-1">ISO/IEC 8859-1</a>.  All other characters could be incorporated by using SGML-style entities. For other textual characteristics of HTML documents, see <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>Semantic tags for paragraphs, up to six heading levels, and list structures of several types have been part of HTML since the earliest use of the markup language. See <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/Tags.html">HTML Tags</a> (from 1992).</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>Preserving particular aspects of layout was not an intent of the original HTML.  The focus was on making the textual content and semantic structure of a resource conveniently readable on different devices.</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>Dave Raggett&apos;s 1994 <a href="https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/HTMLPlus/htmlplus_45.html">Proposal for Mathematical Equations</a> in HTML+, stated, &quot;Currently, the best way of including equations in HTML documents is to first write the document in LaTeX and then use the latex2html filter to create the corresponding HTML document, together with the equations as a number of bitmap files.&quot;  His proposal for mathematical markup was not incorporated into HTML 2.0. See also <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>HTML was developed specifically to support linking among online resources.</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM does not have an entry and signature specifically for the early HTML versions, but does have fmt/96 for &quot;generic&quot; HTML, identified by an opening &lt;HTML&gt; tag and closing &lt;/BODY&gt; and &lt;/HTML&gt; tags.  This matches HTML documents which pre-date the first formal specification (HTML 2.0), or which otherwise to do not fully conform to any formal specifications.  See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/96">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/96</a>.  PUID: fmt/96</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata does not include a Title ID specifically for the HTML file format prior to HTML 2.0.  The <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q8811">Wikipedia Title ID Q881</a> is used for the HTML File Format Family.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>SGML as Basis for HTML</b>:  In his 1998 <a href="https://www.w3.org/People/Raggett/book4/ch02.html">&quot;A History of HTML,&quot;</a> Dave Raggett, wrote, &quot;The HTML that Tim invented was strongly based on SGML (Standard Generalized Mark-up Language), an internationally agreed upon method for marking up text into structural units such as paragraphs, headings, list items and so on. SGML could be implemented on any machine. The idea was that the language was independent of the formatter (the browser or other viewing software) which actually displayed the text on the screen. The use of pairs of tags such as &lt;TITLE&gt; and &lt;/TITLE&gt; to enclose an element&apos;s content is taken directly from SGML, which does exactly the same. The SGML elements used in Tim&apos;s HTML included P (paragraph); H1 through H6 (heading level 1 through heading level 6); OL (ordered lists); UL (unordered lists); LI (list items) and various others. What SGML does not include, of course, are hypertext links: the idea of using the anchor element with the HREF attribute was purely Tim&apos;s invention, as was the now-famous `www.name.name&apos; format for addressing machines on the Web.<br/>Basing HTML on SGML was a brilliant idea: other people would have invented their own language from scratch but this might have been much less reliable, as well as less acceptable to the rest of the Internet community. Certainly the simplicity of HTML, and the use of the anchor element A for creating hypertext links, was what made Tim&apos;s invention so useful.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>HTML was developed as a primary technological component of a distributed information environment, <a href="https://www.w3.org/History/1989/proposal.html">first proposed</a> to CERN management by Tim Berners-Lee in 1989.  According to <a href="http://info.cern.ch/Proposal.html">a CERN page about the proposal</a>, ‘Vague, but exciting’, were the words that his boss wrote on the proposal, allowing Berners-Lee to continue developing what became the World Wide Web.</p>
			<p>Tim Berners-Lee began work on his ideas for the World Wide Web around 1990 and started the <a href="https://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-talk/">WWW-talk mailing list</a> in September 1991. An <a href="http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/Tags.html">early public description of HTML tags (i.e., elements)</a> was published on the Web in 1992.</p>
			<p>Following a period of informal development, the first formal standard for the HTML format was version 2.0, published as <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1866">RFC 1866</a> in November 1995 by the IETF (Internet Engineering Task Force).  The authors were Tim Berners-Lee and Dan Connolly.  The RFC indicates,&quot;This specification roughly corresponds to the
capabilities of HTML in common use prior to June 1994.&quot;  See <fddLink id="fdd000477">HTML_2_0</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The earliest documentation on HTML was not in the form of a formal specification. </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/MarkUp.html</link>
							<tag>HTML | from CERN</tag>
							<comment>From around 1992.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/History/19921103-hypertext/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/MarkUp.html</link>
							<tag>W3C | Copies of pages originally mounted at CERN.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Some specifications for HTML were published as Internet Drafts through the IETF.  These included:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-iiir-html-00</link>
							<tag>Internet Draft (June 1993) | Hypertext Markup Language (HTML): A Representation of Textual Information and MetaInformation
for Retrieval and Interchange</tag>
							<comment>Described as &quot;version 1.1 of this specification.&quot;  Also available at https://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-ietf-iiir-html-00.txt</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-html-spec-05</link>
							<tag>Internet Draft (September 1995) | Hypertext Markup Language - 2.0</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>SGML DTDs defining early proposals for HTML</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/HTMLPlus/htmlplus_58.html</link>
							<tag>HTML+ DTD | Appendix I from Dave Raggett&apos;s 1993 proposal for HTML+ </tag>
							<comment>Does not include META tag.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/htmlplus_paper/htmlplus.dtd</link>
							<tag>HTML+ DTD | By Dave Raggett (1994)</tag>
							<comment>Includes META tag.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/html-spec/html.dtd</link>
							<tag>HTML DTD | By Dan Connolly (September 1995)</tag>
							<comment>Identified as version 1.3.  Clearly intended to correspond to HTML 2.0 (approved in November 1995)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for HTML</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/History.html</link>
					<tag>1991 timeline from CERN on hypertext projects and developments</tag>
					<comment>The development of the World Wide Web and HTML was influenced by earlier experiments with hypertext</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/HTMLPlus/htmlplus_1.html</link>
					<tag>HTML+ (Hypertext markup format).  Dave Raggett.  November 1993</tag>
					<comment>1993 discussion paper on HTML and proposals for developments.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://info.cern.ch/hypertext/WWW/MarkUp/Future.html</link>
					<tag>HTML directions (December 1992)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://tools.ietf.org/wg/html/</link>
					<tag>Status Pages for HyperText Markup Language Working Group</tag>
					<comment>Working Group was active between 1994 and 1996.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://tools.ietf.org/wg/html/draft-ietf-html-spec/rfc1866-from-05.diff.html</link>
					<tag>Differences between published RFC 1866 for HTML 2.0 and previous draft, draft-ietf-html-spec-05.txt (August 8, 1995)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1866</link>
					<tag>IETF RFC 1866 | Hypertext Markup Language - 2.0.   November 1995 (multiformat view)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1866.txt</link>
					<tag>IETF RFC 1866 | Hypertext Markup Language - 2.0.   November 1995 (plain text view)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/</link>
					<tag>W3C | Tim Berners-Lee</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/History/1989/proposal.html</link>
					<tag>Original proposal by Tim Berners-Lee for what became the World Wide Web.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/History/1992/ENRAP/Article_9202.pdf</link>
					<tag>World-Wide Web: The Information Universe (1992)</tag>
					<comment>By Tim Berners-Lee, Robert Cailliau, Jean-François Groff, and Bernd Pollermann (CERN)</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/History.html</link>
					<tag>A Little History of the World Wide Web (1945 to 1995)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The W3C tenth anniversary celebration provided some historical context for the development of HTML</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/2004/Talks/Styles/w3c10/images/timeline.pdf</link>
							<tag>A timeline graphic (1979-2004)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/2004/Talks/w3c10-HowItAllStarted/</link>
							<tag>How It All Started | slideshow from W3C 10th Anniversary Celebration (2004)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/People/Raggett/</link>
					<tag>W3C | Dave Raggett</tag>
					<comment>Dave Raggett was heavily involved in the development of HTML, starting in 1990</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/People/Raggett/book4/ch02.html</link>
					<tag>A History of HTML.  By Dave Raggett.  1998</tag>
					<comment>Chapter 2 of &quot;Raggett on HTML 4&quot;.  Addison Wesley Longman 1998. ISBN 0-201-17805-2</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/People/Connolly/</link>
					<tag>W3C | Dan Connolly</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/html-spec/html-direction.html</link>
					<tag>Toward Closure on HTML.  Dan Connolly.  1994</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://home.cern/topics/birth-web</link>
					<tag>The Birth of the Web | from CERN</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/96</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/96</tag>
					<comment>HTML, pre 2.0.  Identified by opening &lt;HTML&gt; tag and closing &lt;/BODY&gt;&lt;/HTML&gt; tags. PUID: fmt/96</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q8811</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q8811</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about HTML.  Wikidata Title ID: Q8811.  Links to entries for chronological versions.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See also <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
