<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000388" titleName="Email (Electronic Mail Format)" shortName="EML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>email</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2024-12-18</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Email (Electronic Mail Format)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>email formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>text formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>EML, short for electronic mail or email, is a file extension for an email message saved to a file in the <fddLink id="fdd000393">Internet Message Format</fddLink> protocol for electronic mail messages. It is the standard format used by Microsoft Outlook Express as well as some other email programs. Since EML files are created to comply with industry standard RFC 5322, EML files can be used with most email clients, servers and applications. See  <fddLink id="fdd000393">IMF</fddLink> for a description of the message syntax.</p>
			<p>EML files typically store each message as a single file (unlike <fddLink id="fdd000383">MBOX</fddLink> which concatenates all the messages from a folder into one file), and attachments may either be included as MIME content in the message or written off as a separate file, referenced from a marker in the EML file.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>EML is the file extension of the Outlook Express Saved Mail Messages files. It belongs to the Microsoft&apos;s family of email management programs and it is used for emails saving and forwarding purposes. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Used for content in initial (by message authors), middle (by archives) or final state (by message recipients/other end users). </fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000393</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>IMF</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Internet Mail Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has modified version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000615</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EMLX</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Apple Mail Email Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>EMLX is very closely related, technically, to EML format.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress includes EML files in its collections, especially in the Manuscripts and Music Divisions as well as other personal papers repositories.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) lists EML as an acceptable format for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/email.html">Email: For individual messages</a>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Partially documented through RFC 5322 but documentation about EML specifically is not readily available. <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>There is no known specification that defines EML as a file format to store email messages on a file system although it is commonly considered to be an extension of <fddLink id="fdd000393">IMF</fddLink> as defined in RFC 5322. </fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Besides the Microsoft Outlook Express, EML files can be opened using most email clients, such as Microsoft Outlook, Microsoft Entourage, Mozilla Thunderbird, Apple Mail, or IncrediMail. Since EML files are plain text and formatted much like MHT (MIME HTML) files, they can also be opened directly in the Internet Explorer, Mozilla Firefox and Opera, by first changing the file extension from .eml to .mht. It is also possible to view EML files using notepad or any other text editor. </p>
			<p>Windows 8, however, does not natively support EML in the built in Mail application so an <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/p/eml-reader/9nblggh5k5vp?activetab=pivot:overviewtab">EML Reader</a> was developed in order to support reading EML files.</p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://www.dpconline.org/docs/technology-watch-reports/739-dpctw11-01-pdf/file">Prom reports</a> that <fddLink id="fdd000383">MBOX</fddLink> and EML have &quot;achieved a certain status as de facto standards because most modern email clients and servers can import and export one or both of the formats&quot; including Thunderbird, Apple Mail, Outlook and Eudora. In addition, external programs such as Aid4Mail,  Emailchemy and Xena can convert between the two formats and numerous proprietary formats. Once in an <fddLink id="fdd000383">MBOX</fddLink> or EML format, the data can be parsed into XML using standardized schemas. </p>
			<p>The ePADD project developed at Stanford University Libraries added functionality for <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20230126201546/https://library.stanford.edu/blogs/special-collections-unbound/2023/01/epadd-version-10-now-available">export to EML</a> (link via Internet Archive) as of 2023 with version 10.0. This is in addition to existing export to MBOX.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>None</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>EML files are usually simple text files and can be opened in Notepad or a web browser, either by changing the extension from eml to txt or HTML, or by changing the file association to Notepad. </p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000393">IMF</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Accessibility Features</b>
			</p>
			<p>EML does not have specific features to support digital accessibility but as a text-based format, it does comply with <a href="https://www.section508.gov/test/checklist/email-messages/">Section 508</a> guidelines for accessible email. These guidelines include information about five areas of focus for email: Structure (which, in part, advocates for plain-text or HTML formats), General Content of messages including color contrast, file attachments and signature blocks, Graphics and Sensory Characteristics including the use of alt text, Data Tables with a focus on structured data and their headings, and Saving Files as a document file. EML is specifically listed as a preferred option for this, along with <fddLink id="fdd000379">MSG</fddLink>. </p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://www.accessible-email.org/">Accessible-email.org</a> also provides an accessibility evaluation tool "aimed at email marketing professionals and industry developers to give them an overview of their current level and possible improvements" in terms of accessibility and usability.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors/>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>eml</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>message/rfc822</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>This is the common MIME type for all formats based on RFC 822. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>NF00170</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00170.ttl">https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00170.ttl</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000393">IMF</fddLink>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q11198294</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11198294">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11198294</a>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes/>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See <fddLink id="fdd000393">IMF</fddLink>
					</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://cr.yp.to/immhf.html</link>
					<tag>Internet mail message header format</tag>
					<comment>Describes format of an Internet mail message header</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://wiki.archivematica.org/Email_preservation</link>
					<tag>Archivematica Email Preservation</tag>
					<comment>Brief formats descriptions including EML</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Email</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia Email</tag>
					<comment>Includes discussion of many email formats including EML</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.dpconline.org/docs/technology-watch-reports/739-dpctw11-01-pdf/file</link>
					<tag>Preserving Email: DPC Technology Watch report 2011 by Christopher J. Prom</tag>
					<comment>Excellent coverage of issues with preserving email. </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.section508.gov/test/checklist/email-messages/</link>
					<tag>Section508.gov: Checklist for Accessible Email Messages</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.accessible-email.org/</link>
					<tag>accessible-email.org. Includes Accessibility evaluation tool for email</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00170.ttl</link>
					<tag>NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID entry for NF00170</tag>
					<comment>Information in NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID about EML.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11198294</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q11198294</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about EML. Wikidata Title ID: Q11198294.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
