<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000255" titleName="AMR-WB, Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband Speech Codec" shortName="AMR-WB" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>sound</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>telephony</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2012-02-09</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Partial</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>AMR-WB, Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband Speech Codec (G.722.2)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>AMR-WB</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Audio data compression scheme optimized for speech coding in GSM (Global System for Mobile Communications) and UMTS (Universal Mobile Telecommunications System), an elaboration of <fddLink id="fdd000254">AMR</fddLink>, and featuring Algebraic Code Excited Linear Prediction (ACELP) compression coding.</p>
			<p>The AMR-WB bitrates are 6.60, 8.85, 12.65, 14.25, 15.85, 18.25, 19.85, 23.05 and 23.85 kbps. Compared to narrowband speech codecs (like AMR) optimized for traditional telephone voice quality of 300-3400 Hz, the AMR-WB codec's wider bandwidth of 50-7000 Hz provides excellent speech quality.</p>
			<p>Although AMR-WB pre-dates <fddLink id="fdd000253">AMR-WB+</fddLink>, it is more constrained and is therefore treated as a subtype of AMR-WB+ at this Web site; <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Audio data compression scheme optimized for speech coding in GSM (Global System for Mobile Communications) and UMTS (Universal Mobile Telecommunications System), an elaboration of AMR.  Compared to narrowband speech codecs (like AMR) optimized for traditional telephone voice quality of 300-3400 Hz, the AMR-WB codec's wider bandwidth of 50-7000 Hz provides excellent speech quality.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Final-state for end-user delivery.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000253</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>AMR-WB+</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Extended Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband Speech Codec. </fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>
					<a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>
			<fddLink id="fdd000253">AMR-WB+</fddLink> has been selected as the audio codec for LC-produced <a href="http://www.loc.gov/nls/businessplan/businessplan2006.html">Digital Talking Books</a>; see also <fddLink id="fdd000053">DTB</fddLink>.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>None</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>Open standard.  Developed by 3GPP, a collaboration of telecommunications industry and standards groups in Europe, Asia, and North America.   The key European organization is ETSI (European Telecommunications Standards Institute).</p>
			<p>AMR-WB is also codified by ITU-T (International Telecommunication Union-Telecommunication Standardization Sector).</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>3GPP TS 26.171 v.6.0.0 (2004-12), <i>Digital cellular telecommunications system (Phase 2+); Universal Mobile Telecommunications System (UMTS); AMR speech codec, wideband; General Description</i>, and other specifications listed in <a href="#specs">Format specifications</a> below. Some of the other specifications carry different version numbers; it is not clear to the compiler of this Web page if AMR-WB in and of itself has a version number; <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.  The <a href="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/26171.htm">3GPP Web site</a> lists versions of this documents dating to 2001.</p>
			<p>AMR-WB is also specified as <a href="http://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-G.722.2/en">ITU-T G.722.2</a>, <i>Wideband coding of speech at around 16 kbit/s using Adaptive Multi-Rate Wideband (AMR-WB)</i>.  The earliest of the group of specifications under this number is dated 2002; the ITU-T specifications were not inspected by the compiler of this page at this time.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Not investigated for this page.
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<a href="http://www.voiceage.com/AMR-WB.G.722.2.html">VoiceAge</a> holds related patents and offers licensing.   An Open AMR-WB Initiative (active between 2005 and 2012) made a free codec for Windows available for non-commercial use.  However, this initiative cannot be found on the VoiceAge site as of October 2013.  See <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20121030092732/http://www.voiceage.com/openinit_amrwb.php">Open AMR-WB Initiative page from Oct 2012 via Internet Archive</a>.
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication to build tools.
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Not investigated for this page.
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>Not investigated for this page.
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>The available bitrates are: 6.60, 8.85, 12.65, 14.25, 15.85, 18.25, 19.85, 23.05 and 23.85 kbps. The lowest rate that provides excellent speech quality in a clean environtment is 12.65 kbps. Higher rates are useful in background noise conditions and in the case of music. Rates of 6.60 and 8.85 provide reasonable quality when compared to narrow band codecs like <fddLink id="fdd000254">AMR</fddLink>.</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>None.</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:beyondSound>Not investigated for this page.</fdd:beyondSound>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000254">AMR</fddLink>; <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>audio/AMR-wb</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 0x2321414d522d57420a</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: #!AMR-WB\n</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4867.txt">RFC 4867</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>From the <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20120424233153/http://www.voiceage.com/amrwb.php">VoiceAge</a> Web site (consulted in April 2007, now linked via Internet Archive, after redesign of VoiceAge site): Most speech coding systems in use today are based on telephone-bandwidth narrowband speech, nominally limited to about 200-3400 Hz and sampled at a rate of 8 kHz. This limitation built into the public switched telephone network (PSTN) dates back to the first transcontinental telephone service at the beginning of the 20th century and imposes a constraint on communication quality. Today, the increasing penetration of end-to-end digital networks such as the second- and third-generation wireless systems (2G and 3G) and voice over packet networks permits the use of wider speech bandwidth. . . .  The AMR-WB speech codec utilizes the ACELP (Algebraic Code Excitation Linear Prediction) technology, which is also employed in the AMR narrowband and EFR speech codecs as well as in ITU-T G.729 and G.723.1 at 5.3 kbit/s, among others. The AMR-WB speech codec consists of nine speech codec modes with bit rates of 23.85, 23.05, 19.85, 18.25, 15.85, 14.25, 12.65, 8.85 and 6.6 kbps. AMR-WB also includes a background noise mode that is designed to be used in discontinuous transmission (DTX) operation in GSM and as a low bit rate source-dependent mode for coding background noise in other systems. In GSM the bit rate of this mode is 1.75 kbps. . . .   Wideband speech coding results in major subjective improvements in speech quality. Compared to narrowband telephone speech, low-frequency enhancement in AMR-WB from 50 to 200 Hz contributes to increased naturalness, presence, and comfort. The high-frequency extension from 3400 to 7000 Hz provides better fricative differentiation (for example, between words like fin and thin), and therefore higher intelligibility.  The adoption of AMR-WB by ETSI/3GPP and ITU-T (where it is referred to as G.722.2) is of significant importance because, for the first time, the same codec has been adopted for wireless as well as wireline services. This eliminates the need for transcoding and eases the implementation of wideband voice applications and services across a wide range of communication systems and platforms.</fdd:general>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>RFC 4867 (RTP Payload Format and File Storage Format for the Adaptive Multi-Rate [AMR] and Adaptive Multi-Rate Wideband [AMR-WB] Audio Codecs) is available online from IETF at more than one site and in more than one format:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4867</link>
							<tag>RFC 4867 in various formats</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4867.txt</link>
							<tag>RFC 4867 in plain text</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:docGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Relevant specifications are provided at no cost to registered users of the 3GPP Web site from this menu: <a href="http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/26-series.htm">http://www.3gpp.org/DynaReport/26-series.htm</a>.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:referenceList>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.171, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; General description</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.173, ANSI-C code for the Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.174, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec test sequences</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.190, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; Transcoding functions</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.191, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; Error concealment of erroneous or lost frames</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.192, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; Comfort noise aspects</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.193, <a href=""/>Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; Source controlled rate operation</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.194, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; Voice Activity Detector (VAD)</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.201, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; Frame structure</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.202, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; Interface to Iu, Uu and Nb</fdd:specReference>
						<fdd:specReference>TS 26.204, Speech codec speech processing functions; Adaptive Multi-Rate - Wideband (AMR-WB) speech codec; ANSI-C code</fdd:specReference>
					</fdd:referenceList>
				</fdd:docGroup>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_Multi-Rate_Wideband</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia article Adaptive Multi-Rate Wideband</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.voiceage.com/Overview-lic.html</link>
					<tag>Getting a License -- Why Bother?</tag>
					<comment>Includes links to information about various AMR and other codecs.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.voiceage.com/AMR-WB.G.722.2.html</link>
					<tag>AMR-WB/G.722.2 page at VoiceAge</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://ipr.etsi.org</link>
					<tag>ETSI licensing and patent Web site</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
