<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000310" titleName="EPUB (Electronic Publication) File Format Family" shortName="EPUB_family" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>container-wrapper</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2024-05-06</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>EPUB (Electronic Publication) File Format Family</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The EPUB family of standards defines a distribution and interchange format for digital publications and documents. The EPUB format provides a means of representing, packaging, and encoding structured and
semantically enhanced Web content — including <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000482">CSS</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000515">SVG</fddLink> and other resources — for distribution in a single‐file container.  The container file is based on the <fddLink id="fdd000354">ZIP</fddLink> format and defined in the Open Container Format (OCF). It is referred to in this description as an EPUB Container, but the term &quot;OCF ZIP Container&quot; is also used in the EPUB specifications.</p>
			<p>Inside an EPUB Container are the resources needed to permit the rendering of an EPUB Publication; an EPUB Publication typically represents a single intellectual or artistic work. An EPUB Publication consists of one or more Renditions of its content. typically represented by what is called an EPUB Package.  An EPUB Package consists of all the resources needed to render the content. The key file among these is the Package Document, an XML file that serves to centralize metadata, detail the individual resources that compose the Package and provide the reading order and other information necessary to render the Rendition. It includes all the metadata used by EPUB Reading Systems to present the EPUB Publication to the user (e.g., the title and author for display in a list of books, as well rendering metadata such as whether content has a fixed layout or can be reflowed). It also provides a complete <i>manifest</i> of resources, and includes a <i>spine</i> that indicates the normal reading order sequence.   
An EPUB Package also includes another key file called the EPUB Navigation Document.  This document provides critical navigation capabilities, such as the table of contents, that allow users to quickly and easily navigate the content.</p>
			<p>Helpful diagrams that represent the EPUB format include (a) a <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/images/epub.svg">Conceptual diagram</a> and (b) a more <a href="https://www.edrlab.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/edrlab_epub_the-structure-of-an-EPUB-file.png">structural representation of EPUB components</a> in a diagram from <a href="https://www.edrlab.org/open-standards/anatomy-of-an-epub-3-file/">Anatomy of an EPUB 3 file</a>.</p>
			<p>The textual content of the primary rendition for an EPUB Publication is usually in <fddLink id="fdd000484">XHTML</fddLink> markup (or, for EPUB 3, the XML serialization of <fddLink id="fdd000481">HTML 5</fddLink>), one of the <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-spec.html#sec-core-media-types">Core Media Types</a> defined for EPUB.  EPUB also has the concept of "foreign resources," i.e., resources in formats not considered as core media types.  Note that all video formats are considered foreign resources.  In general EPUB Publications should incorporate "fallback" representations for foreign resources using a core format, e.g., by providing a still image as fallback for a video resource. The following Core Media Types are listed in the specification for <fddLink id="fdd000309">EPUB 3.2</fddLink>:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>XHTML Content Documents.  They must conform to the constraints and EPUB-specific refinements of XHTML described in <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-contentdocs.html">EPUB Content Documents 3.2</a>.  May include embedded <a href="https://www.w3.org/Math/whatIsMathML.html">MathML</a> but constrained to a restricted subset of the full MathML markup language.  See <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-contentdocs.html#sec-xhtml-mathml">2.5.1. Embedded MathML</a>.  May include embedded <fddLink id="fdd000515">SVG</fddLink>.</li>
				<li>SVG Content Documents.  They must conform to the constraints and EPUB-specific refinements of SVG described in <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-contentdocs.html">EPUB Content Documents 3.2</a>.  This type of Content Document is typically used for graphical publications, such as illustrated children&apos;s books, comics, or graphic novels.</li>
				<li>Images: <fddLink id="fdd000133">GIF</fddLink>; <fddLink id="fdd000018">JPEG</fddLink>; <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink>; SVG</li>
				<li>Audio: MP3; AAC LC audio using MP4 container (<fddLink id="fdd000233">AAC_MP4_LC</fddLink>)</li>
				<li>
					<fddLink id="fdd000482">CSS</fddLink> Style Sheets</li>
				<li>Font formats: TrueType; OpenType; WOFF; WOFF2</li>
				<li>Scripts in <fddLink id="fdd000443">Javascript</fddLink>
				</li>
				<li>EPUB Media Overlay Documents.  As defined in <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-mediaoverlays.html">EPUB Media Overlays 3.2</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<i>Legacy</i> NCX navigation documents.  As defined in <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/20/spec/OPF_2.0.1_draft.htm#Section2.4.1">Open Packaging Format (OPF) 2.0.1</a>.  This is the deprecated EPUB 2 navigation document. Some EPUB 3 authors still prefer to include it so that EPUB 2 reading systems can process the publication.</li>
				<li>Text-to-Speech (TTS) Pronunciation lexicons.  As defined in <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/pronunciation-lexicon/">Pronunciation Lexicon Specification (PLS) Version 1.0</a> from W3C.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The EPUB Publication&apos;s resources are bundled for distribution in a ZIP-based archive, known as an EPUB Container, with the file extension .epub. As conformant ZIP archives, EPUB Publications can be unzipped by many software programs, simplifying both their production and consumption.  Note that, in addition to any renditions based on XHTML and SVG, an EPUB Publication can optionally include a rendition in <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>Two major chronological versions of EPUB specifications exist: <fddLink id="fdd000278">EPUB 2 </fddLink>and EPUB 3 (see <fddLink id="fdd000308">EPUB_3_0</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000311">EPUB_3_0_1</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000309">EPUB_3_2</fddLink>).  There was no version 1 for the specifications under the EPUB name, because .epub was first used as the extension for the predecessor <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20071030212424/http://idpf.org/ocf/ocf1.0/">Open eBook Publication Structure Container Format (OCF) 1.0 (2006)</a>, an optional ZIP-based container for the Open eBook Publication Structure (<fddLink id="fdd000171">OEBPS</fddLink>), published by the Open eBook Forum.  For details of the phases of development of the EPUB specifications, see <a href="#notes">Notes: History</a> below.</p>
			<p>Two editions of EPUB specifications have been republished by ISO/IEC.  Within ISO and IEC, EPUB is considered by a special joint working group (ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 34/JWG 7).  JWG 7 spans several ISO and IEC committees: JTC 1/SC 34 (Document description and processing languages), ISO TC 46/SC 4 (Technical interoperability), and IEC/TC 100/TA 10 (Multimedia e-publishing and e-book technologies).  EPUB specification published by JWG 7 include the following:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ISO/IEC TS 30135:2014.  Identical to EPUB 3.0.  This was a <a href="https://www.iso.org/deliverables-all.html#TS">Technical Specification</a>, not an International Standard.  According to ISO, &quot;a Technical Specification addresses work still under technical development, or where it is believed that there will be a future, but not immediate, possibility of agreement on an International Standard.&quot;  Published in seven parts.</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 23736:2020.  Identical to EPUB 3.0.1.  Published as an International Standard in six parts.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>As of May 2020, several publications related to the use of EPUB Publications have been in preparation under the auspices of ISO/IEC.  These related to accessibility and archival preservation of EPUB Publications, and to the application of Digital Rights Management (DRM) to digital publications, including EPUB Publications.  For details, see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>a family of standards that define a distribution and interchange format for digital publications and documents.  Openly developed and published by standardization entities: International Digital Publishing Forum (IDPF) [2005-2017, versions 2.0-3.1];  W3C EPUB 3 Community Group (2019, version 3.2)</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>An EPUB file is used primarily as a final-state format, for dissemination to end-users.  It may also be used as a middle-state format within a production workflow.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000309</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_3_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Electronic Publication, Version 3.2</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000311</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_3_0_1</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Electronic Publication, Version 3.0.1,  ISO/IEC 23736:2020</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000308</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_3_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Electronic Publication, Version 3.0,  ISO/IEC TS 30135:2014</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000278</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>EPUB, Electronic Publication, Version 2</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000354</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ZIP-PK</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>ZIP File Format (PKWARE)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>EPUB Open Container Format (OCF) 2 and 3.0 cite ZIP 6.3.0 (September 2006).  OCF 3.01 cites <fddLink id="fdd000362">ZIP 6.3.3</fddLink> (September 2012).  The reference OCF 3.2 gives the September 2012 date but uses the URL that always goes to the most recent version of the ZIP APPNOTE.txt file. </fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000075</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>The XML schema for the EPUB Package Document is defined using RELAX-NG, <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/52348.html">ISO/IEC 19757-2:2008</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000481</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HTML_5</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 5</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment> EPUB 3 XHTML Content Documents use the XML syntax for HTML 5, i.e. the successor to XHTML.  EPUB 2 used <fddLink id="fdd000484">XHTML 1.1</fddLink>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000515</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>SVG_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) File Format Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Used for SVG Content Documents and for images embedded in XHTML Content documents.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress has over 11,000 out-of-copyright books that were selected for scanning by the Internet Archive, for which EPUB versions have been created fully automatically using the results of OCR. See, for example, <a href="https://lccn.loc.gov/25003682">https://lccn.loc.gov/25003682</a> with link to <a href="http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.gdc/scd0001.00139838658">http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.gdc/scd0001.00139838658</a>. Also included in the digital collections are ebooks in the EPUB format deposited in recent years in compliance with copyright law and made available under controlled conditions to staff and onsite users. The Library has many EPUB files in its digital collections - over 1.3TB in 2024 - across numerous collections.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>
			<p>The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) lists EPUB 3 as a Preferred format for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/text.html#digital">Textual Works - Digital</a>. </p>
			<p>As an XML-based format using publicly documented schemas that represent the logical structure of a publication, EPUB satisfies most of the desired characteristics for formats for textual works, if the content files are not encrypted, if the file is not subject to technological protection that inhibits long-term preservation and access, and if all content is stored within the EPUB container.  Bibliographic metadata records, for example, in the ONIX schema, may optionally be included in the EPUB container or may be available through a link to an external record.  The Library of Congress would want to receive or access such metadata records in conjunction with ingestion of an EPUB publication.</p>
		</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>EPUB is an openly documented standard.  It has been developed and maintained under the auspices of a sequence of entities.  The first published version of EPUB was EPUB 2.0, standardized in 2007 by the International Digital Publishing Forum (IDPF) as a successor format to the Open eBook Publication Structure (OEBPS). OEBPS had been published by the Open eBook Forum in 1999 (<fddLink id="fdd000054">OEBPS_1_0</fddLink>), with an update published in 2002 (<fddLink id="fdd000171">OEBPS_2</fddLink>).  The Open eBook Forum became IDPF in 2005. Between 2007 and 2017, IDPF published several editions of EPUB versions 2 and 3.</p>
			<p>At the end of January 2017, the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) and the International Digital Publishing Forum (IDPF) combined organizations.  See <a href="http://idpf.org/news/">IDPF News as of January 31, 2017</a> and <a href="https://www.w3.org/2017/01/pressrelease-idpf-w3c-combination.html">New Roadmap for Future of Publishing is Underway as W3C and IDPF Officially Combine (February 1, 2017)</a> from Publishing@W3C .  Development of EPUB continued under the auspices of the <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/groups/epub3-cg/">W3C EPUB Community Group</a> which produced the specification for EPUB 3.2 as its final report.   In April 2020, the plan to form a new working group was <a href="https://www.w3.org/blog/2020/03/listen-to-the-people-the-future-of-epub-and-new-directions-for-publishing-w3c/">announced</a>. This group will focus on making EPUB 3 a W3C Recommendation and the continuing maintenance of EPUB 3.</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>Freely accessible versions of EPUB specifications:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-spec.html">EPUB 3.2,
Final Community Group Specification. 08 May 2019</a>.  From W3C Publishing Community Group.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://idpf.org/epub/31/spec/epub-spec.html">EPUB 3.1,
Recommended Specification 5 January 2017</a>.  From IDPF, published shortly before IDPF combined with W3C.  This specification was not widely implemented, because of incompatibilities with the previous version.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://idpf.org/epub/301/">EPUB 3.0.1,  Recommended Specification 26 June 2014</a>.  From IDPF.  The most widely implemented version of EPUB.  A minor maintenance update to EPUB 3.0.  Also issued as an international standard  ISO/IEC 23736:2020 in six parts.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://idpf.org/epub/30/">EPUB 3.0</a>.  From IDPF. Also issued as ISO/IEC TS 30135:2014 in seven parts.  All parts were confirmed in 2018.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://idpf.org/epub/201">EPUB 2.0.1</a>. From IDPF.   By September 2014, EPUB 2 had been declared obsolete in the IDPF website.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Support for rendering EPUB documents both for traditional visual display and for reading with assistive technologies, such as screen readers, has been increasing steadily.  According to <a href="https://www.lifewire.com/what-is-an-epub-file-2621084">What Is an EPUB File?</a> from Lifewire (February 2020), the format &quot;supports more hardware eBook readers than any other file format.&quot;  As of early 2020, most online eBook services provide some support for EPUB, either for authors when submitting works, or for readers as a download option, or both.  For example, EPUB appears on the list of <a href="https://kdp.amazon.com/en_US/help/topic/G200634390">Supported eBook Formats </a> for Kindle Direct Publishing.  There are several software development kits (SDKs) that support working with EPUB files.  See <a href="https://kitaboo.com/choose-sdk-custom-ebook-platform/">How to Choose the Best SDK for your Custom eBook Platform (2020)</a>.</p>
			<p>A wide variety of reading applications exist that include EPUB among the ebook formats supported.  Some are associated with ebook retailing outlets; others with software for managing a personal library. Some are specialized for certain categories of publication, e.g., comics.  Some can handle EPUB publications protected by digital right management (DRM).  Among the free applications that appear frequently on lists of recommended applications are: <a href="https://www.adobe.com/la/solutions/ebook/digital-editions.html">Adobe Digital Editions</a> (supported by many public libraries for borrowing ebooks, for Windows, MacOS, iOS, Android); <a href="https://www.apple.com/apple-books/">Apple Books</a> (for MacOS, iOS); <a href="https://calibre-ebook.com/">Calibre</a> (features cataloging and resource management for a personal ebook library, includes editor for EPUB documents and conversion among ebook formats, for Windows, MacOS, Linux); Kobo (<a href="https://help.kobo.com/hc/en-us/articles/360017707874">Kobo Desktop</a> for Windows and MacOS, <a href="https://help.kobo.com/hc/en-us/articles/360017707914-Get-the-Kobo-Books-app">Kobo Books</a> for iOS and Android); <a href="http://www.frenchfrysoftware.com/cover/">Cover - Comic reader</a> (designed for comics, for Windows) ; <a href="https://yourdolphin.com/EasyReader-App">Dolphin EasyReader</a> (aimed at those with low vision, blindness or dyslexia, for Windows, iOS, Android) ; <a href="https://www.voicedream.com/reader/">Voice Dream Reader</a> (text-to-speech with synchronized highlighting, for iOS, Android); <a href="http://www.turnipsoft.co.uk/freda/">freda</a> (includes dyslexic-friendly settings, for Windows, Android); <a href="https://www.edrlab.org/software/thorium-reader/">Thorium Reader</a> (aims to be highly accessible for the visually impaired and dyslexic, for Windows, MacOS, Linux).  <a href="https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPUBReader">EPUBReader</a> is a browser add-on available for the Firefox browser since 2010 and for Chrome in September 2019.  For a list of software and hardware readers for EPUB documents, see <a href="https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPub#Readers">https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPub</a>.</p>
			<p>A substantial number of applications offering support for creating or editing EPUB documents are listed in <a href="https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPub#ePub_Creation_and_Manipulation_software">https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPub</a> and <a href="https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPub_3#Available_Publishing_Tools">https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPub_3</a>. Among commercial XML editors, support is provided by <a href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_editor/epub.html">Oxygen XML Editor</a>, <a href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_author/epub.html">Oxygen XML Author</a>, and <a href="https://www.altova.com/manual/XMLSpy/spyprofessional/xsooxmlzip_epubfiles.html">Altova XMLSpy 2020 Professional Edition</a>.</p>
			<p>An important community that has adopted the EPUB format, particularly EPUB 3, includes organizations active in supporting access to written materials for users with print disabilities.  For more information on Accessibility for EPUB Publications, see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
			<p>Since late 2014, Apple has had readers for EPUB in both MacOS and iOS as shipped, initially with iBooks and since 2018 with the Books application.  Apple&apos;s Pages word processor (formerly part of iWorks for MacOS) added support for export to EPUB in 2010.  As of early 2020, exports from Pages are in EPUB 3.</p>
			<p>The situation for Windows is different. Until October 2019, the Edge browser (now termed &quot;Edge Classic&quot;) would render EPUB Publications, but Microsoft withdrew support and <a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-edge/download-an-epub-app-to-keep-reading-e-books-0114ba69-4cae-b6b0-4d47-99eb50f36449">encouraged the use of third-party applications</a>, making a <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/store/collections/thereadingroom">selection</a> approved by <a href="https://daisy.org/">The DAISY Consortium</a>.  In the meantime, Microsoft continued to work with DAISY, which released a conversion tool (<a href="https://daisy.org/activities/software/wordtoepub/">WordToEPUB</a>) in March 2020. This tool, which can function as an add-on to Word or as a free-standing application is designed to work in coordination with the <a href="https://support.office.com/en-us/article/video-check-the-accessibility-of-your-document-9d660cba-1fcd-45ad-a9d1-c4f4b5eb5b7d">Accessibility Checker</a> in Word.</p>
			<p>Adobe supports EPUB in several contexts.  Adobe InDesign can <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/in/indesign/using/export-content-epub-cc.html">export</a> documents in the EPUB format.  With the free Adobe Digital Editions (ADE) ebook reader, users on Windows, MacOS, iOS, and Android can <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/in/digital-editions/using/get-started-with-adobe-digital-editions.html">read</a> documents in EPUB 2 or EPUB 3.0 format (as well as PDF).  ADE can be used to read EPUB documents protected with DRM and is often used in libraries or in connection with subscription databases.  ADE is compatible with the following widely used screen readers: JAWS and NVDA (for Windows); VoiceOver (for Mac).  Adobe also offers a &quot;white label&quot; version of ADE through Adobe Reader Mobile SDK (<a href="https://www.adobe.com/solutions/ebook/rmsdk.html">RMSDK</a>), allowing companies to develop their own branded reading app.</p>
			<p>The open-source <a href="https://github.com/w3c/epubcheck">EPUBCheck</a> is a tool to validate the conformance of EPUB publications against the EPUB specifications. EPUBCheck can be run as a standalone command-line tool or used as a Java library. </p>
			<p>The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) includes EPUB_3 as a preferred format for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/text.html#digital">textual works in digital form</a>. EPUB 3.0 is listed as an acceptable format for text in <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200724071348/https://www.naa.gov.au/information-management/storing-and-preserving-information/preserving-information/preserving-digital-information/long-term-file-formats">Long-term file formats</a> from the National Archives of Australia and as a <a href="https://library-archives.canada.ca/eng/services/government-canada/information-disposition/managing-government-records/guidelines-information-management/pages/guidelines-file-formats-enduring-value.aspx#j">preferred format</a> by Library and Archives Canada.  <a href="https://digitalpreservation.fi/files/File-Formats-1.8.0.pdf">File Formats (v 1.8.0)</a> from the Finnish National Digital Library Preservation Services lists EPUB versions 2.0.1, 3.0, 3.0.1, and 3.2 as acceptable formats for transfer.</p>
			<p>EPUB 2 is one of the formats in which open access ebooks are published by Project Gutenberg.  As of early 2020, <a href="https://github.com/gutenbergtools/ebookmaker">EbookMaker</a> is the tool developed by Project Gutenberg using other open-source modules for automatic conversion of transcribed texts marked up in HTML to EPUB 2 and <fddLink id="fdd000472">MOBI/Kindle</fddLink> formats.  See also <a href="https://www.pgdp.net/wiki/The_Proofreader%27s_Guide_to_EPUB">The Proofreader&apos;s Guide to EPUB</a> from the Project Gutenberg Distributed Proofreaders site.  When books in the <a href="https://archive.org/details/books">Internet Archive Books Collection</a> are produced by scanning pages and performing OCR, the documents produced by the ABBYY FineReader OCR process are converted automatically to &quot;primitively accessible&quot; EPUB 3 documents.  See <a href="https://abbyy-to-epub3.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">ABBYY XML to EPUB3 documentation</a>.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No licensing concerns for production or use of content compliant with the EPUB specifications or core media types.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>In general, the content of an HTML-based or SVG-based EPUB rendition of a textual work that is not encrypted is easily viewed with text editors or with XML tools.  The XML-based constructs that are used in the EPUB Container to support rendering and packaging are named with human-readable elements and attributes.  The core media types permitted for images and audio are widely used and supported.  &quot;Foreign objects,&quot; i.e., objects in formats not listed as core media types are expected to have &quot;fallback&quot; resources from the core media list.  This means that all video resources are expected to have images as fallbacks.</p>
			<p>The different chronological editions of EPUB 3 have had different constraints and recommendations as regards embedding or linking to video and &quot;foreign objects.&quot; Links are references using URIs.</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>EPUB 3 provides much richer capabilities for bibliographic metadata than EPUB 2, including permitting links to metadata records in schemas such as MARCXML and ONIX in the EPUB Package Document and the optional storage of such records in the ZIP-based EPUB container.
			<p>
				<b>Accessibility Features</b>
			</p>
			<p>EPUB files have good support for accessibility features. For EPUB publications, accessibility metadata is included in the package document to identify accessibility features for the document.</p>
			<p>EPUB publications must include the following accessibility metadata and information:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>The accessMode property to define the human sensory perceptual system or cognitive faculty needed to perceive the content, such as textual, visual, or auditory.</li>
				<li>The <a href="https://www.w3.org/community/reports/a11y-discov-vocab/CG-FINAL-vocabulary-20230718/#accessibilityFeature">accessibilityFeature property</a> to document the accessibility features of the content, including alternative text, extended descriptions, and captions. This property should be repeated for each feature available.</li>
				<li>The <a href="https://www.w3.org/2021/a11y-discov-vocab/latest/#accessibilityHazard">accessibilityHazard property</a> to identify any accessibility hazards in a publication, such as flashing content, motion simulation, or sound. These hazards may result in physical effects such as seizures and nausea for the user. An EPUB creator may also note the absence of hazards in the accessibilityHazard property.</li>
				<li>Alternative text descriptions for image-based content.</li>
				<li>Language of text content in the package document so that reading systems can render this metadata in the proper language for the user.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>EPUB publications should also include the following accessibility metadata:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Language of the text content in the publication, which will assist reading systems in optimizing the reading experience for users (for example by preloading text-to-speech information).</li>
				<li>Page break markers to provide user with context as to where they are within the text (EPUB 3). EPUB 2 does not include markup for static page break markers.</li>
				<li>A page list that links to static page locations with the text. In EPUB 3, the &lt;page-list nav&gt; element is included in the content documents, while in EPUB 2 the NCX file is used with the &lt;pageList&gt; element. </li>
				<li>The <a href="https://www.w3.org/2021/a11y-discov-vocab/latest/#accessibilitySummary">accessibilitySummary property</a> for a description of a publication's accessibility features, or notes on why a publication does not meet accessibility requirements.</li>
				<li>The accessModeSufficient property, which identifies a set of one or more access modes that are sufficient to consume the content without significant loss of information.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>EPUB also provides accessibility options for:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Synchronized text-audio playback, in which an embedded audio element can be synchronized with visible text and also address alternative text for image content. The media overlay documents allow for the ability to synchronize audio with the text of the content documents. Text and audio synchronization not provided for EPUB 2. </li>
				<li>Identification of reading order, so that playback order matches logical order. The reader order is identified through the the sequence of EPUB content documents in the spine and in the order of elements within each EPUB content document.</li>
				<li>Identification of content that should be skippable in playback, such as endnotes or footnotes.</li>
				<li>Identification of escapable content, to allow a user to escape from the playback of these elements to continue reading the text. Escapable content might include figures, lists, or tables.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>For more information about EPUB accessibility features see <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/epub-a11y-11/">EPUB Accessibility 1.1</a> and <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/epub-a11y-tech-11/">EPUB Accessibility Techniques 1.1</a>. </p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>
			<p>In general, the concept is that an EPUB file should include a complete rendition of the EPUB publication.  However, for practical feasibility, some resources, particularly video, are often stored remotely and referenced by URI.</p>
			<p>The different chronological editions of EPUB 3 have had different constraints on linking versus embedding for particular categories of resources.  EPUB 3.2 offers the most flexibility for storing resources remotely.  To comply with EPUB 3.2, all <i>Publication Resources</i> MUST be located in the EPUB Container, with the following exceptions:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Audio resources MAY be located outside the EPUB Container.</li>
				<li>Video resources MAY be located outside the EPUB Container.</li>
				<li>Resources retrieved by scripts MAY be located outside the EPUB Container.</li>
				<li>Font resources MAY be located outside the EPUB Container.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Location of audio, video and script resources inside the EPUB Container is encouraged whenever feasible.  The use of resources outside the container must be indicated by the value &quot;remote-resources&quot; in the <i>properties</i> attribute in the <i>item</i> element for the appropriate item in the package manifest.</p>
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>
			<p>In addition to support for encryption of content files within the OCF container, an optional element of the OCF container format can specify digital rights management (DRM) terms and procedures.  Commercially published EPUBs usually protect their EPUB files with DRM.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
			<p>Embedded third-party fonts may be &quot;obfuscated&quot; by partial encryption.  Reader tools must be capable of performing the decryption as described in the specification in order to be able to use the intended fonts.</p>
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>Good support.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>Representation of the logical structure of a document is an essential feature of EPUB.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>
				<p>Publishers may choose to control some aspects of layout through style-sheets. However, flowable text, by definition, will break lines and paginate text differently depending on the reading platform and user choices.</p>
				<p>Since 2012, authors/publishers have been able to specify a fixed layout instead of the default flowable text.  The first specification for declarative metadata to express the rendering intent was in a separate informational document, <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/fxl/epub-fxl-20120313.html">EPUB 3 Fixed-Layout Documents</a>.  In EPUB 3.01, the specification was merged into <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/301/spec/epub-publications.html#sec-package-metadata-fxl">EPUB Publications 3.0.1: 4.4.2 Fixed-Layout Properties</a> and allowed the values of <i>reflowable</i> and <i>pre-paginated</i>.</p>
			</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>Starting with EPUB 3.0 (2011), an EPUB Publication has been able to include content in MathML.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>Flowable text can adapt to reading devices with a variety of form factors. Synchronization of audio and text is supported. A pronunciation lexicon can be embedded to support text to speech renderings.
</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>epub</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Recommended extension for the EPUB container file. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/epub+zip</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From OCF specifications and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/epub+zip">IANA registration associated with EPUB 3.01</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>From OCF specification:<ul>
						<li>The bytes “PK” will be at the beginning of the file, followed by two additional bytes from the ZIP specification: \003 \004</li>
						<li>The bytes “mimetype” will be at position 30</li>
						<li>actual MIME type (i.e., the ASCII string “application/epub+zip”) will begin at position 38</li>
					</ul>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Indicator for profile, level, version, etc.</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>
						<p>The version of EPUB is identified in the <i>version</i> attribute of the root &lt;package&gt; element in the .opf file, which can be found when the contents of the .epub file is &quot;unzipped&quot;, i.e., extracted from the ZIP archive into its component files.  The official way to find the .opf file is through the mandatory META-INF/container.xml file.  If the EPUB container has a single EPUB Package, this will often be, by convention rather than requirement, in a directory named &quot;EPUB&quot; or &quot;OEBPS.&quot;</p>
						<p>The version attribute for packages complying with all EPUB 3.x specifications is &quot;3.0&quot; and for EPUB 2.x specifications is &quot;2.0&quot;.</p>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/483</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM entry does not differentiate between versions of EPUB. See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/483">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/483</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q475488</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>WikiData entry does not differentiate between EPUB_2 and EPUB_3. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q475488">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q475488</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>NF00556</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00556.ttl">https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00556.ttl</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>Accessibility Recommendations for EPUB Publications:</b>
	The EPUB 3.2 specification included a recommendation that all EPUB Publications conform to the 2017 <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/a11y/accessibility.html">EPUB Accessibility</a> specification from IPDF along with support for <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0</a>.  This accessibility specification set formal requirements for certifying content as accessible, using three categories of compliance: <i>discoverable</i>, <i>accessible</i>, and <i>optimized</i>.  To be judged <i>accessible</i>, a publication must have a high degree of accessibility for users with a wide variety of reading needs and preferences.  In contrast, an <i>optimized</i> publication has been tailored to a specific reading modality, for example, to comply with <a href="https://daisy.org/info-help/guidance-training/standards/navigable-audio-only-epub3-guidelines/">DAISY Guidelines for Navigable Audio Only EPUB 3 Publications</a>. Discoverability requirements relate not only to bibliographic metadata for the publication, but to metadata that describes its level of accessibility.  Also published in 2017 by IDPF was  <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/a11y/techniques/techniques.html">EPUB Accessibility Techniques</a>, providing guidance on how to meet the discovery and accessibility requirements.</p>
			<p>As of May 2020, an update to the 2017 EPUB Accessibility specification is in the ISO/IEC approval process:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ISO/IEC DIS 23761. Digital Publishing — EPUB Accessibility — Conformance and Discoverability Requirements for EPUB Publications.  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/73163.html">https://www.iso.org/standard/76860.html</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The ISO/IEC standard is based closely on IDPF&apos;s 2017 EPUB Accessibility specification, but with re-organization for compatibility with directives for ISO publications.  It refers to <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/a11y/techniques/techniques.html">EPUB Accessibility Techniques (IDPF, 2017)</a> for guidance on meeting its requirements.</p>
			<p>The <a href="https://daisy.org/">DAISY Consortium</a> considers that, &quot;EPUB is a wonderful format for reading publications on laptops, tablets, and smartphones, and it includes features such as rich navigation and great accessibility.&quot;  With support from Microsoft, DAISY released a free tool (<a href="https://daisy.org/activities/software/wordtoepub/">WordToEPUB</a>) in March 2020 to simplify the conversion of Word documents to the EPUB 3 format. The DAISY Consortium also coordinates <a href="http://epubtest.org/results">testing of reading systems</a> against requirements for various controls and modalities that allow people with different reading disabilities to read EPUB titles. Its <a href="https://inclusivepublishing.org/">Inclusive Publishing</a> website reviews reading systems in <a href="https://inclusivepublishing.org/rs-accessibility/">Reading Systems Accessibility Support Roundup</a>. <a href="https://daisy.github.io/ace/getting-started/ace-app/">Ace by DAISY</a> is an EPUB accessibility checking tool.</p>
			<p>Other links related to creating accessible EPUB documents and the applications that can be useful include: <a href="http://aem.cast.org/creating/getting-started-with-epub.html">Getting Started with EPUB</a> from the National Center for Accessible Educational Materials; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220813052634/http://accesstext.gatech.edu/wiki/The_Accessible_EPUB_Eco-System_Overview">The Accessible EPUB Eco-System Overview</a> (link via Internet Archive);and the <a href="http://kb.daisy.org/publishing/docs/">Accessible Publishing Knowledge Base</a>.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Preservation of EPUB Publications</b>:  In 2012, Johan van der Knijff, of the KB/National Library of the Netherlands published an assessment of the suitability of the EPUB format for archival preservation.  The report acknowledged strengths that made EPUB attractive for preservation but raised a number of concerns, including the use of remote storage for audio and video, risks associated with scripts, and the use of foreign resources.  Guidance in relation to concerns including those raised by Johan van der Knijff are addressed in ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020 for EPUB3 Preservation, which was published as two Technical Specifications in January 2020.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ISO/IEC TS 22424-1:2020. Digital publishing — EPUB3 preservation — Part 1: Principles.  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/73163.html">https://www.iso.org/standard/73163.html</a>.</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC TS 22424-2:2020. Digital publishing — EPUB3 preservation — Part 2: Metadata requirements.  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/73169.html">https://www.iso.org/standard/73169.html</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The stated purpose of the specifications is to make it easier for producers and OAIS archives to preserve access to EPUB documents. ISO/IEC 22424-2:2020 provides a technical basis to meet the principles listed in ISO/IEC 22424-1:2020 by specifying metadata required for long-term preservation, and a method for packaging this metadata with the original EPUB container using <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/">METS</a> (Metadata Encoding &amp; Transmission Standard) and the <a href="https://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/">PREMIS</a> Data Dictionary for Preservation Metadata.  For more detail see <fddLink id="fdd000519">EPUB_pres</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Digital Rights Management for eBooks:</b>  Most major publishers continue to require DRM in their eBook distribution agreements, and eBook retailers have used DRM to promote “lock-in” to their platforms. The lack of a standard for DRM has led to fragmentation in the market: different retailers use non-interoperable DRM schemes that are tied in with eBook reader devices or apps.  In 2012, IDPF published <a href="http://idpf.org/epub-content-protection">EPUB Lightweight Content Protection: Use Cases &amp; Requirements</a>, proposed some requirements for a more user-friendly approach.    A system, influenced by this requirements document, and which is designed to be vendor-neutral and promote interoperability, has been developed by Readium and made available as <a href="https://www.edrlab.org/readium-lcp/">Readium LCP</a> (Licensed Content Protection). LCP is based on the concept of a standard form of license that incorporates a passphrase; the license is generated when a user buys a book or borrows it from a library. Supporters of this DRM approach submitted the specification to ISO.  See <a href="https://readium.org/lcp-specs/">Readium LCP Specifications</a> and <a href="https://www.edrlab.org/2019/04/01/lcp-becomes-iso-standard-first-meeting-milan/">LCP to become an ISO standard, first ISO meeting in Milan</a>. In May 2020, three related Technical Specifications were in the approval process:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ISO/IEC CD TS 23078-1. Specification of DRM technology for digital publications — Part 1: Overview of copyright protection technologies in use in the publishing industry.  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/79484.html">https://www.iso.org/standard/79484.html</a>.</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC CD TS 23078-2. Specification of DRM technology for digital publications — Part 2: User key-based protection  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/79485.html">https://www.iso.org/standard/79485.html</a>.</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC CD TS 23078-3. Specification of DRM technology for digital publications — Part 3: Part 3: Device key-based protection.  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/79486.html">https://www.iso.org/standard/79486.html</a>.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>For a good summary of the history of the EPUB format and its predecessor formats, see <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/epub-overview-33/#app-revision-history">EPUB Revision History for EPUB 3.3</a>  EPUB has its roots in the interchange format known as the Open EBook Publication Structure (<fddLink id="fdd000171">OEBPS</fddLink>).</p>
			<p>The Open eBook Publication Structure (<fddLink id="fdd000054">OEBPS</fddLink>), originally produced in 1999 by the Open eBook Authoring Group, was the precursor to EPUB 2 Open Publication Structure.  Following the release of OEBPS 1.0, the Open eBook Forum (OeBF) was formally incorporated in January 2000.  Version 1.0.1, a maintenance release, was brought out in July 2001. OEBPS Version 1.2, incorporating new support for control by content providers over presentation along with other corrections and improvements, was released as a Recommended Specification in August 2002.  The first use of the .epub file extension came with the ZIP-based container specification published as <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20071030212424/http://idpf.org/ocf/ocf1.0/">Open eBook Publication Structure Container Format (OCF) 1.0</a> in September 2006.</p>
			<p>The IDPF announced the adoption of the Open Publication Structure 2.0 and the &quot;.epub&quot; file format standard in September 2007.   The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20071024152816/http://www.idpf.org:80/specs.htm">IDPF Standards page as of October 24, 2007</a> used the following description: &apos;&quot;.epub&quot; is the file extension of an XML format for reflowable digital books and publications. &quot;.epub&quot; is composed of three open standards, the Open Publication Structure (OPS), Open Packaging Format (OPF) and Open Container Format (OCF).&apos;  This combination of specifications became known as EPUB 2. By 2008, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180103230605/http://idpf.org/news?page=22">IDPF news releases</a> and the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080430140959/http://www.idpf.org:80/">IDPF home page</a> used the capitalized &quot;EPUB&quot; to describe its specifications.  A minor update, EPUB 2.0.1, was approved in 2010.  By <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140922070411/http://idpf.org/epub/201">September 2014</a>, EPUB 2 was considered obsolete.</p>
			<p>EPUB, Version 3.0, was approved as an IDPF Recommendation in October 2011.  It is substantially different from EPUB, Version 2.0.1.  Many existing features were dropped, including the use of the Digital Talking Book <fddLink id="fdd000275">DTB_2005</fddLink> as a document content format.  The preferred content format for textual content in EPUB_3 is the XHTML serialization of HTML5.  New features include support for rich media and MathML.  The talking book functionality was replaced by a more general SMIL-based mechanism for media overlays and support for text-to-speech pronunciation hints.  EPUB 3.0.1, published in June 2014, was a minor maintenance update to EPUB 3.0.</p>
			<p>The next version of EPUB to be published was EPUB 3.1 in 2017.  In early 2019, EPUB 3.1 was declared defunct because of lack of adoption due to incompatibility with earlier releases of EPUB 3.  See introduction to <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/31/">EPUB 3.1</a> on IDPF website.</p>
			<p>At the end of January 2017, the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) and the International Digital Publishing Forum (IDPF) combined organizations.  See <a href="http://idpf.org/news/">IDPF News as of January 31, 2017</a> and <a href="https://www.w3.org/2017/01/pressrelease-idpf-w3c-combination.html">New Roadmap for Future of Publishing is Underway as W3C and IDPF Officially Combine</a> from Publishing@W3C on February 1, 2017.  Development of EPUB continued under the auspices of the <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/groups/epub3-cg/">W3C EPUB Community Group</a>.  EPUB 3.2 was published in May 2019 by W3C as a <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-spec.html">Final Community Group Specification</a>.</p>
			<p>In April 2020, the plan to form a new working group was <a href="https://www.w3.org/blog/2020/03/listen-to-the-people-the-future-of-epub-and-new-directions-for-publishing-w3c/">announced</a>. This group will focus on making EPUB 3 a W3C Recommendation and the continuing maintenance of EPUB 3.  As of early May 2020, the <a href="https://w3c.github.io/epub-3-wg-charter/">proposed charter</a> suggested a late 2022 milestone for EPUB 3.x to reach W3C Recommendation status.  The announcement states, &quot;We are very focused on backward compatibility, as we demonstrated with EPUB 3.2. Every valid EPUB 3.2 file should be valid to the new REC-track EPUB 3 spec unless it uses a feature that was never implemented anywhere. We understand the importance of preserving the existing ecosystem. But we hope to also add a few features that were requested by survey respondents.&quot;</p>
			<p>
				<b>ISO/IEC standardization of EPUB</b>: Within ISO and IEC, EPUB has been considered by a special joint working group (ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 34/JWG 7). JWG 7 spans several ISO and IEC committees: JTC 1/SC 34 (Document description and processing languages), ISO TC 46/SC 4 (Technical interoperability), and IEC/TC 100/TA 10 (Multimedia e-publishing and e-book technologies). EPUB 3.0 was approved as a <a href="https://www.iso.org/deliverables-all.html#TS">Technical Specification</a> by <a href="https://www.iso.org/committee/45020.html">ISO/IEC JTC1</a> in 2014 and published as ISO/IEC TS 30135:2014 in seven parts.  Each of these seven ISO specifications is identical to its IDPF equivalent, for example TS-30135-1 is exactly the same content as the EPUB Overview 3.0. So, the IDPF names and ISO numbers may be used interchangeably.   EPUB 3.0.1 was adopted as an international standard by ISO/IEC JTC1 in early 2020 and published as ISO/IEC 23736:2020 in six parts.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>From W3C</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-spec.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB 3.2, Abstract and Outline
| Final W3C Community Group Specification (08 May 2019) </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-overview.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB 3 Overview | Final W3C Community Group Specification (08 May 2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-packages.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB Packages 3.2 | Final W3C Community Group Specification (08 May 2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-contentdocs.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB Content Documents 3.2 | Final W3C Community Group Specification (08 May 2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-mediaoverlays.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB Media Overlays 3.2 | Final W3C Community Group Specification (08 May 2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-ocf.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB Open Container Format (OCF) 3.2 | Final W3C Community Group Specification (08 May 2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>International Digital Publishing Forum</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/301/</link>
							<tag>EPUB 3.0.1.   June 26, 2014</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/30/</link>
							<tag>EPUB 3.0.  October 11, 2011</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/201</link>
							<tag>EPUB 2.0.1.  Approved May 2010, published with editorial changes in September 2010.</tag>
							<comment>Described as a maintenance release of EPUB 2</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/31/</link>
							<tag>EPUB 3.1 (declared defunct in early 2019) | Published by IDPF as a Recommended Specification, 5 January 2017</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>EPUB 3.2 recommends compliance with the following specification for accessibility requirements.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/a11y/accessibility.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB Accessibility 1.0 --
Conformance and Discovery Requirements for EPUB Publications | IDPF (5 January 2017)</tag>
							<comment>Explicitly applies to EPUB 3.1, 3.2.  Designed to be applicable to any EPUB publication.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/Submission/epub-a11y/</link>
							<tag>EPUB Accessibility 1.0 | as submitted to W3C, 25 January 2017</tag>
							<comment>The content of this document is identical to the version at IDPF.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to EPUB (other than specifications) from the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C).</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/2017/01/pressrelease-idpf-w3c-combination.html</link>
							<tag>New Roadmap for Future of Publishing is Underway as W3C and IDPF Officially Combine (February 1, 2017)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub/</link>
							<tag>W3C Community Group Final Report: EPUB 3.2</tag>
							<comment>As of April 2020, contains final report with links to specifications for EPUB 3.2</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/community/epub3/</link>
							<tag>Main page for W3C EPUB 3 Community Group</tag>
							<comment>Possibly an alias for https://www.w3.org/publishing/groups/epub3-cg/</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/2017/02/EPUB3CGcharter</link>
							<tag>W3C EPUB 3 Community Group Charter (2017)</tag>
							<comment>Includes information on different patent policies governing IDPF committee work (RAND -- Reasonable and Non-Discriminatory) and W3C committee work (Royalty-Free)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/blog/2020/03/listen-to-the-people-the-future-of-epub-and-new-directions-for-publishing-w3c/</link>
							<tag>Listen to the People: The Future of EPUB and New Directions for Publishing @ W3C (March 18, 2020)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://w3c.github.io/epub-3-wg-charter/</link>
							<tag>EPUB 3 Working Group Charter (2020)</tag>
							<comment>As of May 2020, this was a draft proposal.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to EPUB (other than specifications) from the International Digital Publishing Forum (IDPF).</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/</link>
							<tag>IDPF Home Page (preserved as an archive since merger with W3C)</tag>
							<comment>Some links related to EPUB 3 now go to W3C.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://idpf.github.io/epub-guides/a11y-faq/</link>
							<tag>EPUB Accessibility Frequently Asked Questions.

6 September 2016 </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/a11y/techniques/techniques.html</link>
							<tag>EPUB Accessibility Techniques 1.0 (2017) | Informational document. 5 January 2017</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub-content-protection</link>
							<tag>EPUB Lightweight Content Protection: Use Cases &amp; Requirements (2012) | by Bill Rosenblatt</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/news/</link>
							<tag>IDPF Has Combined With W3C (January 31, 2017)| from IDPF</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPUB</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for EPUB</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/EPub</link>
					<tag>MobileRead Wiki: EPub</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Informal descriptions and useful diagrams of the EPUB format as a conceptual abstract model or a physical structure.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/images/epub.svg</link>
							<tag>Conceptual diagram of an EPUB 3 file</tag>
							<comment>Shows nesting of EPUB Packages for available renditions of an EPUB Publication stored in an EPUB Container.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.edrlab.org/open-standards/anatomy-of-an-epub-3-file/</link>
							<tag>Anatomy of an EPUB 3 file | from European Digital Reading Lab (EDRLab)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Assessments of the EPUB format and other reports related to the preservability of EPUB Publications and other formats used for eBooks.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.dpconline.org/images/7/73/EPUB_Assessment_v1.4a.pdf</link>
							<tag>EPUB Format Preservation Assessment, V. 1.4 (2019) | by British Library</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.harvard.edu/confluence/display/digitalpreservation/Word+Processing+Formats?preview=%2F204385883%2F207554259%2FFormat+profile+-+ePUB+v04.docx</link>
							<tag>EPUB Format Assessment (2014) | by Paul Wheatley, for Harvard Digital Preservation Services</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.dpconline.org/docs/technology-watch-reports/1230-dpctw14-01/file</link>
							<tag>Preserving eBooks.  DPC Technology Watch Report 14-01 June 2014 | by Amy Kirchhoff and Sheila Morrissey</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://openpreservation.org/system/files/epubForArchivalPreservation20072012ExternalDistribution.pdf</link>
							<tag>EPUB for archival preservation (2012) | by Johan van der Knijff, KB/ National Library of the Netherlands</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.thephilgray.com/blog/epub-dev-testing-and-debugging</link>
					<tag>EPUB Dev Testing and Debugging | from thephilgray blog</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to early history of the International Digital Publishing Forum.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20050914063910/http://www.idpf.org:80/</link>
							<tag>Welcome to the IDPF (IDPF home page as of September 2005)</tag>
							<comment>First capture of the IDPF home page after public announcement of the formation of the organization formerly known as the Open eBook Forum. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20071030212424/http://idpf.org/ocf/ocf1.0/</link>
							<tag>Open eBook Publication Structure Container Format (OCF) 1.0 (2006) | Recommended Specification,
 September 11, 2006</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20071024152816/http://www.idpf.org:80/specs.htm</link>
							<tag>IDPF Standards page (as of October 24, 2007)</tag>
							<comment>Used &quot;.epub&quot; for the combination of the three specifications:  Open Publication Structure (OPS), Open Packaging Format (OPF), and Open Container Format (OCF). </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080725161131/http://www.publishersweekly.com/article/CA6477761.html</link>
							<tag>Trade Group Moves to Make E-books More Flexible (2007) | Publishers Weekly</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080415152139/http://idpf.org:80/</link>
							<tag>IDPF home page (as of April 15, 2008)</tag>
							<comment>Uses .epub as name for the group of IDPF specifications</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080430140959/http://www.idpf.org:80/</link>
							<tag>IDPF home page (as of April 30, 2008)</tag>
							<comment>First use of capitalized &quot;EPUB&quot; on IDPF home page.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00556.ttl</link>
					<tag>NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID entry for NF00556</tag>
					<comment>Information in NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID about EPUB.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pronom/fmt/483</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/483</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM from UK National Archives about EPUB. PUID: fmt/483.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q475488</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q475488</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about EPUB. Wikidata Title ID: Q475488.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
