<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000514" titleName="Microsoft XML Paper Specification, (XPS)" shortName="MS-XPS" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
			</fdd:gdfrGenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-02-20</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Microsoft XML Paper Specification, (XPS)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The XPS (XML Paper Specification) format, developed by Microsoft, serves as a fixed-page document format, a spool file format, and a page description language (PDL) for printers.  The XPS format was designed as a &quot;paginated representation of electronic paper that is based on XML,&quot;  developed to be an important component of printer support in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Vista">Windows Vista</a> (released for distribution in January 2007) but also to be a platform-independent format that could be viewed and printed
without the application used to create it. In September 2007, Microsoft submitted a re-organized version of its XPS specification to Ecma International for approval as an international standard.  See <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/activities/XML%20Paper%20Specification/XPS%20Standard.pdf">XML Paper Specification: Working draft 1.0.1</a>.  After a few further modifications, <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-388.htm">ECMA-388: Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS)</a> was published in June 2009.  See <fddLink id="fdd000513">OpenXPS</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>The XPS document format represents a set of related pages with fixed layout, which are organized as
one or more documents to be printed together.  A file in this format
must include everything necessary to fully render its content on a display device or physical medium (for
example, paper). This includes all resources such as fonts and images that might be required to render
individual pages.   See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for details of the formats permitted for such embedded resources.</p>
			<p>To implement the fixed layout of a page, the location of every visual element on the page is precisely sized and positioned. The format offers no capability to adjust layout or reflow text content.  The XML markup used in XPS bears little relationship to the markup used in XML-based word-processing formats such as <fddLink id="fdd000397">DOCX/OOXML</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000428">ODF_text</fddLink> (.odt) or in XML-based publication formats such as <fddLink id="fdd000451">JATS</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000308">EPUB</fddLink>, all of which represent the logical structure of a document, for example, identifying headings and paragraphs.  The XPS format simply identifies runs of characters in the same font, size, and weight and locates the starting point for each run and the relative position for each character/glyph in the run.   Each page has a corresponding FixedPage &quot;part,&quot; which describes all of the visual elements to be rendered on the page. A page has a fixed size and orientation, defined by height and width attributes that specify the rectangular print area. The position of every visual element on a page is determined by co-ordinates relative to the origin (typically the top left corner) of that fixed rectangle. Markup in the FixedPage part employs Glyphs elements for runs of text and Path and Brush elements for vector graphics. A Canvas element can be used to group Glyphs and Path elements into a structure that can treated as a unit.  Raster images and fonts are stored as individual parts (in specified widely supported formats) and can be referred to by many pages in the same document.</p>
			<p>An annotated example of XPS markup for a fixed page follows.  This is based on the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/msdn-magazine/2006/january/images/cc163664.fig05.gif">sample page</a> used in the MSDN Magazine article <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/msdn-magazine/2006/january/introducing-apis-for-creating-xml-paper-specification-documents">A First Look at APIs For Creating XML Paper Specification Documents</a> from January 2006:</p>
			<p>&lt;FixedPage Width=&quot;800&quot; Height=&quot;500&quot;&gt;<br/>
				<i># the photograph is stored in the page as an image resource and referred to by the Key &quot;b0.&quot;</i>
				<br/>&lt;FixedPage.Resources&gt; &lt;ResourceDictionary&gt; &lt;ImageBrush x:Key=&quot;b0&quot; ViewportUnits=&quot;Absolute&quot; TileMode=&quot;None&quot; ViewboxUnits=&quot;Absolute&quot; Viewbox=&quot;0,0,300,300&quot; Viewport=&quot;0,0,150,150&quot; ImageSource=&quot;/Resources/Images/Image_1.jpeg&quot; /&gt; &lt;/ResourceDictionary&gt; &lt;/FixedPage.Resources&gt;<br/>&lt;Canvas RenderTransform=&quot; 1, 0, 0, 1, 20, 10&quot;&gt;<br/>
				<i># background is filled with a light grey</i>
				<br/>&lt;Path Fill=&quot;#FFEEEEEE&quot; Data=&quot;F0 M 0, 0 L 800, 0 800, 500 0, 500Z&quot; /&gt;<br/>
				<i># lines of text positioned relative to top left with font, font size, and text color specified</i>
				<br/>&lt;Glyphs OriginX=&quot;0&quot; OriginY=&quot;36.59&quot; FontRenderingEmSize=&quot;18&quot; FontUri=&quot;/Resources/Fonts/d79d2c70-3b70-4e00-a376- bee81a5fc96e.ODTTF&quot; UnicodeString=&quot;This is a photo from my recent vacation.&quot; Fill=&quot;#FF000000&quot; /&gt;<br/>&lt;Glyphs OriginX=&quot;0&quot; OriginY=&quot;56.59&quot; FontRenderingEmSize=&quot;18&quot; FontUri=&quot;/Resources/Fonts/d79d2c70-3b70-4e00-a376- bee81a5fc96e.ODTTF&quot; UnicodeString=&quot;I had a great time visiting the different places&quot; Fill=&quot;#FF000000&quot; /&gt;<br/>&lt;Glyphs OriginX=&quot;0&quot; OriginY=&quot;76.59&quot; FontRenderingEmSize=&quot;18&quot; FontUri=&quot;/Resources/Fonts/d79d2c70-3b70-4e00-a376- bee81a5fc96e.ODTTF&quot; UnicodeString=&quot;and seeing all the sights, but my favorite&quot; Fill=&quot;#FF000000&quot; /&gt;<br/>&lt;Glyphs OriginX=&quot;0&quot; OriginY=&quot;96.59&quot; FontRenderingEmSize=&quot;18&quot; FontUri=&quot;/Resources/Fonts/d79d2c70-3b70-4e00-a376- bee81a5fc96e.ODTTF&quot; UnicodeString=&quot;place to visit was Cape Canaveral.&quot; Fill=&quot;#FF000000&quot; /&gt;<br/>
				<i># orange color used to fill specified rectangle (as backdrop to photograph)</i>
				<br/>&lt;Path Fill=&quot;#FFFFA500&quot; RenderTransform=&quot;1, 0, 0, 1, 60, 120&quot; Data=&quot;F0 M 0, 0 L 150, 0 150, 150 0, 150Z&quot; /&gt;<br/>
				<i># finally, the static resource with Key &quot;b0&quot; (i.e., the photograph) is used to fill a specified rectangle</i>
				<br/>&lt;Path Fill=&quot;{StaticResource b0}&quot; RenderTransform=&quot;1, 0, 0, 1, 40, 140&quot; Data=&quot;F0 M 0, 0 L 150, 0 150, 150 0, 150Z&quot; /&gt;<br/>&lt;/Canvas&gt;<br/>&lt;/FixedPage&gt;</p>
			<p>The logical form of an XPS document is a hierarchy of &quot;parts&quot; in an Open Packaging Conventions (OPC) package, using Version 6.2.0 of the <fddLink id="fdd000355">ZIP</fddLink> format as physical container.  The normative reference in the XPS specification for OPC is to <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%202%20(PDF).zip">ECMA-376, Edition 1: Part 2, Open
Packaging Conventions</a> (December 2006), but an XPS file will also conform to the successor <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML</fddLink> as described on this website. </p>
			<p>The parts in an XPS file represent a fixed payload, which has at its root a FixedDocumentSequence part, allowing one or more documents to be stored in the same XPS package, each in a FixedDocument part. A FixedDocument part is an easily indexed root for all pages within the document, identifying a sequence of FixedPage parts and an optional DocumentStructure part (which can support an outline, table of contents, and internal links).  In addition to the markup illustrated above, a FixedPage part can also incorporate chunks of text and graphics stored in a separate StoryFragments part.  The hierarchy of parts is shown in one form as <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/msdn-magazine/2006/january/images/cc163664.fig01.gif">Figure 1: Logical Hierarchy of an XPS Document</a>, a diagram in <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/msdn-magazine/2006/january/introducing-apis-for-creating-xml-paper-specification-documents">A First Look at APIs For Creating XML Paper Specification Documents</a>.  Figure 2 on page 10 of the <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/activities/XML%20Paper%20Specification/TC46%20XPS%20White%20Paper.pdf">Ecma OpenXPS Whitepaper (TC46)</a> shows a more complete set of possible parts in the package for an XPS document.</p>
			<p>In the OPC package, the relationships between parts are defined through links from source parts to named target parts using a URI syntax for the names.  There are no constraints in the XPS specification or schemas on the naming of parts beyond those relating to characters allowed by the OPC specification.  However, the section <i>2.2 Part Naming Recommendations</i> in the XPS specification recommends a well-defined, human-readable naming convention for parts, so that the package is easier to browse when unzipped and specific parts are more easily located. Following this convention, the parts in an example XPS file containing two documents might be named as follows:</p>
			<p>/FixedDocSeq.fdseq
<br/>/Documents/1/FixedDocument.fdoc
<br/>/Documents/1/Pages/1.fpage
<br/>/Documents/1/Pages/2.fpage
<br/>/Documents/1/Resources/Fonts/FontA.ttf
<br/>/Documents/1/Resources/Images/ImageB.jpg
<br/>/Documents/1/Metadata/Document_PT.xml
<br/>/Documents/1/Metadata/Page5_PT.xml
<br/>/Documents/1/Structure/DocStructure.struct
<br/>/Documents/1/Structure/Fragments/1.frag
<br/>/Documents/1/Structure/Fragments/2.frag
<br/>/Documents/2/FixedDocument.fdoc
<br/>/Documents/2/Pages/1.fpage
<br/>/Documents/2/Resources/Fonts/FontB.ttf
<br/>/Documents/2/Resources/Images/ImageA.png
<br/>/Documents/2/Metadata/ColorProfile.icm
<br/>/Documents/2/Metadata/Document_PT.xml
<br/>/Metadata/Job_PT.xml
<br/>/Resources/Fonts/63B51F81-C868-11D0-999C-00C04FD655E1.ttf</p>
			<p>The compilers of this resource have made no attempt to determine the degree to which this naming convention is followed when XPS files are created in contexts other than Microsoft Windows or whether viewers for XPS documents can handle files in which this naming convention is not followed. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>Note that parts with &quot;_PT&quot; in their names in the example above are associated with &quot;print tickets&quot; that are optional instructions for printing.  The XPS specification incorporates a <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/printdocs/print-schema-related-technologies">Print Schema</a> that specifies markup for PrintTicket parts and specifies how such parts should be associated with FixedDocumentSequence, FixedDocument, and
FixedPage parts.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>A proprietary, openly documented specification developed by Microsoft for a format used as a fixed, page-oriented document format, spool file format, and page description language for printers. Introduced as a key part of Windows Vista, released in January 2007.  Precursor to the international standard OpenXPS format (ECMA-388).</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Microsoft&apos;s XPS format was designed as a final-state format, for printing and distribution to end users for viewing.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>XPS is a subtype of <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%202%20(PDF).zip">ECMA-376, Edition 1: Part 2, Open
Packaging Conventions</a> (December 2006), which is a predecessor to OPC/OOXML as described on this website.  Edition 1 of <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376</a> has not been described separately on this website.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for information on the version of OPC that is the basis for MS-XPS and minor differences between that version and <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>. </fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000355</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ZIP_6_2_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>ZIP File Format, Version 6.2.0 (PKWARE)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Various features of the ZIP File Format are not permitted in OPC and thus not in XPS.  Details on the use of ZIP in OPC are in section 9 and Annex C of <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/ECMA-376,%20Fourth%20Edition,%20Part%202%20-%20Open%20Packaging%20Conventions.zip">ECMA-376, Edition 1: Part 2, Open Packaging Conventions</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000396</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MCE/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (Office Open XML)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Formally, an XPS document may employ markup from the Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (MCE) schema defined in ECMA-376 1st edition Part 5 (December 2006). Edition 1 of <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376</a> has not been described separately on this website. Between 2006 and 2015, there was no change in the MCE format significant to the XPS format.  All editions of ECMA-376 and ISO/IEC 29500-3 through 2015 use the same namespace for MCE: <i>http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/markup-compatibility/2006</i>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000513</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>OpenXPS</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Open XML Paper Specification, ECMA-388 (.oxps)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress has acquired a small number of files with the .xps extension, probably through web crawling.  In early 2020, ~200 files had been stored among its digital collections.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>XPS (.xps) is not explicitly listed in the Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) as either Preferred or Acceptable for content in its collections in page-oriented renditions.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>The XPS format specification is proprietary to Microsoft, but made available under royalty-free copyright and patent licenses and was openly published starting in 2005, when Microsoft made a preliminary specification available to developers under the codename Metro. See, for example, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20051017154325/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx">Printing - Architecture and Driver Support (from October 2005)</a> from Microsoft&apos;s Windows Hardware and Driver Central (WHDC).</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>Version 1.0 of the XPS specification was available via the following web pages between 2006 and 2014</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20061117050048/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpsspec.mspx">http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpsspec.mspx</a>, via Internet Archive capture from November 17, 2006</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100901092723/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/xps/xpsspec.mspx">http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/xps/xpsspec.mspx</a>, via Internet Archive capture from September 1, 2010</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110312045140/http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463431">http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463431</a>, via Internet Archive capture from March 12, 2011</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140527075455/http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463431">http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463431</a>, via Internet Archive capture from May 27, 2014.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170308114055/https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463431.aspx">https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463431.aspx</a>, via Internet Archive capture from March 8, 2017.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>All the links above led to the same download file: <a href="http://download.microsoft.com/download/1/6/a/16acc601-1b7a-42ad-8d4e-4f0aa156ec3e/XPS_1_0.exe">http://download.microsoft.com/download/1/6/a/16acc601-1b7a-42ad-8d4e-4f0aa156ec3e/XPS_1_0.exe</a>, which runs to produce a copy of the XPS specification in the .xps format.  The compilers of this resource have not located any updated Microsoft specification for XPS.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=11816">Microsoft XML Paper Specification Essentials Pack Version 1.2 (12/2/2012)</a> includes tools for developers.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Windows Vista, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Office_2007">Microsoft Office 2007</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.NET_Framework_version_history#.NET_Framework_3.0">.NET Framework 3.0</a> all employed XPS and were released together in January 2007.  Microsoft included a free XPS Viewer in Windows Vista and provided viewers and other tools to support the format&apos;s use in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_2000">Windows 2000</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_XP">Windows XP</a> (released in 2001) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Server_2003">Windows Server 2003</a>.  Support for creating XPS documents in Windows has continued in later versions of Windows.  For example, Word 2016 for Windows offers the option to Save As an XPS (.xps) file.</p>
			<p>Some companies producing software for the commercial printing industry worked closely with Microsoft in the development of XPS technology.  These included Global Graphics and Software Imaging; see <a href="https://www.globalgraphics.com/news/ggpress.nsf/GGRVPressReleasesPublished/386F31DF85D23118802571000042540A">Global Graphics and Software Imaging announce compatibility across print solutions for Microsoft&apos;s XPS document format</a> from January 2006. Many printer manufacturers developed XPS drivers or integrated Microsoft&apos;s driver into their products.  Mentioned in <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20051026083438/http://download.microsoft.com/download/D/A/A/DAA7245D-E01D-46A4-AB70-3A95ED3F6934/DocTechnologiesFS.doc">Metro Document Technologies Fact Sheet</a>
from April 25, 2005
are vendors developing or evaluating early versions of XPS-based products, including Xerox, Brother Information and Document Co., Canon Inc., HP, Monotype Imaging Inc., Peerless Systems Corp., Ricoh Company Ltd., Seiko Epson Corp., and Zoran Corp.  All the mainstream printer manufacturers began to support use of XPS.</p>
			<p>The expectations for XPS as a fixed-layout document format for sharing with end users was less successful.  Support for the XPS format was never integrated into Apple&apos;s operating systems. For <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mac_OS_X_10.0
">Mac OS X 10.0</a>, released in March 2001, Apple had chosen to develop its own code associated with PDF (based on <fddLink id="fdd000316">PDF version 1.3</fddLink> which was documented by Adobe in July 2000) and to support creation of PDF files from any application.  Apple chose this version of PDF as its basis for using the same imaging model and language to describe layout and graphics on the screen and for printers.  See <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/archive/documentation/GraphicsImaging/Conceptual/drawingwithquartz2d/dq_pdf/dq_pdf.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP30001066-CH214-TPXREF101">PDF Document Creation, Viewing, and Transforming</a> in the Quartz 2D Programming Guide and the description of the <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/coregraphics">Core Graphics framework</a> for Mac OS X and iOS.  The Core Graphics framework is based on Quartz 2D, a two-dimensional drawing engine accessible in the iOS environment and from all Mac OS X application environments since 2001. Mac OS X came with the Preview application, which was a PDF Viewer, and users could print to PDF.  See <a href="https://planetpdf.com/planetpdf/pdfs/pdf2k/01W/rosenthol_macosxpdf.pdf">Mac OS X and PDF: The Real Story</a> by Leonard Rosenthol. Although XPS viewers were developed for Mac OS X by third parties, there was little reason for Mac users to acquire them.  As a result, PDF continued as the de facto standard for sharing documents for viewing and review in contexts where it was important to reach a wide audience.  The compilers of this resource have not investigated the degree to which XPS may have been used for archiving documents for internal use in corporate settings. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>A number of tools have been developed for viewing and converting XPS documents.  See <a href="#useful">Useful References below</a>.</p>
			<p>In 2018, support for OpenXPS and XPS was dropped in some contexts where the formats were supported previously. <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/deployment/planning/windows-10-removed-features">Features and functionality removed in Windows 10</a> indicates that starting with the April 2018 release, the XPS Viewer utility would require special action for installation in Windows.  Adobe&apos;s Acrobat Pro (for Windows) used to import XPS files, but has withdrawn default support.  As of early 2020, an Adobe help file, entitled <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/acrobat/kb/unable-convert-xps-to-pdfs.html">Unable to convert XPS files to PDFs</a>, states that &quot;With December 2018 release of Acrobat, converting XPS files to PDFs is disabled&quot;  and that support can be re-enabled using the Windows Registry Editor. It appears to the compilers of this resource that the availability of well-supported tools for viewing XPS files in the future cannot be guaranteed. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>By early 2006, Microsoft offered a royalty-free <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060627035414/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpscopyright.mspx">copyright license</a> to copy and distribute the XPS specification and a royalty-free <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20070314061209/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpspatentlic.mspx">patent license</a> to implement and use XPS technology. See <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20061106063225/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpslicense.mspx">XML Paper Specification Licensing Overview (from 2006)</a> and <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/windows/hardware/design/dn641614(v=vs.85)#licensing">XML Paper Specification Licensing Overview (as online in early 2020)</a>.</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>Very good. At the container level, transparency corresponds to that of <fddLink id="fdd000354">ZIP_PK</fddLink>.  Many tools exist to permit browsing and extraction of the files contained in ZIP archives. The parts/files that represent the structure of an OPC package and the XPS document text, layout, and vector graphics are all in XML and thus both human readable and easily machine processable.</p>
			<p>Transparency also depends on non-XML resources that can be embedded, including fonts and raster images in widely used formats. See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below on formats allowed for embedded resources.</p>
			<p>Embedded fonts may be obfuscated.   Embedded font obfuscation is a means of preventing casual misappropriation of embedded fonts.  It is not considered a strong encryption of the font data. An algorithm is provided in the specification for reversing the obfuscation.</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Document-level descriptive metadata is optional. An XPS document may contain the <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC</fddLink> part with the name Core Properties. This part has fifteen elements, all optional and all non-repeatable. Six are selected from the main Dublin Core Metadata Initiative (DCMI) set (title; creator; description; subject; identifier; language) and two from the supplementary dcterms vocabulary (created; modified).  Compilers of this resource have used Word 2016 to Save As an XPS file.  This created an XPS file with a Core Properties part with values derived from properties of the source DOCX file.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>All content to be rendered must be contained in the XPS Document, including images and fonts.  The payload of an XPS file includes the full set of parts required for processing the file starting at the root FixedDocumentSequence
part.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>The XPS specification does not have internal support for encryption, or other forms
of content protection, other than obfuscation of embedded fonts, which is required for fonts that are not freely licensed. An algorithm is provided in the specification for reversing the obfuscation.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>An XPS file may consist of a single image or have images positioned on fixed pages.  Formats permitted are: JPEG in <fddLink id="fdd000018">JFIF</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000147">EXIF</fddLink> containers; <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink>; <fddLink id="fdd000022">TIFF</fddLink> (compressed and uncompressed); and Windows Media Photo (<fddLink id="fdd000243">WMP</fddLink>), later known as HD Photo and JPEG XR.  See specific formats for additional detail on image quality factors.</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>High-quality color for printing, includng the printing of photographs, was an important objective for XPS.  Excellent support for high spatial resolution and high bit-depth for colors, depending on the image format used.  See <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20051027034803/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/vista_print.mspx">XPS and Color Printing Enhancements in Windows Vista (September 2005)</a>.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>XPS producers and consumers must support sRGB,
scRGB, and CMYK color data and provide color management
using ICC Version 2.1.0 profiles.  See <a href="http://www.color.org/icc34.pdf">ICC Profile Format Specification, Version 3.4 (August 15, 1997)</a>, which is a normative reference for the XPS 1.0 specification.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>XPS has rich support for 2D vector graphics, using markup defined in the XPS specification, which is compatible with the markup used for graphics to be rendered on the screen in the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/framework/wpf/">Windows Presentation Foundation</a>, also introduced with Windows Vista.  Drawing operations supported include line, horizontal line, vertical line, cubic Bézier curve,
quadratic Bézier curve, smooth cubic Bézier curve, and elliptical arc.  A region can be filled with a solid color, a raster image, a drawing, or color gradients (linear or radial).</fdd:graphics>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>
				<p>The XPS format is not designed to support wordprocessing or document design.  The expectation is that an XPS file will be created by an automated process to produce a document with fixed pagination and layout.  For example, Windows Vista offered a virtual printer, Microsoft XPS Document Writer, which created a file in the XPS format.</p>
				<p>Although not intended as a word-processing format, the XPS format was designed to support convenient full text indexing and text selection and extraction.  Textual data is represented internally as Unicode strings. [Note: There is no reason why an XPS file should not be composed of page images, for example, images output by a scanner.  However, the compilers of this resource have not attempted to determine whether this is common practice. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.]</p>
				<p>A Unicode value in a UnicodeString is typically represented by a single UTF-16
code unit and has a single corresponding glyph representation in a font.  A mapping mechanism is available to support more complex situations, such as those required for ligatures and in many non-Latin scripts.</p>
			</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>An XPS document does not represent the structure of a document with tags representing the logical/semantic structure.  The format does support named anchors for pages or for locations on pages.  These can be used by the software creating the file to assemble a table of contents or internal links within the document that matches the functionality of a source word-processing document.  The degree to which the XPS file will represent the creator&apos;s intent for document structure will depend on the capabilities of the software (e.g., a virtual printer) that transforms the document in the format for the software used by the creator into the XPS format.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>
				<p>The XPS format is designed to represent a page-oriented document with fixed layout. The degree to which the XPS file will represent the creator&apos;s intent for layout will depend on the capabilities of the software (e.g., a virtual printer) that transforms the document in the format for the software used by the creator into the XPS format.</p>
				<p>XPS requires that fonts be embedded, in order to avoid the need for font substitution, which can interfere with layout integrity when the correct font is not available.  XPS took advantage of recent developments in font formats, by requiring use of the latest OpenType Font Format, from <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/otspec140/">OpenType Specification, Version 1.4 (2004)</a>.  This version of OpenType was a Microsoft specification, but incorporated TrueType (developed by Apple) and was based on collaboration with Adobe.  This version of OpenType had been adopted by MPEG by reference and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110605091909/http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/pressroom/pressreleases/200508/081505OpenTypeISO.html">submitted in August 2005</a> by Microsoft and Adobe for formal approval by ISO as an international standard.  The next version of OpenType was published as <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c043466_ISO_IEC_14496-22_2007(E).zip">ISO/IEC 14496-22: 2007</a>.</p>
			</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>Can be represented visually by embedded graphics.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>The XPS specification provides recommendations for creating documents that address accessibility requirements and also provides guidance for screen readers.</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>xps</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.ms-xpsdocument">IANA registration for XPS</a> from 2006.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.ms-xpsdocument</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.ms-xpsdocument">IANA registration for XPS</a> from 2006.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 50 4B 03 04</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: P K etx eot</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>This 4-byte magic number applies to all formats based on the <fddLink id="fdd000354">ZIP-PK</fddLink> format.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>XML namespace declaration</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>http://schemas.microsoft.com/xps/2005/06</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>This namespace declaration occurs in the mandatory FixedDocumentSequence part that serves as the root of the content in a Microsoft XPS file (package). In the specification, the extension <i>fdseq</i> is recommended but not mandated for this part.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Type=&quot;http://schemas.microsoft.com/xps/2005/06/fixedrepresentation&quot;</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>This type declaration will occur in the top-level Relationships part (<i>\_rels\.rels</i>) in the OPC package representing a Microsoft XPS document, as an attribute of a &lt;Relationship&gt; element within the &lt;Relationships&gt; element.  In a document that follows the naming scheme recommended in the specification, the target of this relationship will have the extension <i>fdseq</i>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM does not include an entry for Microsoft&apos;s XPS format.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q977900</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q977900">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q977900</a> which covers XPS and OpenXPS.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>XPS enhancements for color printing and graphics in Windows Vista</b>:  XPS was designed to address increasing demand for color laser printing and color fidelity and increasing use of advanced graphics and color in documents.  XPS introduced 16-bits-per-channel color printing, twice the existing standard at the time, and integrated support for the wide color gamut <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ScRGB">scRGB</a> color space.  XPS printing provided more faithful rendering of graphics attributes such as gradients and transparency though native support of these attributes in the XPS spool file format.  For vector graphics, XPS specifies markup for graphics primitives compatible with the Windows Presentation Foundation markup introduced for screen display in Windows Vista (e.g., Path, Brush, and Glyphs).</p>
			<p>
				<b>Version of OPC on which OpenXPS is based:</b> OpenXPS and Microsoft&apos;s XPS formats are subtypes of the Open Packaging Conventions (OPC) as specified in <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%202%20(PDF).zip">ECMA-376, Part 2, 1st edition (December 2006)</a>. The only significant difference between this and later versions of OPC, including ISO/IEC 29500-2 versions through <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, is an expansion of characters permitted in names for parts in a package.  In contrast to <i>ECMA-376, Part 2, 1st edition</i>, later editions permit part names in the package to be IRIs (Internationalized Resource Identifiers) as defined in <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3987.txt">RFC 3987</a>, not simply URIs as defined in <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3986.txt">RFC 3986</a>.  Since this was an extension to OPC rather than a restriction, XPS files are also subtypes of <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.  [Note: Editions of OPC published since 2008 as ISO/IEC 29500-2 and ECMA-376 Part 2 describe the same format, with textual changes representing corrections and clarifications.  The same namespaces and package-wide relationships defined in ECMA-376 Part 2 are valid in ISO/IEC 29500-2: 2012, the most recent published version of this part of ISO/IEC 29500 as of late 2019.]</p>
			<p>
				<b>Formats allowed for embedded resources: </b>  The raster image formats that can be embedded in an XPS document were selected for their wide support: JPEG in <fddLink id="fdd000018">JFIF</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000147">EXIF</fddLink> containers; <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink>; <fddLink id="fdd000022">TIFF</fddLink> (compressed and uncompressed); and Windows Media Photo (<fddLink id="fdd000243">WMP</fddLink>), later known as HD Photo and JPEG XR.</p>
			<p>Fonts are stored in font parts. All fonts used in XPS documents must adhere to the OpenType font format. As normative references, the XPS specification cites <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/otspec140/">version 1.4 of Microsoft&apos;s OpenType Specification</a> and Microsoft&apos;s <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20011115000607/http://www.microsoft.com/typography/otspec/otff.htm">OpenType Font File specification from 2001</a>.  The OpenType specification incorporates TrueType and CFF font formats. To support portability,
Unicode-encoded fonts are recommended.  Fonts
may be subsetted based on usage in the document. Although a subsetted font does not contain all
the glyphs in the original font, it must be a valid OpenType font file according to the specifications listed above.  Fonts that may not be legally embedded may be obfuscated as a means of preventing casual misappropriation of embedded
fonts. The specification specifies a method for obfuscation and recommends that the extension of an obfuscated Font
part name be “.odttf” for TrueType fonts and “.odttc” for
TrueType collections.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>XPS was deployed for public use in January 2007 as part of Windows Vista.  Many of the components of Vista had been made available to developers, using the codename Longhorn, over the previous few years.  At the Windows Hardware Engineering Conference (WinHEC) in May 2004, Microsoft introduced the &quot;Longhorn NextGen Printing Architecture.&quot;  See <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20040615190449/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx">Printing - Architecture and Driver Support</a> from WHDC in June 2004. By <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20050508224729/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx">early 2005</a> the printing architecture was known as Metro and a preliminary specification (version 0.7) was available for the document format specification. By <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20051017154325/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx">October 2005</a>, Metro had been renamed as XPS (XML Paper Specification).</p>
			<p>Microsoft encouraged the use of XPS by others, making a preliminary specification for XPS available under the codename Metro (as version 0.7) for download by developers in May 2005.  <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20051026083438/http://download.microsoft.com/download/D/A/A/DAA7245D-E01D-46A4-AB70-3A95ED3F6934/DocTechnologiesFS.doc">Metro Document Technologies: Fact Sheet
(April 25, 2005)</a> indicated that Microsoft planned to offer a royalty-free license for Metro when the specification and documentation were final.  By October 2005, version 0.75 of the specification was available under a royalty-free license.  The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20061214130003/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/downloads.mspx">XPS page as of December 2006</a> made version 1.0 of the specification available.  This openness was in keeping with a general move by Microsoft at the time towards platform-independent interoperability for its most widely used products. For example, in December 2005, a Technical Committee of the Ecma International standards organization (<a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/memento/tc45.htm">TC45</a>) was established to review documentation for the proposed Office Open XML (OOXML) specification submitted by Microsoft.  OOXML was approved as an international standard (<a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376</a>, 1st edition) in December 2006.  The container format used by XPS is the Open Packaging Conventions (OPC) format, published as <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%202%20(PDF).zip">Part 2 of ECMA 376, 1st edition</a>.</p>
			<p>Windows Vista included a redesigned print architecture, built around Windows Presentation Foundation (WPF). See <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/framework/wpf/advanced/printing-overview">WPF: Printing Overview</a>. Through the use of XPS, the new print architecture provided high-fidelity color printing through improved use of color management, removed limitations of the previous print subsystem, and added support for printing advanced effects such as gradients, transparency layers, etc. 
The print subsystem in Windows Vista implemented a new print path based on XPS.  The <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/framework/wpf/advanced/printing-overview#xps-print-path">XPS Print Path</a> used XPS files as the print spooler format and implemented high quality 16-bit color printing.  Applications using WPF for the user interface display (which included Office 2007 applications) could print directly to the XPS print path without the need for image or colorspace conversion.  The Microsoft XPS Document Writer was introduced as a &quot;print-to-file converter&quot; (a virtual printer) that allowed users to create XPS Document files.</p>
			<p>When Microsoft announced the Metro format in April 2005, as pointed out in <a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/microsoft-gunning-for-adobes-pdf-format/">Microsoft gunning for Adobe&apos;s PDF format?</a> from C|Net, some analysts were quick to see the format as intended to be a &quot;PDF killer.&quot;  However, unlike PDF, Microsoft was not trying to create a multimedia format or a format that allowed users to fill in a form. It was trying to address increased expectations of efficiency, quality, and fidelity associated with printing by (a) using the same methodology and compatible markup for sending data to a printer that it uses for displaying data on screen and (b) using the same format for spooling to the printer as for the viewable document.  For more on these topics and informal introductions to the format, see <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060108215031/http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/06/01/XMLPaperSpecification/default.aspx">A First Look at APIs For Creating XML Paper Specification Documents</a> from MSDN Magazine (January 2006), a <a href="https://channel9.msdn.com/blogs/scobleizer/jerry-dunietz-xml-paper-specification">video interview about XPS with Jerry Dunietz</a> from August 2005 and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060319194408/http://download.microsoft.com/download/9/c/5/9c5b2167-8017-4bae-9fde-d599bac8184a/XPSWorkflow.doc">Document Workflow Advances in Windows Vista (January 2006)</a>.</p>
			<p>When XPS was released for public use with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Vista">Windows Vista</a> in January 2007, it was also the basis for printer support in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.NET_Framework_version_history#.NET_Framework_3.0">.NET Framework 3.0</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Office_2007">Microsoft Office 2007</a>.  See the May 2007 <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/adrianford/intro">Intro</a> from a Microsoft blog on <i>XPS et cetera</i>.</p>
			<p>In September 2007, Microsoft submitted a version of the XPS specification to Ecma International as an initial draft for a neutral international standard. This version and several intermediate drafts are available at <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/memento/tc46-availabledocs.htm">TC46 - Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS): Documents</a>.  The OpenXPS standard, <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-388.htm">ECMA-388</a>, was officially adopted by the Ecma General Assembly in June 2009.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Version 1.0 of Microsoft&apos;s XML Paper Specification, dated 10/18/2006, was still available for download via microsoft.com as of early 2020. </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://download.microsoft.com/download/1/6/a/16acc601-1b7a-42ad-8d4e-4f0aa156ec3e/XPS_1_0.exe</link>
							<tag>Microsoft XML Paper Specification Version 1.0, October 18, 2006</tag>
							<comment>This is a .exe file that, when run, leads to the XPS specification and related schemas.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20181111045144/http://download.microsoft.com/download/1/6/a/16acc601-1b7a-42ad-8d4e-4f0aa156ec3e/XPS_1_0.exe</link>
							<tag>Microsoft XML Paper Specification Version 1.0, October 18, 2006 | via Internet Archive</tag>
							<comment>Included in case the live copy at the above URL is removed. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>XPS is based on the Open Packaging Conventions (OPC) and Markup
Compatibility and Extensibility (MCE) parts of the OOXML standard, which were published in December 2006 as parts of <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376</a> and in 2008, with minor changes, as parts of ISO/IEC 29500.  Formally, XPS is based on the first ECMA-376 editions of OPC (Part 2) and MCE (Part 5).  The descriptions of <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000396">MCE</fddLink> on this website are based on the 2012 editions of ISO/IEC 29500.  Links below are to the specification versions that are cited in Version 1.0 of the Microsoft specification for XPS.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%202%20(PDF).zip</link>
							<tag>ECMA-376, 1st edition, Office Open XML File Formats (December 2006), Part 2, Open
Packaging Conventions</tag>
							<comment>PDF with 2 annexes in ZIP file.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%205%20(PDF).zip</link>
							<tag>ECMA-376, 1st edition, Office Open XML File Formats (December 2006), Part 5, Markup
Compatibility and Extensibility</tag>
							<comment>PDF in ZIP file</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_XML_Paper_Specification</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for Open XML Paper Specification</tag>
					<comment>Covers both Microsoft&apos;s original XPS format described here and the successor OpenXPS international standard</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technical_features_new_to_Windows_Vista#Print</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry on Technical Features New to Windows Vista: Print</tag>
					<comment>Describes the new XPS print path introduced with Windows Vista in 2007.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources with useful introductions to the XPS format and how it fitted in to the new printing architecture for Windows Vista.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20051026083438/http://download.microsoft.com/download/D/A/A/DAA7245D-E01D-46A4-AB70-3A95ED3F6934/DocTechnologiesFS.doc</link>
							<tag>Metro Document Technologies: Fact Sheet (April 25, 2005) | via Internet Archive</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060319194408/http://download.microsoft.com/download/9/c/5/9c5b2167-8017-4bae-9fde-d599bac8184a/XPSWorkflow.doc</link>
							<tag>Document Workflow Advances in Windows Vista (January 2006) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
							<comment>Includes helpful diagrams.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060108215031/http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/06/01/XMLPaperSpecification/default.aspx</link>
							<tag>XPS Documents: A First Look at APIs For Creating XML Paper Specification Documents  (MSDN Magazine, January 2006) | via Internet Archive</tag>
							<comment>The article as presented online in January 2006.  Includes a description of the structure of an XPS document file and an example of the markup for a fixed page.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ecma-international.org/activities/XML%20Paper%20Specification/TC46%20XPS%20White%20Paper.pdf</link>
							<tag>Ecma OpenXPS White Paper (June 2009) | from Ecma Technical Committee TC46</tag>
							<comment>Although this describes the international standard known as OpenXPS and published as ECMA-388, most of what is covered is relevant for XPS, including a section entitled Rationale for an Electronic Paper Format and a diagram of an example XPS document.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://channel9.msdn.com/blogs/scobleizer/jerry-dunietz-xml-paper-specification</link>
							<tag>Video interview with Jerry Dunietz about the XML Paper Specification (Aug 08, 2005)</tag>
							<comment>Dunietz was a software architect associated with the development of XPS.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Technical resources from Microsoft about the development and release of XPS.  Support for XPS was introduced with Windows Vista, .NET Framework 3.0 and the 2007 Microsoft Office System.  These products were released for general distribution in January 2007.  However, information was shared with developers well in advance.  The first capture of a Microsoft page specifically for XPS by the Internet Archive was in October 2005.  Public information about the new print architecture had been released under previous names, &quot;Longhorn NextGen Printing Architecture&quot; and &quot;Metro.&quot;  Resources from these earlier phases of the project are to be found below, towards the end of the Useful References.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20051022233658/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/default.mspx</link>
							<tag>The first capture by the Internet Archive of Microsoft&apos;s web page for XPS</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/msdn-magazine/2006/january/introducing-apis-for-creating-xml-paper-specification-documents</link>
							<tag>XPS Documents: A First Look at APIs For Creating XML Paper Specification Documents  (MSDN Magazine, January 2006) | by Bob Watson</tag>
							<comment>Includes a description of the structure of an XPS document file and an example of the markup for a fixed page.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060108215031/http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/06/01/XMLPaperSpecification/default.aspx</link>
							<tag>XPS Documents: A First Look at APIs For Creating XML Paper Specification Documents  (MSDN Magazine, January 2006) | via Internet Archive</tag>
							<comment>The article as presented online in January 2006.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20061007080306/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/default.mspx</link>
							<tag>XPS (2006) | from Microsoft&apos;s Windows Hardware Development Central (WHDC)</tag>
							<comment>States, &quot;Microsoft has integrated XPS-based technologies into the 2007 Microsoft Office system and the Microsoft Windows Vista operating system, but XPS itself is platform independent, openly published, and available royalty-free.&quot;</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080305082458/http:/www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpsspec.mspx</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification Version 1.0 (2006) | From Microsoft WHDC</tag>
							<comment>Available for download as a .exe file</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080305050816/http:/www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpscommunitypromise.mspx</link>
							<tag>Community Promise for XPS (2007) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20061106063225/http:/www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpslicense.mspx</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification Licensing Overview (2006) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20070314061209/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpspatentlic.mspx</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification Patent License (2006) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
							<comment>States, &quot;Microsoft hereby grants you a royalty-free license under Microsoft&apos;s Necessary Claims to make, use, sell, offer to sell, import, and otherwise distribute Licensed Implementations solely for the purpose of reading or writing XPS Documents, or rendering XPS Documents as allowed by the XML Paper Specification.&quot;</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060627035414/http:/www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpscopyright.mspx</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification Copyright License (2006)</tag>
							<comment>States that &quot;Permission to copy, display and distribute the contents of this document (the &quot;Specification&quot;), in any medium for any purpose without fee or royalty is hereby granted,&quot; provided that the copyright statement was retained in any copies.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The following blogs by Microsoft staff focused on the development and use of the XPS format and associated tools.  The blogs are still available on the Microsoft website, but at new locations and with new look and feel.  Many links redirect automatically but not all.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/xps/</link>
							<tag>XPS Team Blog - XML Paper Specification and the Open Packaging Conventions (2005-2009) | Microsoft blog</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/andy_simonds/xps-5-points-shortcut</link>
							<tag>Andy Simonds Blog: XPS 5-Points Shortcut (January 2006) | Microsoft blog (2005-2007)</tag>
							<comment>Andy Simonds blogged about five characteristics of XPS and the benefits to end users and developers.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/adrianford/</link>
							<tag>Adrian Ford on XPS et cetera (2007-2009) | Microsoft blog</tag>
							<comment> Adrian Ford was a program manager on the Windows documents and printing team</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.ecma-international.org/memento/tc46-availabledocs.htm</link>
					<tag>TC46 - Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS): Documents.</tag>
					<comment>Documents associated with development of the successor OpenXPS format.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Miscellaneous resources about XPS from the period between initial announcement  (as Metro) until submission to Ecma International for standardization.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.cnet.com/news/microsoft-gunning-for-adobes-pdf-format/</link>
							<tag>Microsoft gunning for Adobe&apos;s PDF format? (May 2005) | from C|Net</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.globalgraphics.com/news/ggpress.nsf/GGRVPressReleasesPublished/386F31DF85D23118802571000042540A</link>
							<tag>Global Graphics and Software Imaging announce compatibility across print solutions for Microsoft&apos;s XPS document format (January 2006)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.computerworld.com/article/2544832/with-xps-as-pdf-killer--microsoft-opens-second-front-on-adobe.html</link>
							<tag>With XPS as PDF killer, Microsoft opens second front on Adobe (2007) | from ComputerWorld</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://whattheythink.com/news/31367-global-graphics-demonstrates-its-wide-range-xps/</link>
							<tag>Global Graphics Demonstrates its Wide Range of XPS Printing Solutions Using the Company&apos;s Next Generation RIP and eDocument Platform (May 2007)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://printplanet.com/threads/future-role-of-xps.135/</link>
							<tag>Future role of XPS (discussion thread from September 2007)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.prepressure.com/library/technology/xps</link>
							<tag>Microsoft XPS | from Prepressure.com</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Miscellaneous articles about support for XPS in Windows after the release of Windows 8, which incorporated the use of the international standard <fddLink id="fdd000513">OpenXPS</fddLink> as a print spooler.  These are listed roughly chronologically, with the newest first.  In April 2018, Microsoft eliminated the XPS viewer utility from the default distribution package for Windows 10, suggesting that Microsoft does not expect to continue full support for XPS or OpenXPS.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/deployment/planning/windows-10-removed-features</link>
							<tag>Features and functionality removed in Windows 10</tag>
							<comment>Starting with update 1803 (April 2018), the XPS Viewer utility required special administrative action for installation in Windows.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.windowscentral.com/how-get-xps-viewer-app-back-windows-10-april-2018-update</link>
							<tag>How to access XPS Viewer in the Windows 10 April 2018 Update | from Windows Central</tag>
							<comment>States that &quot;Microsoft is finally retiring support for the file format and removing the XPS Viewer app on new installations.&quot;</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://windowsreport.com/handle-xps-files-windows-10/</link>
							<tag>How to Handle XPS Files In Windows 10 (2018) | from Windows Report</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.howtogeek.com/148499/what-is-an-xps-file-and-why-does-windows-want-me-to-print-to-one/</link>
							<tag>What Is an XPS File and Why Does Windows Want Me to Print to One? (2017) | from How-To Geek</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.rawinfopages.com/tips/2015/10/print-to-pdf-in-windows-10-and-forget-xps/</link>
							<tag>Print to PDF in Windows 10 and forget XPS (2015) | from Raw Computing</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-8-OpenXPS-the-Latest-PDF-Killer-226721.shtml</link>
							<tag>Windows 8 OpenXPS, the Latest PDF Killer | from Softpedia News</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/printdocs/documents</link>
							<tag>XPS Documents | from Windows Dev Center</tag>
							<comment>Although dated 05/30/2018, this information is associated with Windows 8 and earlier versions of Windows.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/printdocs/app-support-for-openxps-printing</link>
							<tag>App Support for OpenXPS Printing</tag>
							<comment>Despite being dated 05/30/2018, this relates to Windows 8 (released in 2012)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/windows/hardware/design/dn641615(v=vs.85)</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification: Overview</tag>
							<comment>Despite being dated 05/31/2017, the resources linked from this page date from as early as 2005</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20190112024614/https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/windows/hardware/design/dn641615(v=vs.85)</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification: Overview | via Internet Archive</tag>
							<comment>Included because the resource immediately above is no longer supported and may be removed. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Tools for viewing, manipulating, or converting XPS files.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.gnome.org/action/show/Projects/libgxps</link>
							<tag>libgxps | GObject based library for handling and rendering XPS documents. </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.globalgraphics.com/application/files/3815/5309/5467/brochure-mako-sdk.pdf</link>
							<tag>Mako SDK | from Global Graphics PLC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://mupdf.com/</link>
							<tag>MuPDF from Artifex | lightweight PDF, XPS, and E-book viewers tailored for mobile devices</tag>
							<comment>MuPDF runs on Android, iOS, Linux, macOS, OpenBSD, and Windows.  Open source with GNU AGPL license.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://okular.kde.org/</link>
							<tag>Okular | from KDE</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.online-convert.com/file-format/xps</link>
							<tag>Online-Convert: XPS, Microsoft XML Paper Specification File (.xps)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://convertio.co/xps-pdf/</link>
							<tag>Convertio: XPS to PDF Converter</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://convertio.co/xps-oxps/</link>
							<tag>Convertio: XPS to OXPS Converter</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.aconvert.com/format/xps/</link>
							<tag>Aconvert: Convert XPS Online</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://rootrisetech.com/product/xpsview</link>
							<tag>XPSView  (for Mac and IOS) | from RootRise Technologies</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://rootrisetech.com/product/xps-to-pdf</link>
							<tag>XPS-to-PDF | from RootRise Technologies</tag>
							<comment>Batch conversion of XPS to PDF, available for Mac OS and Windows</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.novapdf.com/convert-xps-to-pdf-kb.html</link>
							<tag>NovaPDF: Convert XPS/OXPS to PDF</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=11816</link>
							<tag>Microsoft XML Paper Specification Essentials Pack (Version 1.2) | published 12/2/2010</tag>
							<comment>Download package includes XPS Viewer EP to read XPS Documents and the Microsoft XPS Document Writer to output files to the XPS Document format.  States &quot;On 06/06/2013 12 months from 06/06/2012 this XPS Essentials Pack will no longer have support available.&quot;</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.softwareimaging.com/our-work/xps/</link>
							<tag>Software Imaging | Our Work: XML Paper Specification</tag>
							<comment>Software Imaging was involved in the early development of XPS</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.softwareimaging.com/our-work/xps-viewer/</link>
							<tag>XPS Viewer | from Software Imaging</tag>
							<comment>A free, stand-alone application for Windows. Based on Software Imaging’s PrintMagicXPS toolkit.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to precursors to XPS.  Immediately prior to adoption of &quot;XPS&quot; as the name for the format, the codename Metro was used.  Earlier, the name &quot;Longhorn NextGen Printing Architecture&quot; has been used for the project that led to Metro and XPS.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20040615190449/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx</link>
							<tag>Printing - Architecture and Driver Support (June 2004) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
							<comment>Note that many links from this page are to resources that were not captured by Internet Archive. Presented &quot;Longhorn NextGen Printing Architecture.&quot;  Longhorn was a codename for what became Windows Vista.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20050305122734/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx</link>
							<tag>Printing - Architecture and Driver Support (March 2005) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
							<comment>Very similar to the June 2004 version of the page.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20050508224729/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx</link>
							<tag>Printing - Architecture and Driver Support (May 2005) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
							<comment>By May 5, 2005, the format specification and new print path architecture used the Metro codename.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20051017154325/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/device/print/default.mspx</link>
							<tag>Printing - Architecture and Driver Support
(October 2005) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
							<comment>By October 2005, Metro was renamed XML Paper Specification (XPS).</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20051026083438/http://download.microsoft.com/download/D/A/A/DAA7245D-E01D-46A4-AB70-3A95ED3F6934/DocTechnologiesFS.doc</link>
							<tag>&quot;Metro&quot; Document Technologies: Fact Sheet
(April 25, 2005) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://download.microsoft.com/download/5/D/6/5D6EAF2B-7DDF-476B-93DC-7CF0072878E6/metro_FAQ.doc</link>
							<tag>Metro Print Path FAQ (April 25, 2005) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20051022233658/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/default.mspx</link>
							<tag> Hub for information about XPS (XML Paper Specification). (October 2005) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20051027034803/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/vista_print.mspx</link>
							<tag>XPS and Color Printing Enhancements in Windows Vista (September 2005) | from Microsoft WHDC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to OpenType, the font specification incorporated into the XPS format.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20011115000607/http://www.microsoft.com/typography/otspec/otff.htm</link>
							<tag>The OpenType Font File (2001)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/otspec140/</link>
							<tag>OpenType Specification, Version 1.4.  (2004)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/</link>
							<tag>OpenType overview</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q977900</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q977900</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about XML Paper Specification.   Wikidata Title ID: Q977900</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
