<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000532" titleName="PDF/A-4, PDF for Long-term Preservation, Use of ISO 32000-2" shortName="PDF/A-4" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2025-07-25</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>ISO 19005-4:2020
Document management — Electronic document file format for long-term preservation — Part 4: Use of ISO 32000-2 (PDF/A-4)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>Portable Document Format (PDF)</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>PDF/A</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>PDF</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>PDF/A-4, developed as an international standard and approved in November 2020 as <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/71832.html">ISO 19005-4:2020</a> is a constrained form of the Portable Document Format (PDF) as defined in <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/75839.html">ISO 32000-2:2020</a>.  The primary purpose of ISO 19005 is &quot;to define a file format based on PDF, known as PDF/A, which
provides a mechanism for representing electronic documents in a manner that preserves their visual
appearance over time, independent of the tools and systems used for creating, storing or rendering the
files.&quot;  Each part of ISO 19005 is based on a particular underlying PDF specification.  Note that all versions of the PDF/A specifications are considered current; there is no expectation that content compliant to earlier PDF/A versions will be converted to PDF/A-4. Previous versions are as follows:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ISO 19005-1:2005 -- Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (<fddLink id="fdd000125">PDF/A-1</fddLink>)</li>
				<li>ISO 19005-2:2011 -- Part 2: Use of ISO 32000-1 (<fddLink id="fdd000319">PDF/A-2</fddLink>)</li>
				<li>ISO 19005-3:2011 -- Part 3: Use of ISO 32000-1 with support for embedded files (<fddLink id="fdd000360">PDF/A-3</fddLink>).  PDF/A-3 is an extension of PDF/A-2 with a single and highly significant feature, support for embedding files in any arbitrary format within the PDF/A-3 file. See <fddLink id="fdd000360">PDF/A-3</fddLink> for use cases and examples that illustrate motivation for embedding files in archival PDF files.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>PDF/A-4 is based on PDF 2.0 (as defined in ISO 32000-2:2020) and the specification provides
recommendations on handling content that uses some of the newer features in PDF 2.0,
including page level output intents.
 Some content in the PDF/A-2 or PDF/A-3 specifications has been dropped from the PDF/A-4 specification because it is included in the base PDF 2.0.  For example, requirements for embedding associated files are in subclause 14.13 of the 2020 dated revision of ISO 32000-2.  Earlier requirements relating to features deprecated in PDF 2.0 may not be found individually in the PDF/A-4 specification, which has a blanket prohibition on use of such deprecated features. The PDF/A-4 specification also makes some significant changes over previous versions in allowing non-static content that can be
present in PDF documents, such as form fields and <fddLink id="fdd000443">ECMAScript</fddLink> (often referred to as Javascript). A number of requirements have been totally removed.  For example, special requirements for embedding XMP Extension Schemas to allow custom metadata properties in earlier PDF/A versions (see <a href="https://pdfa.org/resource/technical-note-tn-0009-xmp-extension-schemas-in-pdfa-1/">Technical Note 0009: XMP Extension Schemas in PDF/A-1</a>) have been dropped.  Most significantly, the separate conformance levels, A, B, and U are not used in PDF/A-4.  As a result, the subclause from the PDF/A-2 and PDF/A-3 specifications that described requirements for the highest conformance level (A) intended to represent the logical structure of a document and ensure the recovery of text in natural reading order is missing entirely, replaced by encouragement to incorporate higher-level semantic information following guidance in the <fddLink id="fdd000350">PDF/UA</fddLink> family of standards (ISO 14289).  Note that an updated version of PDF/UA, to be based on PDF 2.0, is under development but not yet published.  The current version of PDF/UA is <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/64599.html">ISO 14289-1:2014
Document management applications — Electronic document file format enhancement for accessibility — Part 1: Use of ISO 32000-1 (PDF/UA-1)</a>.  In line with the middle conformance level (U) in PDF/A-2 and PDF/A-3, all fonts in PDF/A-4 require Unicode mappings, including OCR text from scanned documents.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>A number of additional requirements from earlier PDF/A versions are relaxed. For example, archiving of fillable forms is better supported. PDF/A-4 also seeks to preserve more information in
the file (by not requiring its removal during conversion to the archival format) and puts a greater burden on
conforming viewers to ensure that such information does not alter the visual appearance of the file during
consumption.  Javascript can now be preserved in the file, for example to store information about an interactive form’s values or
logic, but must be stored in an embedded file stream and not executed by a &quot;conforming interactive processor&quot; without explicit action by a user. A conforming
processor that is non-interactive must not execute scripts at all.  Note that the PDF/A-4 specification replaces the concept of an &quot;interactive reader&quot; used in earlier PDF/A specifications with &quot;interactive processor.&quot;  The compilers of this resource have not located any PDF processing software that declares itself as a conforming processor of PDF/A-4 documents that is either interactive or non-interactive. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>Annotation types of Sound, Screen and Movie are not permitted in a PDF/A-4 file. Sound and Movie annotations are deprecated in PDF 2.0, replaced by a more general RichMedia annotation type. A Screen annotation specifies a region of a page upon which media clips may be played; the RichMedia annotation type provides equivalent functionality. Annotations are restricted in other ways to prevent the use of annotations that are hidden or that are viewable
but not printable. Annotations of 3D and RichMedia types are only permitted in a <fddLink id="fdd000651">PDF/A-4e</fddLink> compliant file.</p>
			<p>This version of PDF/A has two new subsidiary profiles, defined in annexes. Annex A defines <fddLink id="fdd000652">PDF/A-4f</fddLink>, a profile that allows files in any other format to be embedded. Note that this is not considered a replacement for the <fddLink id="fdd000360">PDF/A-3</fddLink> standard, the earlier PDF/A variant allowing arbitrary embedded files. Annex B defines <fddLink id="fdd000651">PDF/A-4e</fddLink>, intended for engineering documents and acting as a successor to the <fddLink id="fdd000495">PDF/E-1</fddLink> standard.  PDF/A-4e supports Rich Media and 3D Annotations as well as embedded files.</p>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink> for more information on the PDF/A family of standards.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>A constrained form of Adobe PDF version 2.0 (as defined in ISO 32000-2:2020)intended to be suitable for archiving page-oriented documents for which PDF is already being used in practice. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>A final-state format for delivery to end users and long-term preservation of the document as disseminated to users.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000030</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Portable Document Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000474</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF_2_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF, Version 2.0  (ISO 32000-2:2020)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000651</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A-4e</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF/A for Engineering, Use of ISO 32000-2 (PDF/A-4): ISO 19005-4, Annex B</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000652</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A-4f</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF/A for Embedded Files, Use of ISO 32000-2 (PDF/A-4): ISO 19005-4, Annex A</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Extension of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000318</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF for Long-term Preservation</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000319</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A-2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF for Long-term Preservation, Use of ISO 32000-1 (PDF 1.7)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000360</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A-3</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF/A-3, ISO 19005-3:2012</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>LC was represented on the working group for the original PDF/A standard and continues to participate in the development of new versions.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) lists <fddLink id="fdd000651">PDF/A-4e</fddLink> as a acceptable format for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/design3D.html">2D and 3D Computer Aided Design - vector</a> formats. <p>See also  <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.  </p>
		</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>Open standard, published by ISO in November 2020.  Developed under the auspices of  <a href="https://www.iso.org/committee/53674.html">ISO/TC 171 SC2</a>, for which the PDF Association (<a href="https://pdfa.org/">PDFA</a>) was acting as secretariat at the time of publication.  The particular working group responsible is ISO/TC 171/SC 2/WG 5, described by ISO as &quot;Joint TC 171/SC 2 - TC 42 - TC 46/SC 11 - TC 130 WG: Document management applications - Application issues - PDF/A.&quot;  A formal dated revision of PDF/A-4 is currently being prepared by ISO TC 171 SC 2 WG 5 in 2025 and errata are listed on the PDF Association's <a href="https://github.com/pdf-association/pdf-issues/issues?q=is%3Aissue+label%3APDF%2FA-4">GitHub repository</a>. </p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>
				<a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/71832.html">ISO 19005-4:2020.	Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -- Part 4: Use of ISO 32000-2 (PDF/A-4)</a>. The standard cannot be used without <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/75839.html">ISO 32000-2:2020. Document management -- Portable document format -- Part 2: PDF 2.0</a>, which it uses as a normative reference.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink> for a discussion of adoption of PDF/A in general, bearing in mind that much written about PDF/A considers primarily PDF/A-1 and PDF/A-2.</p>
			<p>The specifications for PDF/A-4 and for the dated revision of PDF 2.0 on which it is based were published in late 2020.  As of December 2020, of the mainstream commercial PDF creation, editing, and conversion applications and libraries, only a few have released versions with PDF/A-4 support. <a href="https://bfo.com/blog/2020/12/11/bfo_pdf_library_2_24_4_whats_new/">Big Faceless PDF library</a> also announced support in December 2020.  It is likely that other products that have supported <fddLink id="fdd000360">PDF/A-3</fddLink> for enterprise use will be updated to support PDF/A-4, including the PDF/A-4f profile which, like PDF/A-3 allows embedding of files in any format.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>The embedding of arbitrary files in a PDF poses challenges for archival institutions both for ingestion workflows and for long-term preservation management and access.  The British Library&apos;s <a href="https://wiki.dpconline.org/images/2/22/PDFA_Assessment_v1.0.pdf">PDF Format Preservation Assessment Part 2: PDF/A Profile</a> recommends that &quot;Receipt or deposit of PDF/A is recommended to prefer the PDF/A-1 profile rather than PDF/A-2 and 3 to reduce the risk concerning attached files.&quot;  As of December 2020, several lists of preferred formats from archival institutions list PDF/A-1 and PDF/A-2 as preferred formats for textual content but explicitly do not list PDF/A-3.   These include the <a href="https://www.archives.gov/records-mgmt/policy/transfer-guidance-tables.html#textualdata">U.S. National Archives and Records Administration (NARA)</a>; and the Canadian Government&apos;s <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/heritage-information-network/services/digital-preservation/recommendations-file-format.html#a6a1">National Heritage Digitization Strategy -- Digital Preservation File Format Recommendations</a>. </p>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000360">PDF/A-3</fddLink> in the Adoption and Notes sections for use cases presented by proponents of the extension to allow embedding of files in other formats in a PDF/A document.</p>
			<p>One important use case for PDF/A with embedded files is in manufacturing.  See <a href="https://3dpdfconsortium.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/PDF_in_Manufacturing.pdf">PDF in Manufacturing: The future of 3D documentation</a>, developed and published jointly by the 3D PDF Consortium and the PDF Association in May 2020.  A PDF/A-3 file could present an interactive 3D model in the document and related files can be embedded, creating what is sometimes called a &quot;technical data package&quot; or TDP.  Changes introduced with <fddLink id="fdd000651">PDF/A-4e</fddLink>, the PDF/A-4 profile intended as a successor to the <fddLink id="fdd000495">PDF/E-1</fddLink> standard, are likely to increase adoption of PDF/A in this domain.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No concerns for <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink> per se.  Licensing or patent concerns may arise for embedded files.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink> in relation to PDF/A-1 and PDF/A-2.  For PDF/A-3 and PDF/A-4, transparency and characterization of non-PDF/A-4 embedded files are primary concerns for long-term preservation.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>As for earlier versions of PDF/A, the intent of the PDF/A-4 specification is to encourage the provision of descriptive, administrative, and provenance metadata in addition to the technical details needed to render the document visually.  For PDF/A-4, all metadata, whether for a document or for an object (such as a page or illustration), is in <a href="https://developer.adobe.com/xmp/docs/">XMP</a> packets in metadata streams. It is mandatory to have a document-level metadata stream.  Primary namespaces supported are defined in ISO 32000-2 (PDF2.0), ISO 16684-1 (XMP) and ISO 19005-4 (PDF/A-4) and have prefixes <i>dc:</i>, <i>pdf:</i>, <i>xmp:</i>, <i>xmpMM:</i> and <i>pdfaid:</i>. Extension schemas are also permitted. The requirement in PDF/A-3 that descriptions of all extension schemas used be embedded either in the referencing metadata stream or the document-level metadata stream has been dropped for PDF/A-4.  Instead, there is a recommendation that metadata streams have schemas conforming to ISO 16684-2, Description of XMP
schemas using RELAX NG stored in embedded associated files.  The compilers of this resource have not determined the degree to which extension schemas are used in PDF documents. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>As for PDF/A-2 and PDF/A-3, the specification supplies (a) options for the inclusion of identifiers from external schemes such as a Digital Object Identifier (DOI) or International Standard Book Number (ISBN) and (b) guidance on the use of the <i>xmpMM:History</i> property to record when high-level actions are taken to create or transform a PDF/A-4 file.</p>
			<p>Note: The text specifying metadata requirements for PDF/A-4 has been simplified in comparison to earlier PDF/A versions because there is no longer a requirement to ensure consistency of metadata values stored in the <i>document information dictionary</i> (identified by the <i>Info</i> &quot;key&quot; in a PDF file trailer) and values for equivalent information in XMP metadata streams. This is because PDF 2.0 has deprecated the <i>document information dictionary</i> except for very limited use.  For PDF/A-4, the <i>Info</i> key shall not be present in the trailer dictionary of PDF/A-4 conforming files unless there exists
a <i>PieceInfo</i> entry in the document catalog dictionary.  If a document information dictionary is present, it
shall only contain a <i>ModDate</i> entry. <i>PieceInfo</i> has been used since PDF 1.4 for storing vendor-specific private data associated with a document, page or form to facilitate workflows or document management. Its use has led to problems because the structure was sometimes used for information about individuals, and provided an unintentional mechanism to reveal personally identifiable information (PII). PDF 2.0 suggests the use of associated files as an alternative mechanism for vendor-specific private data.</p>
			<p>See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Accessibility Features</b>
			</p>
			<p>Unlike other members of the <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>, PDF/A-4 does not have a specific "a" level for accessibility. Instead, it encourages but doesn't mandate the inclusion of logical structure tags, and it requires Unicode mapping for all fonts. PDF/A-4 also recommends following the <fddLink id="fdd000350">PDF/UA</fddLink> standard, which provides detailed guidelines and technical specifications for creating accessible tagged PDFs.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>In comparison to earlier specifications in the <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>, PDF/A-4 does not include requirements to represent the logical structure of a document, replacing requirements for use of Tagged PDF functionality in earlier versions with a recommendation to follow guidance in the <fddLink id="fdd000350">PDF/UA</fddLink> family of standards. See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>PDF 2.0 introduced the ability to incorporate MathML and this continues for PDF/A-4. MathML can be incorporated via a structure element or XObject with the  <i>Alternative</i> value in the AFRelationship entry in the file specification dictionary.  The structure element method provides semantic context and attributes such as Bounding Box (BBox) coordinates to indicate sizing and position.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>. See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>
				<p>A PDF/A-4 file may contain geospatial information (e.g., to support geo-registration of maps or satellite imagery) or measurement properties (e.g., as used for CAD documents) using any mechanism allowed in PDF 2.0.   See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</p>
				<p>With the standards harmonization improvements introduced in <fddLink id="fdd000474">PDF 2.0</fddLink>, it's possible (although may not be practical for users without sophisticated toolsets) for a file to co-exist as a <fddLink id="fdd000124">PDF/X</fddLink> (at creation), <fddLink id="fdd000350">PDF/UA</fddLink> (after creation for accessibility remediation) and <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A</fddLink> (archiving file). </p>
			</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>pdf</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The standard does not indicate that a different extension should be used to distinguish PDF from PDF/A.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: %PDF-2.</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From the PDF/A-4 specification. &quot;The file header shall begin at byte zero and shall consist of “%PDF-2.n” followed by a single
EOL marker, where ‘n’ is a single digit number between 0 (30h) and 9 (39h).&quot; The requirement for this string to begin at byte zero is a tighter constraint than for <fddLink id="fdd000474">PDF 2.0</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Indicator for profile, level, version, etc.</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>The standard specifies that the PDF/A version and conformance level of a file shall be specified using the PDF/A Identification extension schema defined in the standard.  This schema has two mandatory elements: pdfaid:part (integer), pdfaid:rev (4-character integer of the date of publication or revision). A PDF/A-4 file should have the integer value 4 for pdfaid:part. Claim to conformance with one of the profiles defined in Annexes A and B is made in the optional pdfaid:conformance by the following single characters: E for PDF/A-4e and F for PDF/A-4f.  E and F are the only valid values for pdfaid:conformance in a PDF/A-4 file. Note that pdfaid:conformance is not mandatory for PDF/A-4 as it is for previous versions of PDF/A.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>NF00646</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00646.ttl">https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00646.ttl</a> for Portable Document Format/Archiving (PDF/A-4).</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/1910</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1910">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/1910</a> for PDF/A - Portable Document Format 4.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000651">PDF/A-4e</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000652">PDF/A-4f</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q123594568</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q123594568">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q123594568</a> for Portable Document Format/Archive, version 4.
</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000651">PDF/A-4e</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000652">PDF/A-4f</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>Fonts in PDF/A-4</b>:  The intent of the requirements in 6.2.10.2 to 6.2.10.9 in the specification is &quot;to ensure that the future rendering of
the textual content of a conforming file matches, on a glyph by glyph basis, the static
appearance of the file as originally created and, when possible, to allow the recovery of
semantic properties for each character of the textual content.&quot;  Subclause 6.2.10.4 requires that  &quot;The font programs for all fonts used for rendering within a conforming file shall be embedded within that
file, as defined in ISO 32000-2:2020, 9.9. A font is considered to be used if at least one of its glyphs is
referenced from a content stream.&quot;  In comparison with, PDF/A-2, PDF/A-4 adjusts some of constraints on embedding fonts, relating to embedding font subsets and font metrics.  The adjustments are based on differences between ISO 32000-1 and ISO 32000-2 and experience of vendors of software and services for conversion of PDF files to to PDF/A for archiving.  The compilers of this resource have not determined the degree to which these changes might be of concern to cultural heritage institutions.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Support for Unicode in PDF/A-4</b>:  The font dictionary of all fonts, regardless of their rendering mode usage, should include a
ToUnicode entry whose value is a CMap stream object that maps character codes for at
least all referenced glyphs to Unicode values,
unless the font meets at least one of the following four conditions:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>fonts that use the predefined encodings MacRomanEncoding, MacExpertEncoding or WinAnsiEncoding as defined in Annex D of the PDF 2.0 specification</li>
				<li>Type 1 and Type 3 fonts where the glyph names of the glyphs referenced are all contained
in the Adobe Glyph List or the set of named characters in the Symbol font, as defined in Annex D of the PDF 2.0 specification</li>
				<li>Type 0 fonts whose descendant CIDFont uses the Adobe-GB1, Adobe-CNS1, Adobe-
Japan1 or Adobe-Korea1 character collections</li>
				<li>Non-symbolic TrueType fonts.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The first version of PDF/A <fddLink id="fdd000125">PDF/A-1</fddLink> was published in 2005 as ISO 19005–1:2005.</p>
			<p>Since the intention of the PDF/A family of formats is to support long-term preservation, all versions of PDF/A are considered to be current specifications.</p>
			<p>The primary difference between PDF/A-1 and PDF/A-2 was the use of a later underlying version of PDF.  Added capabilities, all in compliance with ISO 32000-1, included:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Improvements to tagged PDF (for enhanced accessibility)</li>
				<li>Compressed Object and XRef streams (for smaller file sizes)</li>
				<li>Support for embedding of PDF/A-compliant file attachments, portable collections and PDF packages</li>
				<li>Support for transparency in images</li>
				<li>Support for JPEG 2000 compression for images</li>
			</ul>
			<p>PDF/A-3 is equivalent to PDF/A-2 except for allowing files in any format to be embedded.</p>
			<p>PDF/A-4, a version of PDF/A based on <fddLink id="fdd000474">PDF 2.0</fddLink> (ISO 32000-2) was published as <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/71832.html">ISO 19005-4:2020</a> in November 2020.  In early presentations PDF/A-4 was referred to as PDF/A-NEXT.</p>
			<p> See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/71832.html</link>
					<tag>ISO 19005-4:2020
Document management — Electronic document file format for long-term preservation — Part 4: Use of ISO 32000-2 (PDF/A-4)</tag>
					<comment>Catalog record, preview, and opportunity to purchase</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/75839.html</link>
					<tag>ISO 32000-2:2020
Document management — Portable document format — Part 2: PDF 2.0</tag>
					<comment>Catalog record, preview, and opportunity to purchase.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A_family</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000651">PDF/A-4e</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000652">PDF/A-4f</fddLink>.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDF/A</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for PDF/A</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Fall 2020 resources from the PDF Association relating to PDF/A-4</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://pdfa.org/the-new-pdf-2-0-and-subset-standards/</link>
							<tag>The new PDF 2.0 and subset standards (December 16, 2020)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Rc6mPNWy5I4</link>
							<tag>PDF/A-4, PDF/X-6 and the other new PDF standards (2020) | video</tag>
							<comment> From OctoberPDFfest meeting.  By Dietrich von Seggern of callas software GmbH.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://bfo.com/blog/2020/12/11/bfo_pdf_library_2_24_4_whats_new/</link>
					<tag>BFO PDF Library 2.24.4 - what&apos;s new? (December 2020) | Big Faceless PDF library</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Selected resources related to challenges for archival institutions posed by the arbitrary embedded files permitted in PDF/A-3  and misgivings about the format&apos;s suitability for long-term preservation and access.  See <fddLink id="fdd000360">PDF/A-3</fddLink> for additional resources.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.digitalpreservation.gov/documents/NDSA_PDF_A3_report_final022014.pdf</link>
							<tag>The Benefits and Risks of the PDF/A-3 File Format for Archival Institutions</tag>
							<comment>Published in February 2014 by the National Digital Stewardship Alliance.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.dpconline.org/docs/technology-watch-reports/1707-twr17-01-revised/file</link>
							<tag>Preservation with PDF/A | DPC Technology Watch Report 17-01 July 2017</tag>
							<comment>By Betsy Fanning</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.dpconline.org/images/2/22/PDFA_Assessment_v1.0.pdf</link>
							<tag>PDF Format Preservation Assessment Part 2: PDF/A Profile  (2019) | British Library</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link> https://www.notarius.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Case-study-MTQ.pdf</link>
					<tag>Ministry of Transportation in Quebec Goes Digital for Their Engineering Drawings and Plans (May 2018)</tag>
					<comment>Mentions adoption after a pilot, of archiving engineering drawings and plans as PDF/A-3 with AutoCAD or BIM Files embedded.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See <fddLink id="fdd000360">PDF/A_3</fddLink> for resources related to motivations and use cases for allowing files to be embedded in PDF/A files and challenges for long-term archiving posed by this feature.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.archives.gov/files/lod/dpframework/id/NF00646.ttl</link>
					<tag>NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID entry for NF00646</tag>
					<comment>Information in NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID about Portable Document Format/Archiving (PDF/A-4).</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pronom/fmt/1910</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/1910</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM from UK National Archives about Acrobat PDF/A - Portable Document Format 4. PUID: fmt/1910.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q123594568</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q123594568</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about PDF/A-4.  Wikidata Title ID: Q123594568</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
