<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000518" titleName="WebM" shortName="WebM" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>sound</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>aggregate</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
				</fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
			</fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>container-wrapper</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>unstructured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-08-19</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Partial</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>WebM</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>container formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>wrapper formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>WebM is an openly documented, non-proprietary, royalty-free open source format developed and maintained by Google and optimized for web-based media content. It was first <a href="http://blog.webmproject.org/2010/05/introducing-webm-open-web-media-project.html">announced</a> on May 19, 2010 with wide industry support including Mozilla, Opera, Google Chrome and Adobe listed as collaborators. WebM is a subtype of the  <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska Multimedia Container</fddLink> which, in turn, is based on <fddLink id="fdd000516">EBML</fddLink>. The DocType element in the EBML Header identifies the content of the EBML Body. For WebM, this would manifest as <i>EBMLSchema docType="webm"</i>. See Matroska for details about the overall structure. As defined in the Implementation Details section of the <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/container/">WebM Container Guidelines</a>, there are many elements not supported in WebM although are supported in Matroska. These include, for video 'ColourSpace', 'GammaValue', and for audio 'ChannelPositions', 'ContentCompression' (describing the compression used) and 'ContentCompAlgo ' (describing the compression algorithm used). Attachments are not supported by WebM. </p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>WebM is an openly documented, non-proprietary, royalty-free open source format developed and maintained by Google optimized for web-based media content. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>A final state format for enduser delivery.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Modification of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000342</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>Matroska</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Matroska Multimedia Container</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000516</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EBML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Extensible Binary Meta Language</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>The definition is via the same EBML schema used for Matroska.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:titleName>VP8 Video Codec. Not described at this time</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Developed by Google. Published as IETF <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6386.txt">RFC 6386</a> in 2011. Not defined as an Internet Standards Track specification but instead published for informational purposes only.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:titleName>VP9 Video Codec. Not described at this time</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Developed by Google. For more information, including link to specification published in in 2017, see <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/vp9/">Draft VP9 Bitstream and Decoding Process Specification</a>
				</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000109</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>Vorbis_I</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Vorbis Audio Codec, Version I</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:titleName>WebVTT (Web Video Text Tracks) Format. Not described at this time. </fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Standard format for subtitles, captions, and related timed metadata defined by WC3: <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/webvtt1/">WebVTT: The Web Video Text Tracks Format</a>
				</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>As of August 2020, the Library of Congress has over 2,300 files (6.6 GB) with the .webm extension in its digital collections. These have come from various sources, including archived websites.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>WebM is not included on the <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/index.html">Recommended Formats Statement</a> in relation to acquisition of digital video for LC collections.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>WebM is an openly documented, non-proprietary, royalty-free open source format developed and maintained by Google in collaboration with the <a href="https://aomedia.org/alliance-to-deliver-next-generation-open-media-formats/">Alliance for Open Media</a>. WebM is a constrained subtype of <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska</fddLink>. Matroska is defined by <fddLink id="fdd000516">EBML</fddLink> and the two are both standardized through the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF). As these are newer formats, all these specifications continue to evolve.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<ul>
				<li>The WebM specification is available on the <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/container/">WebM Project</a> website</li>
				<li>Matroska is an IETF Internet Draft specification. <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-cellar-matroska/">Draft version 05</a> is available as of this writing in August 2020</li>
				<li>EBML format specification is standardized through IETF. <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-cellar-ebml/">https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-cellar-ebml/</a> is available as of this writing in August 2020.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The WebM Project lists a wide variety of <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/tools/">tools</a> for creating and publishing content in the WebM format including free and open source as well as commercial options. This includes <a href="https://www.ffmpeg.org/">FFmpeg</a>, a popular open source &quot;cross-platform solution to record, convert and stream audio and video&quot; which has strong support for Matroska as well as <fddLink id="fdd000341">FFV1</fddLink>. Other tools listed on the Matroska website include <a href="https://www.matroska.org/downloads/mkclean.html">mkclean</a>, a command line tool to clean and optimize Matroska and WebM files and <a href="https://matroska.org/downloads/mkvalidator.html">mkvalidator</a> a command line conformance checker for Matroska and WebM files. In addition, <a href="https://mkvtoolnix.download/index.html">MKVToolNix</a> is the de-facto reference implementation of a Matroska multiplexer which bundles a set of Matroska and WebM focused tools to get information about (via mkvinfo) Matroska files, extract tracks/data from (via mkvextract) Matroska files and create (via mkvmerge) Matroska files from other media files and (via) mkvpropedit can edit properties such as header and chapter information or attachments without remuxing.</p>
			<p>Viewing options for WebM includes native support by Mozilla Firefox 4 and later, Opera 10.06 and later, Catalina, Sierra, and Google Chrome 6 and later while Internet Explorer 9+ requires the <a href="https://tools.google.com/dlpage/webmmf">WebM for Internet Explorer</a> plugin. According to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebM">Wikipedia</a>, Safari for macOS which relied on QuickTime to play web media until Safari 12, still does not have native support for WebM. As of 2019 QuickTime does not natively support WebM, but does with a suitable third-party plug-in. In 2011, the Google WebM Project Team released plugins for Internet Explorer and Safari to allow playback of WebM files through the standard <fddLink id="fdd000481">HTML5</fddLink>
				<i>video</i> tag. Starting in June 2012, Internet Explorer 9 and later supported the <a href="https://tools.google.com/dlpage/webmmf/"> WebM Media Foundation Components plugin </a> for Windows Vista and later releases as well as Windows Media Player 12 on Windows 7 or 8. According to the <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/ie/">WebM</a> site, "although the components refer to Internet Explorer 9, installing them will add system-wide WebM support in applications that use Media Foundation." WebM provides <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/downloads.webmproject.org/releases/webm/index.html">DirectShow filters</a> for playing and working with earlier versions. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>. </p>
			<p>Other players with native support include VLC media player, MPlayer, K-Multimedia Player and JRiver Media Center.</p>
			<p>WebM is supported on popular video sites including YouTube (a subsidiary of Google). </p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>WebM carries a <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/license/bitstream/">Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License</a> from Google which states that &quot;Google hereby grants to You a perpetual, worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable (except as stated in this section) patent license to make, have made, use, offer to sell, sell, import, and otherwise transfer implementations of the WebM Specifications, where such license applies only to those patent claims, both currently owned by Google and acquired in the future, licensable by Google that are necessarily infringed by implementation of the WebM Specifications.&quot;</p>
			<p>In addition, Google lists the <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/license/additional/">Additional IP Rights Grant (Patents)</a> for &quot;the use of WebM codecs distributed by Google as part of the WebM Project.&quot; </p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon included encodings, some of which will depend upon algorithms and tools to read and require sophistication to build tools. </fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>See <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska</fddLink>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies/>
		<fdd:techProtection>Encryption is supported in <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska</fddLink> in a generic way &quot;to allow people to implement whatever form of encryption is best for them&quot; according to the <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-ietf-cellar-matroska-05.txt">IETF Internet draft</a> from April 2020. In Matroska, encryption data is contained by the ContentEncryption element. According to <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/webm-encryption/">WebM project</a>, there is an effort to develop a more structured effort to support <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Encryption_Standard">AES encryption</a> through a <a href="https://w3c.github.io/encrypted-media/#simple-decryption">W3C proposal</a> (last updated August  2020 as of this writing). This project includes defining new elements specifically for Matroska and WebM including adding a master element named ContentEncAESSettings as a sub-element of the existing ContentEncryption element, which contains elements representing the features of AES. &quot;ContentEncAESSettings contains one sub element. AESSettingsCipherMode conveys the block cipher mode used with the AES encryption. AESSettingsCipherMode contains one value, CTR. With these new elements, clients should be able to decode frames encoded with AES.&quot; In addition, WebM supports the existing Matroska elements: ContentEncryption,
ContentEncAlgo,
ContentEncKeyID,
ContentEncAESSettings
and AESSettingsCipherMode. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:movingImageQF>
			<fdd:normalVideo>Good support</fdd:normalVideo>
			<fdd:clarity>Varies according to encoding</fdd:clarity>
		</fdd:movingImageQF>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Good support</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>Varies according to encoding</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>Varies according to encoding</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:samples>Varies according to encoding</fdd:samples>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>webm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/container/">WebM Container Guidelines</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/webm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/container/">WebM Container Guidelines</a>. Not listed in IANA Media Type assignments as of August 2020. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>audio/webm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For audio only content. From <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/container/">WebM Container Guidelines</a>. Not listed in IANA Media Type assignments as of August 2020. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>HEX: 0x1A45DFA3</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: EBML </fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From EBML specification, section 11.2.1. Used for all EBML-based files including <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska Multimedia Container</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000518">WebM</fddLink>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>&quot;1A45DFA3{0-32}4282847765626D4287&quot; from <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/573">PRONOM fmt/573</a> entry.  0x1A45DFA3 (&apos;EBML&apos;), 0x428284 (EBML DocType element ID), 0x7765626D (&apos;webm&apos;), 0x4287 (EBML DocTypeVersion element ID)</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>EBMLSchema docType="webm"</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>As declared in the EBML Header</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/573</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/573">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/573</a>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q309440</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q309440">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q309440</a>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>YouTube&apos;s Michael Bradshaw included a presentation of WebM at the first <a href="https://mediaarea.net/NoTimeToWait1">No Time to Wait</a> conference in Berlin in 2016. The blog post, <a href="https://youtube-eng.googleblog.com/2016/04/a-look-into-youtubes-video-file-anatomy.html">A look into YouTube’s video file anatomy</a> discusses WebM and Matroska&apos;s growing popularity. The YouTube Engineering and Developers blog in June 29, 2010 <a href="https://youtube-eng.googleblog.com/2010/06/flash-and-html5-tag_29.html">stated</a> &quot;we’re excited about the new WebM project. Google is open sourcing and contributing the VP8 codec to the WebM effort. Google, Mozilla, and Opera have all committed to support WebM, and we have already started making YouTube videos available in the WebM format. Adobe has also committed to support VP8, the video codec for WebM, in an upcoming Flash Player release.</fdd:general>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.webmproject.org/docs/container/</link>
					<tag>WebM Container Guidelines from WebM Project</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska Multimedia Container</fddLink>
					</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See <fddLink id="fdd000516">Extensible Binary Meta Language for Matroska</fddLink>
					</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://opensource.google/projects/webm</link>
					<tag>WebM from Google Open Source</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.webmproject.org/</link>
					<tag>WebM: an open web media project</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.webmproject.org/tools/</link>
					<tag>Open source and commercial tools from WebM Project website</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebM</link>
					<tag>WebM entry from Wikipedia</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://w3c.github.io/encrypted-media/#simple-decryption</link>
					<tag>Encrypted Media Extensions by W3C</tag>
					<comment>W3C Editor&apos;s Draft 19 August 2020</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://aomedia.org/alliance-to-deliver-next-generation-open-media-formats/</link>
					<tag>Alliance for Open Media Established to Deliver Next-Generation Open Media Formats: Press Release August 28, 2015</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.ffmpeg.org/</link>
					<tag>FFmpeg </tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://youtube-eng.googleblog.com/2016/04/a-look-into-youtubes-video-file-anatomy.html</link>
					<tag>A look into YouTube’s video file anatomy blog post by YouTube developer Michael Bradshaw</tag>
					<comment>From No Time to Wait conference in Berlin, 2016</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.webmproject.org/vp9/</link>
					<tag>Draft VP9 Bitstream and Decoding Process Specification from Google</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://storage.googleapis.com/downloads.webmproject.org/docs/vp9/vp9-bitstream-specification-v0.6-20160331-draft.pdf</link>
					<tag>VP9	Bitstream	&amp;	Decoding	Process	Specification
Version	0.6</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6386.txt</link>
					<tag>IETF 6386: VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/TR/webvtt1/</link>
					<tag>WebVTT: The Web Video Text Tracks Format format specification published by W3C</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q309440</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q309440</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about WebM. Wikidata Title ID: Q309440.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/573</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/573</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM from UK National Archives about WebM. PUID: fmt/573.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
