<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000155" titleName="MPEG-4 File Format, Version 2" shortName="MP4_FF_2" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>unstructured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2012-03-02</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>ISO/IEC 14496-14:2003. Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 14: MP4 File Format (formal name); MPEG-4 file format, version 2 (common name)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>MPEG</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>MPEG-4</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>mp4</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>The second MPEG-4 file format developed by the Moving Picture Experts Group (MPEG).  The format's object-based design defines a set of tools that present binary coded representation of individual audiovisual objects, text, graphics, and synthetic objects.  (See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.)  This format is intended to serve web and other online applications; mobile devices, i.e., cell phones and PDAs; and broadcasting and other professional applications. See also <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>The second MPEG-4 file format developed by the Moving Picture Experts Group (MPEG).  The format's object-based design defines a set of tools that present binary coded representation of individual audiovisual objects, text, graphics, and synthetic objects.  This format is intended to serve web and other online applications; mobile devices, i.e., cell phones and PDAs; and broadcasting and other professional applications.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Generally a final-state (end-user delivery) format, may also serve as middle-state format. </fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000079</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ISO_BMFF</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>ISO Base Media File Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000157</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_V</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with Visual Encoding (All Profiles)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000158</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, No Profile Indicated</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000225</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC_BP</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, Baseline Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000219</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC_MP</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, Main Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000220</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC_EP</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, Extended Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000221</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC_HP</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, High Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000222</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC_H10P</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, High 10 Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000223</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC_H422P</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, High 4:2:2 Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000224</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AVC_H444P</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with AVC, High 4:4:4 Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000234</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_2_AAC</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with Advanced Audio Coding</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>For other object types, not described at this time</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000037</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP4_FF_1</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-4 File Format, Version 1</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The content produced by the <a href="http://www.loc.gov/today/pr/2006/06-147.html">NDIIPP partnership project</a> with <a href="http://www.scola.org">SCOLA</a> consists of foreign television news broadcasts in <fddLink id="fdd000157">MP4_FF_2_V</fddLink>, MPEG-4 File Format, V.2, with Visual Encoding.</fdd:experience>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard.  Developed through ISO technical program <a href="http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_technical_committee.html?commid=45316">ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 29</a> for coding of audio, picture, multimedia and hypermedia information.  The working group WG11 (for coding of moving pictures and audio) is also known as the Moving Picture Experts Group (<a href="http://mpeg.chiariglione.org">MPEG</a>).  See the ISO Standards Catalogue for the <a href="http://www.iso.org/iso/home/store/catalogue_tc/catalogue_tc_browse.htm?commid=45316&amp;published=on&amp;includesc=true">list of standards published by ISO/IEC JTC1/SC29</a>. See <a href="http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-4">http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-4</a> for information specific to MPEG-4 and its many parts.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>ISO/IEC 14496-14:2003. Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 14: MP4 File Format.</p>
			<p>The total documentation package for ISO/IEC 14496 is extensive; 17 parts have been published from 1998 to 2004, with more to come. See complete list of documents in <a href="#specs">Format specifications</a> below.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Appears to be more widely adopted than <fddLink id="fdd000037">MP4_FF_1</fddLink>.  Overall, the adoption of MPEG-4 has been slowed by licensing terms that require some content disseminators to pay fees according to the number of endusers or the extent of content delivered. As adoption advances, it may not extend to all profiles, levels, or parts of the standard.
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>MPEG-4 Visual, Systems, and Advanced Video Coding licensing is managed by <a href="http://www.mpegla.com/">MPEG LA LLC</a> (http://www.mpegla.com/).  These licenses cover the manufacture and sale of devices or software and, for some content disseminators, levy fees according to number of endusers or the extent of content delivered.  The arrangements are updated periodically; for example, in January 2005, MPEG LA announced that the patent portfolio had been expanded to cover the FRExt (Fidelity Range Extensions) associated with <fddLink id="fdd000081">MPEG-4_AVC</fddLink> and ITU H.264.</p>
			<p>MPEG-4 Audio licensing is managed by <a href="http://www.via-corp.com/licensing/index.html">Via Licensing Corporation</a> (http://www.via-corp.com/licensing/index.html), an independent subsidiary of Dolby Laboratories.  MPEG-4 Audio licensing appears to be limited to the manufacture of devices or software.
</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon included encodings, but all MPEG-4 encodings depend upon algorithms and tools to read and require sophistication to build tools.
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>The inclusion of metadata of various types is a key element in MPEG-4.  As indicated in the <a href="#notes">notes</a> below, object and scene descriptions are required in order for MPEG-4 content to be presented.</p>
			<p>Semantic description is carried by Object Content Information (OCI) descriptors and streams; the standard also permits the inclusion of <a href="http://xml.coverpages.org/mpeg7.html">MPEG-7</a> data, a separately standardized structure for metadata to support discovery and other purposes.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>Playback of surround sound requires multiple loudspeakers.
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>MPEG-4 offers a standardized Intellectual Property Management and Protection (IPMP) interface consisting of IPMP-Descriptors (IPMP-Ds) and IPMP-Elementary Streams (IPMP-ES) that allow the design and use of domain-specific IPMP systems.
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:movingImageQF>
			<fdd:normalVideo>Good support. The format supports <i>timescales</i> that manage the playout of time-based media streams and <i>hint tracks</i> employed in streaming applications.</fdd:normalVideo>
			<fdd:clarity>Depends upon encoding; see <fddLink id="fdd000080">MPEG-4_V</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000081">MPEG-4_AVC</fddLink>.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:beyondVideo>MPEG-4 program streams may be multiplexed in MPEG-2 transport streams.  Random access and other features are discussed in the specification.</fdd:beyondVideo>
		</fdd:movingImageQF>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:fidelity>
				<p>Depends upon encoding; the encodings used are generally lossy and provide moderate to very good fidelity.  See, for example, <fddLink id="fdd000114">AAC_MP4</fddLink>, considered to be superior to <fddLink id="fdd000012">MP3</fddLink> (MPEG-2 layer 3 audio) at a given bit rate.</p>
				<p>The MPEG-4 standard also provides support for other "natural" sound encodings, e.g., parametric coding (HILN or Harmonic and Individual Lines plus Noise) and CELP (Code Excited Linear Prediction) and other encodings for speech.  The standard also supports the synthesis of audio, and for what is called Synthetic-Natural Hybrid Coding (SNHC).  The presentation of these elements depends upon the use of AudioBIFs (Audio BInary Format for Scenes).  In 2005, the MPEG committee announced two additional audio capabilities: Audio Lossless coding (ALS; lossless compression of multi-channel sound using time-domain prediction and entrogy coding) and Scalable to Lossless coding (SLS; a scalable enhancement layer is added to a lossy bitstream that extends the representation to lossless but which can be truncated at delivery time).  The compilers of this document do not know the degree to which any of these various elements may be implemented in practice.</p>
			</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>
				<p>The <fddLink id="fdd000114">AAC_MP4</fddLink> audio structure provides a capability of up to 48 main audio channels, 16 LFE (Low Frequency Encoding or Effects) channels, 16 overdub/multilingual channels, and 16 data streams.</p>
				<p>SNHC [and other note-based or synthetic?] sound can be spatially presented using extensions of the concepts initially implemented in Virtual Reality Modeling Language (VRML).</p>
			</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:samples>Not applicable.</fdd:samples>
			<fdd:beyondSound>Not fully investigated at this time.  Recent published or announced additions to the standard include Part 16, the Animation Extension Framework; Part 17 for "timed text," e.g., subtitles or karaoke; Part 18 for font compression and streaming; and Part 22 for Open Fonts based on the OpenType specification.</fdd:beyondSound>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>mp4</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>m4a</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>
					<p>Paraphrased from the former <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20130114111221/http://www.m4a.com/">www.m4a.com</a> site: <i>MP4</i> can be used for MPEG 4 video files, combined video and audio files, or just plain MPEG 4 audio. <i>M4A</i> files contain only MPEG 4 Audio. Apple started using <i>M4A</i> to identify files unprotected by digital rights management; note that protected <fddLink id="fdd000110">QTA_AAC</fddLink> files carry the <i>M4P</i> and and <i>M4B</i> (for bookmarkable files) extensions. Apple felt that <i>MP4</i> was too general (video, video/audio, or audio) and might confuse some media players. Until recently, encoder and player software like Nero and Compaact used <i>.mp4</i> for audio files while WinAmp 5.02, Apple iTunes, and others used <i>.m4a</i>.  Today, most audio software developers allow you to choose the file extension you prefer.</p>
					<p>The Wikipedia article <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_lossless">Apple Lossless</a> (consulted November 2, 2012) reports that the <i>m4a</i> extension is used for files containing either <fddLink id="fdd000114">AAC_MP4</fddLink> or the Apple Lossless encoding, wrapped in the <fddLink id="fdd000155">MPEG4_FF_2</fddLink> (MPEG-4, version 2) file format.</p>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mp4</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>According to <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4337.txt">IETF RFC 4337</a> (March 2006), for files with video and audio streams (including MPEG-J<footNote id="1"/>).</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>audio/mp4</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>According to <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4337.txt">IETF RFC 4337</a> (March 2006), for files with audio but no visual aspect (including MPEG-J<footNote id="1"/>).</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/mp4</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>According to <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4337.txt">IETF RFC 4337</a> (March 2006), for files with neither visual nor audio presentations but only MPEG-J<footNote id="1"/> or MPEG-7 metadata.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/mpeg4-iod</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/mpeg4-iod-xmt</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>IOD (Initial Object Descriptor) in binary format and (with appended xmt) in textual format, from <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4337.txt">IETF RFC 4337</a> (March 2006).</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mp4v-es</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mpeg4-generic</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Additional MIME types referred to in various documents.  <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3016.txt">IETF RFC 3016</a> reports that MIME types may have indicators for data rate or profile-level appended to them.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>Not found.</fdd:sigValueNA>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Uniform Type Identifier (Mac OS)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>mpg4</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Similar in function to a filename; the <i>mpg4</i> type code is documented in <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4337.txt">IETF RFC 4337</a> (March 2006).</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>File type brand (ISO Base Media File Format)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>mp42</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>
						<fddLink id="fdd000079">ISO_BMFF</fddLink> includes a file type box that contains major and minor brands (identifiers); this brand is specified in Part 14, Section 4 (ISO/IEC 14496-14:2003. Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 14: MP4 File Format, p. 6).</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>The four file formats associated with the ISO/IEC 14496 family of specifications are:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<fddLink id="fdd000037">MP4_FF_1</fddLink>, "version 1" from Part 1 (2001)</li>
				<li>MP4_FF_2, "version 2," this document, from Part 14</li>
				<li>
					<fddLink id="fdd000137">MP4_FF_AVCE</fddLink>, for Advanced Video Coding extensions, from Part 15</li>
				<li>
					<fddLink id="fdd000156">MP4_XMT</fddLink>, "textual format" from Part 11</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Version 2 is very similar to its predecessor <fddLink id="fdd000037">MP4_FF_1</fddLink> as both owe a debt to the <fddLink id="fdd000052">QuickTime</fddLink> file format that preceded them.  This lineage is shared with the supertype for MP4_FF_2, <fddLink id="fdd000079">ISO_BMFF</fddLink>, defined in Parts 12 of both the MPEG-4 and JPEG 2000 standards.</p>Note that "object-oriented building blocks" are called <i>boxes</i> in this file format and its parent, <fddLink id="fdd000079">ISO_BMFF</fddLink>; in contrast, they are called <i>atoms</i> in the predecessor MP4_FF_1 and <fddLink id="fdd000052">QuickTime</fddLink>.<p>The object-based design of MPEG-4 is characterized as follows in Fernando Pereira and Touradj Ebrahimi's <i>The MPEG-4 Book</i> (Upper Saddle River, NJ: IMSC Press, 2002): "MPEG-4 is an ISO/IES standard developed by MPEG for communicating interactive audiovisual scenes.  The standard defines a set of tools that provide binary coded representation of individual audiovisual objects, text, graphics, and synthetic objects.  The interactive behaviors of these objects and the way they are composed in space and time to form an MPEG-4 scene are dependent on the scene description, which is coded in a binary format known as binary format for scenes (BIFS) . . . . The audiovisual streams are defined as elementary streams (ESs) and managed according to the object descriptor (OD) framework . . . .  In addition, the OD framework defines additional streams for object content information (OCI), MPEG-J [Java APIs], and intellectual property management and protection (IPMP)." (p. 188)</p>
			<p>BIFS owes a debt to the Virtual Reality Modeling Language (VRML), even as it extends VRML's capabilities and employs binary encoding.  Timing of elements in MPEG-4 is managed by a Synchronization Layer (SL).  The delivery of MPEG-4 content is supported by the Delivery Multimedia Framework or DMIF and its application interface.</p>
			<p>MPEG-J is described in Part 1 of the standard (ISO/IEC 14496-1:2004). This API for the interoperation of MPEG-4 media players with Java code is  contrasted with a conventional parametric system.  "By combining MPEG-4 media and safe executable code, content creators may embed complex control and data processing mechanisms with their media data to intelligently manage the operation of the audio-visual session. The parametric MPEG-4 System forms the Presentation Engine while the MPEG-J subsystem controlling the Presentation Engine forms the Application Engine.  The Java application is delivered as a separate elementary stream to the MPEG-4 terminal. There it will be directed to the MPEG-J run time environment, from where the MPEG-J program will have access to the various components and required data of the MPEG-4 player to control it." (p. xii)</p>
		</fdd:general>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.iso.org/iso/home/store/catalogue_tc/catalogue_tc_browse.htm?commid=45316&amp;published=on&amp;includesc=true</link>
					<tag>ISO Catalogue of standards published under ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 29.</tag>
					<comment>MPEG-4 is ISO/IEC 14496.  This file format is described in Part 14.  All parts and associated amendments and corrections are listed in this SC29 catalogue.  Parts published through 2004 are listed immediately below.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-1:2001   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 1: Systems</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-1:2004   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 1: Systems</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-1:2001/Amd 1:2001   Extended BIFS</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-1:2001/Amd 4:2003   SL extensions and AFX streams</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-1:2001/Amd 8:2004   New ObjectTypeIndiciation code points</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-2:2004   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 2: Visual</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-2:2004/Cor 1:2004</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-2:2004/Amd 1:2004   Error resilient simple scalable profile</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-3:2001   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 3: Audio</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-3:2001/Cor 1:2002</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-3:2001/Amd 1:2003   Bandwidth extension</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-3:2001/Amd 1:2003/Cor 1:2004</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-3:2001/Cor 2:2004M</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-3:2001/Amd 2:2004	 Parametric coding for high-quality audio</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-4:2000   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 4: Conformance testing</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-4:2000/Cor 1:2002 </fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-5:2001   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 5: Reference software</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-5:2001/Amd 1:2002   Reference software for MPEG-4</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-5:2001/Amd 2:2003   MPEG-4 reference software extensions for XMT and media nodes</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-5:2001/Amd 3:2003   Visual new level and tools</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-5:2001/Amd 4:2004	IPMPX reference software extensions</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-5:2001/Amd 5:2004	Reference software extensions for error resilient simple scalable profile</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-6:2000   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 6: Delivery Multimedia Integration Framework (DMIF) </fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC TR 14496-7:2002   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 7: Optimized reference software for coding of audio-visual objects</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-8:2004  Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 8: Carriage of ISO/IEC 14496 contents over IP networks</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC TR 14496-9:2004  Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 9: Reference hardware description</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-10:2003   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 10: Advanced Video Coding</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-12:2004   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 12: ISO base media file format</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-13:2004  Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 13: Intellectual Property Management and Protection (IPMP) extensions</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-14:2003   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 14: MP4 file format</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-15:2004   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 15: Advanced Video Coding (AVC) file format</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-16:2004   Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 16: Animation Framework eXtension (AFX)</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-18:2004  Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 18: Font compression and streaming</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 14496-19:2004  Information technology -- Coding of audio-visual objects -- Part 19: Synthesized texture stream</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/</link>
					<tag>Moving Picture Experts Group website</tag>
					<comment>From Leonardo Chiariglione, one of MPEG&apos;s founding figures.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-4</link>
					<tag>MPEG-4 section of Moving Picture Experts Group website</tag>
					<comment>From Leonardo Chiariglione, one of MPEG&apos;s founding figures.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.oipf.tv/mpegif</link>
					<tag>MPEG-4 Industry Forum</tag>
					<comment>Existed from 2000 to 2012, when its existing documentation from http://www.m4if.org/ was merged into the Open IPTV Forum </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MPEG-4</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for MPEG-4</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4337.txt</link>
					<tag>RFC 4337: MIME Type Registration for MPEG-4</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3016.txt</link>
					<tag>RFC 3016: RTP Payload Format for MPEG-4 Audio/Visual Streams</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3640.txt</link>
					<tag>RFC 3640: RTP Payload Format for Transport of MPEG-4 Elementary Streams</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_technical_committee.html?commid=45316</link>
					<tag>Public ISO/IEC JTC1/SC29 page at ISO</tag>
					<comment>Parent committee for WG 11, the working group for MPEG.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://wg11.sc29.org/</link>
					<tag>MPEG document management system</tag>
					<comment>As of late 2013, this page had little useful public information, with several links to obsolete URLs.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/faq/mp4-sys/sys-faq-esm.htm</link>
					<tag>MPEG-4 FAQ</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-4/mpeg-j-extension-rendering</link>
					<tag>MPEG-J Extension for Rendering</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20030218051108/http://www.diffuse.org/video.html#MPEG-4</link>
					<tag>MPEG-4 on the Diffuse Web Site</tag>
					<comment>Archived copy from the Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20130114111221/http://www.m4a.com/</link>
					<tag>Former site for users of the AAC audio format.</tag>
					<comment>Archived copy from the Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>VIA Licensing</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.via-corp.com/licensing/index.html</link>
							<tag>VIA Licensing</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.via-corp.com/licensing/aac/overview.html</link>
							<tag>Advanced Audio Coding - AAC</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.via-corp.com/licensing/aac/faq.html</link>
							<tag>AAC Frequently Asked Questions</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:bookReference>Pereira, Fernando and Touradj Ebrahimi.  <i>The MPEG-4 Book</i>. Upper Saddle River, NJ: IMSC Press, 2002.</fdd:bookReference>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
	<fdd:footNotes>
		<fdd:footNote id="1">
			<fdd:text> Adapted from <a href="http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-4/mpeg-j-extension-rendering">http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-4/mpeg-j-extension-rendering</a>: MPEG-J (MPEG-4 Java), originally defined in part 1 of the of the MPEG-4 standard [MPEG-4 Systems Standard].  MPEG-J lets content creators embed simple or complex algorithmic control along with audio and video streams. MPEG-J enables monitoring of network bandwidth (and packet losses) and helps in adapting to a wide range of dynamically varying network conditions.</fdd:text>
		</fdd:footNote>
	</fdd:footNotes>
</fdd:FDD>
