<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000335" titleName="MPEG-2 Encoding Family" shortName="MPEG-2_family" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>family</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2012-02-14</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>ISO/IEC 13818. Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information (formal name)  MPEG-2 (common name)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>MPEG</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>MPEG-2</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>H.262</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>The family of MPEG-2 encodings were initially developed to serve the transmission of compressed television programs via broadcast, cablecast, and satellite, and subsequently adopted for DVD production and for some online delivery systems.  Picture, sound, and data elements consist of streams, i.e., the format&apos;s sequences of encoded bytes. Elementary streams are the basic element; these are broken into packets of variable length, forming a packetized elementary stream (PES). Each PES packet includes a header. In many applications, the audio and video are multiplexed, thus combining the two elements. Packetized and multiplexed elementary streams may take the form of single-program <i>program stream</i> or are combined with other programs in a multi-program <i>transport stream</i>.</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>The family of MPEG-2 encodings were initially developed to serve the transmission of compressed television programs via broadcast, cablecast, and satellite, and subsequently adopted for DVD production and for some online delivery systems.  Picture, sound, and data elements consist of streams, i.e., the format&apos;s sequences of encoded bytes. 
</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000028</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MPEG-2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-2 Video Encoding (H.262)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000033</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MPEG-2_SP</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-2, Simple Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000032</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MPEG-2_MP</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-2, Main Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000034</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MPEG-2_422</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-2, 4:2:2 Profile</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Other MPEG-2 profiles not documented at this time: SNR Scalable, Spatially Scalable, and High.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000269</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>D-10</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>D-10 Video Encoding (IMX)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000012</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MP3_ENC</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MP3 audio encoding</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000036</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>AAC_MP2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Advanced Audio Coding (MPEG-2)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000338</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MPEG_layer_2_audio</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-1 and MPEG-2 Layer II Audio Encoding</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000336</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MPEG-2_MP_layer_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-2 File with Main Profile Video and Layer II Audio Encoding</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000337</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MPEG-2_422_layer_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MPEG-2 File with 422 Video and Layer II Audio Encoding</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress National Audio-Visual Conservation Center, Packard Campus, at Culpeper, Virginia, has received significant numbers of MPEG-2 files for their holdings as a part of two important retrospective collections. MPEG-2 is used as the &quot;mezzanine&quot; computer-file format for reformatted video recordings, e.g., from VHS tapes, in the American Folklife Center Veterans History Project.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>Content received as MPEG-2 files will be held in this format for the near term although there is discussion of future migrations into <fddLink id="fdd000206">MXF_OP1a_JP2_LL</fddLink>, the format currently being employed by the Packard Campus facility as an archival master when reformatting videotapes.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard. Developed through ISO technical program <a href="http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_technical_committee.html?commid=45316">JTC 1/SC 29</a> for coding of audio, picture, multimedia and hypermedia information by Working Group 11 (WG11) aka the Moving Picture Experts Group (<a href="http://mpeg.chiariglione.org">MPEG</a>).  The video coding aspects were co-developed with the International Telecommunication Union (ITU) Telecommunication Standardization Sector (ITU-T), who published the &#34;common text&#34; as H.262.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>ISO/IEC 13818; first approvals in 1994.  Ten parts have been published; parts 1, 2, 3, and 7 are central.  Part 2 concerns the coding and specifies profiles and levels.  See list of ISO documents in <a href="#specs">Format specifications</a> below.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Widely adopted for filemaking, DVD disks, and other applications.   Most significant is the format's required use in digital terrestrial broadcasting to homes in the United States and several other nations, as governed by the ATSC (Advanced Television Systems Committee) specifications. Many software tools exist for encoding and decoding.<br/>
			<br/>Wide adoption may not extend to all profiles, levels, or parts of the standard.  Evidence in various documents suggests that the Simple, Main, and 4:2:2 profiles are the most widely adopted. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
Managed by <a href="http://www.mpegla.com/main/default.aspx">MPEG LA LLC</a> (http://www.mpegla.com/main/default.aspx).  Licenses pertain to tools and not to streams or files per se.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication to build tools.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>Technical (coding) information is contained in the MPEG-2 bitstream in macroblock headers, slice headers, picture headers, Group of Picture (GOP) headers, and sequence headers.  The sequence header provides data needed before decoding can begin, such as the size of the picture and the frame rate. Because it is so important, the sequence header is usually repeated as often as twice a second.</p>
			<p>The lack of metadata of the type called <i>bibliographic</i> by librarians motivated the MPEG group to develop MPEG-7, a separately standardized structure for metadata to support discovery and other purposes.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>Playback of surround sound requires multiple loudspeakers.
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>MPEG-2 shares with MPEG-4 elements of a standardized Intellectual Property Management and Protection (IPMP) scheme; see <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/documents/LIAISON/file944.htm">Intellectual Property Management and Protection
in MPEG Standards</a>.	</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:movingImageQF>
			<fdd:normalVideo>Good support.</fdd:normalVideo>
			<fdd:clarity>Moderate to very good, given that this is a format for lossy compression. Outcome will depend on the type and extent of compression, and the encoder used. </fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:beyondVideo>The MPEG-2 transport stream permits the multiplexing of multiple programs.</fdd:beyondVideo>
		</fdd:movingImageQF>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Good support.</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>
				<p>Moderate to very good, given that the options for audio employ lossy compression.  Widespread use is made of MPEG-2 layer 3 audio, aka <fddLink id="fdd000012">MP3_ENC</fddLink>.  Some producers make use of Advanced Audio Coding, aka <fddLink id="fdd000036">AAC</fddLink>, considered to be superior to MP3 at a given bit rate.</p>
				<p>Producers are not limited to the audio structures inherent in MPEG-2.  The Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers (SMPTE) provides specifications for incorporating <fddLink id="fdd000208">AES3_SMPTE</fddLink> data into the MPEG-2 transport stream.  Among other things, this permits the use of <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink> compressed audio (aka Dolby Digital).</p>
				<p>For all types of compressed audio, the quality of the outcome will depend on the type and extent of compression, and the encoder used.</p>
			</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>
				<p>Multi-channel sound is supported in both the backwardly compatible (BC) audio structures shared with <fddLink id="fdd000035">MPEG-1</fddLink>, which includes layer 3 audio (<fddLink id="fdd000012">MP3_ENC</fddLink>), and in the non-backwardly compatible <fddLink id="fdd000036">AAC</fddLink> audio structure.  MPEG-2 BC can deliver five main channels and an optional LFE (Low Frequency Encoding or Effects) channel, i.e., 5.1 surround sound.  AAC provides a capability of up to 48 main audio channels, 16 LFE channels, 16 overdub/multilingual channels, and 16 data streams.</p>
				<p>The use of <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink> compressed audio (aka Dolby Digital), described above in connection with <fddLink id="fdd000208">AES3_SMPTE</fddLink> data, provides another means for presenting surround sound.</p>
			</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:beyondSound>None</fdd:beyondSound>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>mpg</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>mpeg</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>There is no explicit MPEG-2 file format; MPEG-2 content "ready to be delivered" is exchanged in a de facto file format that may carry one of these extensions.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mpeg</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.ietf.org/">IETF</a> (Internet Engineering Task Force) <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt">RFC 2046</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mpv</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mp2t</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue> video/mp1s</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue> video/mp2p </fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.ietf.org/">IETF</a> (Internet Engineering Task Force) <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3555.txt">RFC 3555</a>; the four subtypes are glossed as "MPEG-1 or -2 Elementary Streams," "MPEG-2 Transport Streams," "MPEG-1 Systems Streams," and "MPEG-2 Program Streams."</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mpg</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/x-mpg</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/mpeg2</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/x-pn-mpg</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/x-mpeg</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/x-mpeg2a</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Additional examples selected from <a href="http://filext.com/">The File Extension Source</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 00 00 01 Bx</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: ....</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html">Gary Kessler's File Signatures Table</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:history>MPEG stands for the Moving Picture Experts Group, which began developing video compression standards in the 1980s.  The group was founded by two men described by one commentator as "the fiery Leonardo Chiariglione (CSELT, Italy)" and "the peaceful Hiroshi Yasuda (JVC, Japan)."  MPEG's initial development (of MPEG-1) was partly inspired by the H.261 video coding standard published by the ITU (International Telecom Union).</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-1:2007 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information: Systems. <i>Two primary purposes: 1). a syntax for transporting packets of audio and video bitstreams over digital channels and storage media, 2). a syntax for synchronizing video and audio streams.</i>
					<footNote id="1"/>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-1:2007/Amd 3:2009/Cor 1:2011</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-1:2007/Cor 1:2008</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-1:2000/Amd 1:2003 Carriage of metadata over ISO/IEC 13818-1 streams </fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-1:2000/Amd 2:2004 Support of IPMP on MPEG-2 systems </fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC FDIS 13818-2 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information: Video. <i>Jointly developed with the ITU-T, where it is known as recommendation H.262.  Describes syntax (header and bitstream elements) and semantics (algorithms telling what to do with the bits).</i>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-2:2000/Cor 1:2002 </fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-2:2000/Amd 1:2001 Content description data </fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-3:1998 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures andassociated audio information -- Part 3: Audio.  <i>Describes syntax and semantics for three classes of compression methods. Known as Layers I, II, and III, the classes trade increased syntax and coding complexity for improved coding efficiency at lower bitrates.</i>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information -- Part 4: Conformance testing. <i>Conformance testing. Defines the meaning of MPEG conformance for all three parts (Systems, Video, and Audio), and provides two sets of test guidelines for determining compliance in bitstreams and decoders.</i>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004/Amd 2:2005/Cor 1:2007</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004/Cor 1:2007</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004/Amd 2:2005/Cor 2:2009</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004/Cor 2:2011</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004/Amd 1:2005</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004/Amd 2:2005</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-4:2004/Amd 3:2009</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC TR 13818-5:2005 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information -- Part 5: Software simulation.  <i>Contains an example ANSI C language software encoder and compliant decoder for video and audio.</i>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-6:1998 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information -- Part 6: Extensions for DSM-CC. <i>Extensions for Digital Storage Medium Command and Control (DSM-CC).  Provides a syntax for controlling VCR-style playback and random-access of bitstreams encoded onto digital storage mediums such as compact disc.</i>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-6:1998/Amd 1:2000/Cor 1:2002</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-6:1998/Cor 1:1999</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-6:1998/Cor 2:2002</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-6:1998/Amd 1:2000 Additions to support data broadcasting</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-6:1998/Amd 2:2000 Additions to support synchronized download services, opportunistic data services and resource announcement in broadcast and interactive services</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-6:1998/Amd 3:2001 Transport buffer model in support of synchronized user-to-network download protocol</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-7:2006 Information technology - Generic coding
of moving pictures and associated audio
information -
Part 7:
Advanced Audio Coding (AAC)</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>ISO/IEC 13818-7:2006/Amd 1:2007</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-7:2006/Cor 1:2009</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-7:2006/Cor 2:2010</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> Part 8.  10-bit video extension. Withdrawn.</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-9:1996 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information -- Part 9: Extension for real time interface for systems decoders. <i>Real-Time Interface (RTI) for systems decoders defines a syntax for video on demand control signals between set-top boxes and head-end servers.</i>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-10:1999 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information -- Part 10: Conformance extensions for Digital Storage Media Command and Control (DSM-CC). <i>Related to part 6.</i>
				</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference> ISO/IEC 13818-11:2004 Information technology -- Generic coding of moving pictures and associated audio information -- Part 11: IPMP on MPEG-2 systems</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20090621154148/http://bmrc.berkeley.edu/frame/research/mpeg/mpeg2faq.html</link>
					<tag>Berkeley FAQ</tag>
					<comment>2009 Web page archived by the Internet Archive. </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.mpeg.org/</link>
					<tag>http://www.mpeg.org/</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.faqs.org/faqs/mpeg-faq/</link>
					<tag>MPEG FAQ</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.pinnaclesys.com/files/MainPage/Professional/TopTabItems/products/dc1000/WhitePapers/DC1000-DVD1000MPEG2whitepaper.pdf</link>
					<tag>MPEG-2 White Paper</tag>
					<comment>From a product manufacturer.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.bbc.co.uk/rd/pubs/papers/paper_14/paper_14.shtml</link>
					<tag>MPEG-2 Video Compression</tag>
					<comment>A 1995 white paper by Phil Tudor of the BBC. </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.edithouse.com.au/information/imx.html</link>
					<tag>Sony&apos;s IMX Format</tag>
					<comment>2002 introductory article by Alistair Jackson, describing this all-I-frame, 50 Mbps (SD) version of MPEG-2.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/documents/LIAISON/file944.htm</link>
					<tag>Intellectual Property Management and Protection
in MPEG Standards</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt</link>
					<tag>RFC 2046</tag>
					<comment>Includes some MPEG registrations.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3555.txt</link>
					<tag>RFC 3555</tag>
					<comment>Includes some MPEG registrations.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html</link>
					<tag>Gary Kessler's File Signatures Table</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://filext.com/</link>
					<tag>The File Extension Source</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
	<fdd:footNotes>
		<fdd:footNote id="1">
			<fdd:text> The italicized blurbs in the specifications section are derived from the Berkeley Multimedia Research Center. This link is to the Internet Archive&apos;s saved copy of this page: <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20090621154148/http://bmrc.berkeley.edu/frame/research/mpeg/mpeg2faq.html">MPEG-2 FAQ</a>
			</fdd:text>
		</fdd:footNote>
	</fdd:footNotes>
</fdd:FDD>
