<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000519" titleName="EPUB (Electronic Publication) Version 3 Preservation. ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020" shortName="EPUB_pres" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>container-wrapper</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-04-21</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>EPUB (Electronic Publication) Version 3 Preservation. ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020, Digital publishing -- EPUB 3 Preservation, Parts 1-2</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020, for EPUB3 Preservation, was published as two Technical Specifications in January 2020, titled &quot;Principles&quot; and &quot;Metadata Requirements.&quot;  The purpose of the specifications is to make it easier for
producers and OAIS archives to preserve access to EPUB documents.  ISO/IEC 22424-2:2020 provides a technical
basis to meet the principles listed in the first document by specifying metadata required for long-term
preservation, and a method for packaging this metadata with the original EPUB container using <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/">METS</a> (Metadata Encoding &amp; Transmission Standard) and the <a href="https://www.loc.gov/standards/premis/">PREMIS</a> Data Dictionary for Preservation Metadata.</p>
			<p>These documents were prepared by ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 34/JWG 7 and not by a group that is part of <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/">Publishing@W3C</a>.  The W3C EPUB 3 Community Group, which is part of Publishing@W3C, published the EPUB 3.2 specification in May 2019.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for more information on the activities at W3C relevant to EPUB and <a href="#sustainability">Disclosure</a> for more information on JWG 7.  The introduction to Part 1: Principles states, &quot;The specification at hand covers EPUB 3 versions up to EPUB 3.0.1. EPUB 3.1 was the first major
revision of EPUB 3.0.1, but there are no implementations of version 3.1 and therefore it is not covered in this document.  The most widely used version of the standard is still 3.0.1. EPUB 3.2, was published in May 2019. Unlike 3.1, it is fully backwards compatible with 3.0.1. It will be covered in the next edition of this document.&quot;</p>
			<p>The two documents do not specify particular digital formats, but make recommendations for constraints on EPUB 3 files in consideration of the challenges of digital preservation, but they also make recommendations for Submission Information Packages (SIPs, as defined in the <a href="http://www.oais.info/">OAIS Reference Model</a>) and metadata to be included in the <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/">METS</a> file which is recommended as a packaging standard by ISO/IEC TS 22424-1:2020.</p>
			<p>ISO/IEC TS 22424-1:2020 (Principles) includes the following requirements (indicated by &quot;SHALL&quot;) and recommendations (indicated by &quot;SHOULD&quot;) for EPUB files.  Notes enclosed in [ ] have been added by the compilers of this resource.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Submitted EPUB publications SHALL be conformant with EPUB requirements and
 conformance SHOULD be validated. [Note: This statement refers to <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/301/spec/epub-publications.html#sec-package-documents">Clause 3: Package Documents</a> from the EPUB Publications 3.0.1 specification.]<br/> Listed separately are the following requirements and recommendations emphasizing compliance with EPUB specifications:<ul>
						<li>For each rendition of the EPUB content document, there SHALL be a <i>manifest</i> file, which identifies and describes a set of resources that collectively compose a given rendition of a
 document, and EPUB <i>spine</i>, which provides a default reading order for a given rendition.  [Note: Required in the EPUB Publications 3.0.1 specification]</li>
						<li>The structure of each EPUB ZIP archive SHALL be described using the EPUB <i>container.xml</i>
 file (which describes the locations of root files of available renditions of the EPUB
publication, and the rendition’s package document and navigation document).  [Note: Consistent with requirements in the EPUB Open Container Format (OCF) 3.0.1 and the EPUB Publications 3.0.1 specifications both of which govern any EPUB file.]</li>
						<li>EPUB Package document and navigation document SHALL contain all metadata needed for rendering the publication, including the recommended reading system. [Note: The only obvious addition to the requirements in the EPUB Publications 3.0.1 specification is the need to identify a recommended reading system. This could be done using the <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/301/spec/epub-publications.html#sec-meta-elem">&lt;meta&gt;</a> element provided for in the EPUB Publications 3.0.1 specification.]</li>
						<li>The minimum required descriptive metadata for EPUB publications are <i>title</i>, <i>identifier</i>, and
<i>language</i> from the Dublin Core Metadata Element Set. Each rendition of a publication
SHOULD also have at least the <i>modified</i> date property from <a href="https://www.dublincore.org/specifications/dublin-core/dcmi-terms/#http://purl.org/dc/terms/modified">DCMI Metadata Terms</a>.
Each rendition SHOULD also have the publication date encoded as DCMI <i>date</i>, if the
publication date is required to distinguish between publications.  [Note: The recommendations beyond the EPUB requirements relate to identification of intended replacement submissions or different editions.]</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>Requirements and recommendations related to possible external dependencies:<ul>
						<li>Submitted EPUB publications SHALL either contain or at least facilitate access to all the data and metadata required to render the content information successfully. [Note: This is a primary objective of the EPUB family of formats.]</li>
						<li>Fonts SHALL be embedded into the EPUB publication in full and un-obfuscated, if permitted by the font license.</li>
						<li>Remotely-hosted resources SHOULD be avoided.</li>
						<li>Related resources such as audio and video SHOULD be embedded in the EPUB publication.</li>
						<li>If an EPUB content document in a SIP contains scripting, the EPUB publication SHALL contain a
fallback for the content in question. In the EPUB context scripting enables the use of JavaScript
applications for e.g. image manipulation or enabling dynamic changes of the content.  [Note: TS 22424-1 does not make this statement explicitly, but TS 22424-2 includes it in a summary of requirements from TS 22424-1.  <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-contentdocs.html#sec-scripted-content">2.4 Scripted Content Documents</a> in the EPUB Content Documents 3.0 specification states that EPUB Content Documents may provide fallbacks for such content.]</li>
						<li>Descriptive and other metadata SHOULD be embedded in the SIP. [Note: TS 22424:2020 does not require that such metadata be embedded in the EPUB file.]</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>Requirements and recommendations related to identifiers:<ul>
						<li>Identifiers SHALL be used in such a way that the OAIS archive will be able to link all versions of the publication and delete preview versions as appropriate.</li>
						<li>International standard identifiers, such as ISBNs for books and DOIs for articles, SHALL be
used as EPUB unique identifiers whenever possible.</li>
						<li>It SHOULD be possible to express the identifiers (also) as actionable HTTP URIs. Use of persistent identifiers (Handles, DOIs, URNs, or ARKs) is recommended.</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>Constraints related to technical protection:<ul>
						<li>EPUB publications in SIPs SHOULD NOT be encrypted.</li>
						<li>DRM protection, if any, SHOULD be removed before the document is submitted.</li>
						<li>If data is compressed, the user [sic] of the compression method SHALL be specified using the Compression metadata element in the EPUB’s encryption.xml file. [Note: <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/301/spec/epub-ocf.html#sec-zip-container-zipreqs">3.2 ZIP File Requirements</a> in the EPUB Open Container Format (OCF) 3.0.1 specification, requires that files in the ZIP archive be uncompressed or use Deflate compression. The compilers of this resource have not found a Compression element in a schema for the encryption.xml file. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</li>
					</ul>
				</li>
				<li>If there is a foreign resource embedded or linked to [in] a submitted EPUB publication, a
fallback chain ending in a core media type resource SHOULD be provided even if the foreign resource is in an archivable format. This requirement is stricter than those in the EPUB 3.x specifications, which require a fallback only in certain situations.</li>
				<li>If there are multiple renditions of a work in an EPUB publication, requirements in the <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/renditions/multiple/">EPUB Multiple-Rendition Publications 1.0</a> specification SHALL be followed. Each rendition of an
EPUB publication in a SIP SHALL have its own identifier.</li>
				<li>EPUB Fragment Identifiers SHOULD not be used in EPUB publications sent to a repository
system.  [Note: Fragment identifiers are designed for use in references from outside an EPUB file to permit opening an EPUB Publication at a particular location.  This prohibition presumably applies to fragment identifiers within one EPUB Publication to a location in another EPUB Publication.]</li>
				<li>Distributable objects (as defined in <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/do/">EPUB Distributable Objects 1.0

Draft Specification 23 July 2015</a>) SHALL NOT be submitted individually. They MAY be embedded within EPUB publications. [Note: the draft specification for Distributable Objects defines a refinement to the EPUB 3.0.1 specification, based on a &lt;<i>collection</i>&gt; element in the EPUB Package Document with the <i>role</i> attribute of &quot;distributable-object&quot;.  An example of how this construct may be used is for an EPUB Package Document that represents an entire book, but includes markup and metadata that permits individual chapters to be extracted and transformed into separate EPUB Package Documents.]</li>
			</ul>
			<p>TS 22424-2:2020 (Metadata requirements) provides requirements and recommendations for metadata associated with a SIP. Most of the recommendations are associated with the use of METS.  The following requirements and recommendations relate to metadata in EPUB files.  Notes enclosed in [ ] have been added by the compilers of this resource.  There is some overlap with the list from TS 22424-1.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>This document does not require copying of EPUB structural metadata to METS documents.</li>
				<li>A publication identifier [e.g., ISBN] SHALL NOT be used as [a SIP] package identifier. A SIP can contain multiple EPUB
publications; one EPUB publication can be submitted in multiple SIPs and even if a SIP contains just one
publication it may be necessary to re-send the SIP with other package identifier.  [Note: An example suggests that a publication identifier can be concatenated with a date and time of modification as an identifier for the SIP package using the @ sign as a separator.  This is consistent with a recommendation in <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/301/spec/epub-publications.html#sec-opf-metadata-identifiers-pid">4.1.2 Release Identifier</a> in the EPUB Publications 3.0.1 specification.]</li>
				<li>EPUB publications in SIPs SHOULD contain resources in file formats not suitable for preservation if and
only if the same resource is also included in an acceptable file format using a fallback mechanism.  [Note: TS 22424:2020 assumes that an archive specifies a list of acceptable formats as part of a general submission policy or specific submission agreement.]</li>
				<li>The internal structure of an EPUB publication SHALL, according to the EPUB standard, be specified in
an EPUB Navigation Document in both human and machine readable format.  [Note:  The specification for an EPUB Navigation Document is in <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/301/spec/epub-contentdocs.html#sec-xhtml-nav">2.2 EPUB Navigation Documents</a> in the EPUB Content Documents 3.0.1 specification.]</li>
				<li>Each EPUB publication in a SIP SHALL contain the complete table of contents in the EPUB navigation
document, covering all levels of the document hierarchy (see
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150317012427/http://www.idpf.org/accessibility/guidelines/content/nav/toc.php">http://www.idpf.org/accessibility/guidelines/content/nav/toc.php</a>). [Note: The cited document has been superseded.  The link provided here is to an Internet Archive capture that appears to have the appropriate statement.]</li>
				<li>The EPUB manifest file manifest.xml SHALL be compliant with the EPUB Open Container Format
requirements.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Provides requirements and recommendations, including some beyond those in the EPUB 3 specifications, for use when EPUB files are submitted to an archive for long-term preservation and access.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>An EPUB file is likely to be used primarily as a final-state format, for dissemination to end-users.  It may also be used as a middle-state format for transfer between a publisher and an entity that makes eBooks available to end users.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Other</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000310</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Electronic Publication (EPUB) File Format Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>These guidelines for preservation apply primarily to EPUB 3.0 and EPUB 3.0.1, but are also relevant to other versions of the EPUB File Format Family.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Other</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000311</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_3_0_1</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>EPUB, Electronic Publication, Version 3.0.1 (2014). ISO/IEC 23736:2020</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Recommends restrictions on EPUB 3.0.1 for using in a submission package to a preservation archive.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Other</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000308</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_3_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>EPUB, Electronic Publication, Version 3.0 (2011). ISO/IEC TS 30135:2014</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Recommends restrictions on EPUB 3.0 for using in a submission package to a preservation archive.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>See <fddLink id="fdd000310">EPUB_family</fddLink> for experience with EPUB documents.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See <fddLink id="fdd000310">EPUB_family</fddLink>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>The EPUB3 Preservation specification has been published as a Technical Specification by ISO/IEC.  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/deliverables-all.html">Deliverables: The different types of ISO publications</a>, which states, &quot;A Technical Specification addresses work still under technical development, or where it is believed that there will be a future, but not immediate, possibility of agreement on an International Standard.&quot;</p>
			<p>The specification was developed under the auspices of a special joint working group (ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 34/JWG 7).  JWG 7 spans several ISO and IEC committees: JTC 1/SC 34 (Document description and processing languages), ISO TC 46/SC 4 (Technical interoperability), and IEC/TC 100/TA 10 (Multimedia e-publishing and e-book technologies).</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>The technical specifications are available for purchase from ISO, national standards organizations, and commercial suppliers of standards.  See <a href="#specs">Format Specifications</a> below for links to the ISO catalog.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020 does not define a format, but provides guidelines intended to make it easier for
producers and OAIS archives to preserve access to EPUB documents.  The compilers of this resource have not attempted to assess the degree to which preservation archives have submission policies that follow these recommendations in general or specifically for content in the EPUB 3 formats.  One institution whose practices are cited in the technical specifications is the National Digital Preservation Services of Finland, which has published <a href="https://digitalpreservation.fi/en/specifications">specifications</a>, including one for <a href="https://digitalpreservation.fi/files/Metadata-1.7.2.pdf">Metadata Requirements and Preparing Content for Digital Preservation</a> which is intended to apply to digital content in all acceptable formats, including EPUB.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>Not applicable directly.  See <fddLink id="fdd000310">EPUB_family</fddLink>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Not applicable directly.  See <fddLink id="fdd000310">EPUB_family</fddLink>.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>ISO/IEC TS 22424-2:2020 gives requirements and recommendations for metadata of various categories needed in an OAIS SIP: descriptive; structural; administrative; preservation; provenance; rights management.  See also <fddLink id="fdd000310">EPUB_family</fddLink>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>
			<p>The EPUB 3.0 and 3.0.1 specifications permit audio and video resources to be stored remotely, but encourage the inclusion of such media files in the EPUB Container.  See, for example, <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-publications.html#sec-resource-locations">5.3 Publication Resource Locations</a> in the EPUB Publications 3.0 specification. EPUB 3.2, not formally covered by ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020, also allows fonts and resources retrieved by scripts to be located remotely.  See <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/epub32/epub-spec.html#sec-resource-locations">3.2 Resource Locations</a> in the EPUB 3.2 specification.</p>
			<p>ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020 makes a stronger recommendation, using the SHOULD term,  for including all resources in the EPUB container.</p>
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>An EPUB file that complies with the requirements and recommendations in ISO/IEC TS 22424:2020 will have no form of technical protection except obfuscation for any font with license terms that require it.  The decryption process required to use the obfuscated fonts is described in the EPUB Open Container Format (OCF) specifications, e.g. at <a href="http://idpf.org/epub/30/spec/epub30-ocf.html#fobfus-algorithm">4.2 Obfuscation Algorithm</a>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>See <fddLink id="fdd000310">EPUB_family</fddLink>.</fdd:normalText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000311">EPUB_3_0_1</fddLink>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>Activities at W3C related to EPUB specifications</b>: W3C has an activity known as <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/">Publishing@W3C</a>, which has a number of subgroups.   Formed in early, the W3C EPUB 3 Community Group was <a href="https://www.w3.org/2017/02/EPUB3CGcharter">chartered</a> to carry out &quot;ongoing technical development of EPUB 3 and related extension specifications and ancillary deliverable.&quot; This group published the EPUB 3.2 specification as a Final Report in May 2019.  A blog post on March 18, 2020, <a href="https://www.w3.org/blog/2020/03/listen-to-the-people-the-future-of-epub-and-new-directions-for-publishing-w3c/">Listen to the People: The Future of EPUB and New Directions for Publishing @ W3C</a>, announced the formation of a new EPUB 3 Working Group to focus on making EPUB 3 a W3C Recommendation by June 2022 and the continuing maintenance of EPUB 3.  Also part of Publishing@W3C is a <a href="https://www.w3.org/publishing/groups/publ-bg/">Publishing Business Group</a>, formed to foster ongoing participation by members of the publishing industry and overall publishing ecosystem in the development of the Web for publishing, and serve as a conduit for feedback between the publishing ecosystem and W3C.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The creation of the principles in ISO/IEC TS 22424-1:2020 was inspired by the draft
common requirements published by the E-ARK Project.  See <a href="https://dilcis.eu/images/Specifications/CS/Common_Specifications_For_IPs_v017.pdf">Common Specification for Information Packages (CSIP) v .17 (December 2016)</a>.  This document has since been updated under the auspices of the Digital Information LifeCycle Interoperability Standards Board.  See <a href="https://dilcis.eu/specifications/common-specification">Common Specification for Information Packages (CSIP)</a>.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/73163.html</link>
					<tag>ISO/IEC TS 22424-1:2020, Digital publishing — EPUB 3 Preservation — Part 1: Principles</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/73169.html</link>
					<tag>ISO/IEC TS 22424-2:2020,
Digital publishing — EPUB 3 Preservation — Part 2: Metadata requirements</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources from the International Digital Publishing Forum (IDPF)</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/301/</link>
							<tag>Introduction to EPUB Version 3.0.1 Specifications at IDPF</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/do/</link>
							<tag>EPUB Distributable Objects 1.0.

Draft Specification 23 July 2015</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/renditions/multiple/</link>
							<tag>EPUB Multiple-Rendition Publications 1.0.

Recommended Specification 26 August 2015 </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://idpf.org/epub/dir/</link>
							<tag>EPUB Specifications and Projects (12 February 2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Format assessments</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.dpconline.org/images/7/73/EPUB_Assessment_v1.4a.pdf</link>
							<tag>EPUB Format Preservation Assessment, V. 1.4 (2019) | by British Library</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.dpconline.org/images/a/a9/EPUB_Assessment_v1.2.pdf</link>
							<tag>EPUB Format Preservation Assessment, V. 1.2 (2015) | by British Library</tag>
							<comment>This version is cited in ISO/IEC TS 22424-1:2020.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.harvard.edu/confluence/display/digitalpreservation/Word+Processing+Formats?preview=%2F204385883%2F207554259%2FFormat+profile+-+ePUB+v04.docx</link>
							<tag>EPUB Format Assessment (2014) | by Paul Wheatley, for Harvard Digital Preservation Services</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://openpreservation.org/system/files/epubForArchivalPreservation20072012ExternalDistribution.pdf</link>
							<tag>EPUB for archival preservation (2012) | by Johan van der Knijff, KB/ National Library of the Netherlands</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://dilcis.eu/images/Specifications/CS/Common_Specifications_For_IPs_v017.pdf</link>
					<tag>Common Specification for Information Packages (CSIP) v .17 (December 2016) | originated from E-Ark Project</tag>
					<comment>Now maintained by the Digital Information LifeCycle Interoperability Standards (DILCIS) Board.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://dilcis.eu/specifications/common-specification</link>
					<tag>Common Specification for Information Packages (CSIP) | from DILCIS</tag>
					<comment>Provides links to other versions of CSIP documentation.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://digitalpreservation.fi/en/specifications</link>
					<tag>Specifications for National Digital Preservation Services, Finland</tag>
					<comment>Includes &quot;Metadata Requirements and Preparing Content for Digital Preservation&quot; and a list of acceptable file formats.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to the OAIS Reference model, maintained by Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems (CCSDS) and adopted as an International Standard <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/57284.html">ISO 14721:2012
Space data and information transfer systems — Open archival information system (OAIS) — Reference model</a>.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://public.ccsds.org/Pubs/650x0m2.pdf</link>
							<tag>Reference Model for an Open Archival Information System (OAIS).  2012 Edition</tag>
							<comment>Consultative Committee for Space Data Systems Recommended Practice: CCSDS 650.0-M-2</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.oais.info/</link>
							<tag>Website for information about the OAIS Reference Model (ISO 14721)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See also <fddLink id="fdd000310">EPUB_family</fddLink>.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
