<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000402" shortName="PPTX/OOXML_Strict_2012" titleName="PPTX Strict (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-1: 2008-2012" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-0.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>presentation</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2014-10-13</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>PPTX Strict, (Office Open XML, PresentationML) ISO 29500-1:2008-2012, also ECMA-376, Editions 2-4.</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>Vector graphics</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>markup languages</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The Strict variant of PPTX described here disallows a variety of elements and attributes that are permitted in the more common Transitional variant (<fddLink id="fdd000397">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>).  The markup for the Strict variant is essentially a subset of markup for the Transitional variant, but the schemas use different namespaces and are distributed separately in complete form.</p>
			<p>The primary distinction between Strict and Transitional PPTX is that all use of the deprecated VML (Vector Markup Language) is disallowed in the Strict variant.  DrawingML is used for all graphics features in PPTX Strict.  Also disallowed are attributes or elements related to a deprecated practice for expressing percentages as integers used when techniques to save space and calculation time were deemed necessary.</p>
			<p>The Strict variant of PPTX was introduced during the standardization in ISO/IEC 29500 in 2008 with the intention of excluding features included in ECMA-376, Edition 1 that were present simply to handle bugs and features of earlier applications or to permit continued use of deprecated markup (e.g. VML markup for drawings).  The intent of the split of the markup specification into Strict (Part 1) and Transitional (Part 4) was that applications would create new documents in the Strict variant; however, in practice, pressure for backwards compatibility has meant that most new files are marked up by applications using the Transitional namespace even if they use no features that are incompatible with the Strict specification.</p>
			<p>For discussion of other aspects of the Strict PPTX format, see the description of the more common Transitional variant of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>A format for presentation documents in the Open Office XML (ISO 29500) format family.  The Strict variant of PPTX was introduced during the standardization in ISO/IEC 29500 in 2008; disallowed is the deprecated VML markup for graphics.  The ability to read Strict PPTX files was implemented in Microsoft&apos;s PowerPoint 2010; PowerPoint 2013 added the ability to write Strict files as an option.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Can be used in any production phase.  Likely used primarily for creating documents (initial state; for editing and review (middle-state); and for final use or distribution.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000395</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>OOXML Family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>OOXML (ISO/IEC 29500) Format Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000363</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>OPC/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Open Packaging Conventions (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-2:2008-2012</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Modification of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000399</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PPTX/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PPTX Transitional (Office Open XML), ISO 29500:2008-2012, ECMA-376, Editions 1-4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>The Transitional form of DOCX allows additional legacy markup to address backward compatibility with bugs and features of older word-processors.  The legacy markup is specified in Part 4 of ISO 29500. </fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000396</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName> MCE/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-3:2008-2012, ECMA-376, Editions 1-4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000075</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>In 2014, the Library of Congress is not aware of any documents in the Strict form of PPTX in its collections.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>As of September 2014, no format preference has been explicitly expressed by the Library of Congress in relation to acquisition of digital presentations for its collections.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>International open standard.  Maintained by ISO/IEC JTC1 SC34/WG4 as Part 1 of ISO/IEC 29500, first published in 2008.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>
				<i>ISO/IEC 29500-1, Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Part 1: Fundamentals and Markup Language Reference</i>.  Latest version (dated 2012 as of August 2014) is available from <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/">ISO/IEC Publicly Available Standards</a>.</p>
			<p>All editions of the OOXML standards as published by ECMA are available from <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376: Office Open XML File Formats</a>.  The split between Strict and Transitional variants of PPTX was introduced in Edition 2 of ECMA-376 which is identical to ISO/IEC 29500:2008.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The Strict variant of PPTX is not widely used or supported as of September 2014.  The ability to read Strict PPTX files was implemented in Microsoft&apos;s PowerPoint 2010; PowerPoint 2013 added the ability to write Strict files as an option.  Office 365 (a cloud-based  product) can also read and write Strict files.  As of September 2014, the latest version of PowerPoint for a desktop Mac (in Office for Mac 2011) can neither write nor read Strict files. </p>
			<p> Versions of LibreOffice since 4.2.3 can read Strict PPTX files.  A test using LibreOffice 4.3 suggests that PPTX files written by that application are always in the more common Transitional form.  </p>
			<p>Whether the Strict version of PPTX is more widely used in the future will likely depend on whether pressure on software vendors from governments for its adoption outweighs market pressure, which currently seems to favor backwards compatibility.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink> for functionality supported.</fdd:normalImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:textQF/>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>pptx</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Used for Strict and the more common Transitional form of DOCX.  A file with the .ppsx extension, intended to run as a slideshow rather than open for editing is based on the same specification and may have essentially identical markup.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.presentationml.presentation</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.presentationml.presentation">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>XML namespace declaration</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>http://purl.oclc.org/ooxml/presentationml/main</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>This namespace declaration is for the Strict variant of PPTX.  It occurs in the mandatory Main Document part of a PPTX file (package), usually with the name <i>/ppt/presentation.xml</i> and mapped to the prefix <i>p</i>.  The same namespace declaration will be found in a Strict .ppsx file.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Target=&quot;ppt/presentation.xml&quot;</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Will usually occur in the top-level Relationships part (<i>/_rels/.rels</i> part in an OPC package in the &lt;Relationships&gt; element of a PPTX or PPSX file.  In the Strict variant, it will be the target of a relationship of type <i>http://purl.oclc.org/ooxml/relationships/officeDocument</i>.  See root namespace and source relationship for Presentation Part in ISO/IEC 29500-1:2012, ยง13.3.6.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The latest versions of ISO/IEC 29500 are made available at no charge from ISO. The formal titles of the part that specifies the Strict variant of DOCX is <i>Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Part 1:  Fundamentals and Markup Language Reference</i>.  The schemas for the Strict variant described here are available as <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061750_ISO_IEC_29500-1_2012_Electronic_inserts.zip">electronic inserts</a> to Part 4.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/index.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC Publicly Available Standards</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061750_ISO_IEC_29500-1_2012_Electronic_inserts.zip</link>
							<tag>Schemas in W3C XML Schema language and in RELAX NG for the Strict variant of DOCX.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm</link>
					<tag>ECMA-376: Office Open XML File Formats</tag>
					<comment>Provides access to all chronological published versions.  </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/Feature_Comparison:_LibreOffice_-_Microsoft_Office</link>
					<tag>Feature Comparison: LibreOffice - Microsoft Office</tag>
					<comment>Indicates that LibreOffice 4.3 supports reading of Strict OOXML files.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.libreofficeforum.org/node/7505</link>
					<tag>What is the level of support for MS Office formats?</tag>
					<comment>Feb 2014 blog post from &quot;unofficial LibreOffice support forum&quot; with later addenda.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See the more common Transitional form of PPTX, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>
					</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
