<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000435" titleName="OpenDocument Presentation Document Format (ODP), Version 1.2,  ISO 26300-1:2015" shortName="ODF_presentation_1_2" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>presentation</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>office/business</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2015-12-30</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>OpenDocument Presentation Document Format (ODP), Version 1.2.  Part of OASIS Open Document Format for Office Applications, Version 1.2 and the equivalent ISO 26300-1:2015.</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>markup languages</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The OpenDocument Presentation Document Format (ODP), Version 1.2 (given the short name <i>ODF_presentation_1_2</i> here) is a format for editable documents that are presentations based on sequences of &quot;slides.&quot;  Designed to be a native format for applications for assembling slide-show presentations,  the format is sometimes called ODP after its usual file extension.  The term ODP will be used here to refer to ODF_presentation_1_2 and other chronological versions of the OpenDocument Presentation format. It is one of several subtypes in the <fddLink id="fdd000247">ODF family</fddLink> for particular content categories.  This description relates to part 1 of the ODF 1.2 specification as published by OASIS and the equivalent ISO/IEC 26300-1:2015 specification.  The standard specifies markup for presentations using the ODF <i>presentation:</i>, <i>draw:</i>, and <i>text:</i> namespaces in particular. Other namespaces used in many presentations are <i>table:</i>, <i>anim:</i>, <i>smil:</i>.</p>
			<p>The primary ODF markup used for presentations is actually in the <i>draw:</i> namespace, with the <i>&lt;draw:page&gt;</i> element as the usual container for a single slide.  The content.xml file’s &lt;office:presentation&gt; element typically holds a series of &lt;draw:page&gt; elements, each of which has a unique <i>draw:name</i> attribute, often in the form <i>page</i>n.  The <i>presentation:</i> namespace is used for presentation-specific elements, such as <i>&lt;presentation:notes&gt;</i>, <i>&lt;presentation:animations&gt;</i> and specifications for headers and footers on slides.</p>
			<p>The ODF specification covers two physical forms for ODF documents, a flat form as a single XML file and a package form based on the <fddLink id="fdd000355">ZIP_6_2_0</fddLink> format.  This description focuses on the more commonly used ZIP-based package format for ODF presentation files, given the <i>.odp</i> file extension.  Files using the same markup specification and package but with an extension of <i>.otp</i> are for use as presentation document templates.</p>
			<p>An ODF package can be recognized as a presentation document in several ways.  Externally, there are file extensions for two ways in which ODF presentation documents may be used in graphics applications, as noted above.  The primary internal indication is that the mandatory file named <i>mimetype</i> will contain one of the corresponding strings listed as <a href="#sign">File type signifiers</a> below.  An additional way to recognize an ODF presentation document is that  the &lt;office:body&gt; element, a child of the root &lt;office:document-content&gt; element in content.xml has the child element &lt;office:presentation&gt;.</p>
			<p>The ZIP-based package for any ODF file contains, at a minimum, five files:  a one-line <i>mimetype</i> file containing a single text string; <i>content.xml</i>; <i>styles.xml</i>; <i>meta.xml</i>; and <i>settings.xml</i>.  The typical <i>content.xml</i> file for a minimal presentation document has the basic form:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>&lt;office:document-content&gt;</li>
				<li>&lt;office:automatic-styles&gt;</li>
				<li>... styles created automatically based on direct user choices, e.g., for margins or default fill color for shapes, with references to fuller and named style specifications in <i>styles.xml</i> ...</li>
				<li>&lt;/office:automatic-styles&gt;</li>
				<li>&lt;office:body&gt;</li>
				<li>&lt;office:presentation&gt;</li>
				<li>&lt;draw:page draw:name=&quot;page1&quot;&gt; ... content for a slide.  The name shown here is conventional rather than required by the standard, which only requires uniqueness.</li>
				<li>&lt;draw:page draw:name=&quot;page2&quot;&gt; ... </li>
				<li>   ...   </li>
				<li>&lt;/office:presentation&gt;</li>
				<li>&lt;/office:body&gt;</li>
				<li>&lt;/office:document-content&gt;</li>
				<li>Note that several of these elements will usually have attributes omitted here. Additional elements in the office: namespace may be included within the office:presentation element to reflect application-specific defaults.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>For details of the ZIP-based package for ODF_presentation_1_2, see <fddLink id="fdd000425">ODF_package_1_2</fddLink>.  The package specification defines the form for the package manifest, and options for digital signatures, encryption, etc.</p>
			<p>See Notes in <fddLink id="fdd000247">ODF Family</fddLink> for more information about the flat XML-only variant of ODF files.  For a flat ODF presentation file, the root <i>&lt;office:document&gt;</i> element has an <i>office:mimetype</i> attribute with one of
the values listed below as <a href="#sign">File signifiers</a>.</p>
			<p>Apart from changes to the underlying package format, changes made to the markup for ODF presentations between ODF versions 1.1 and 1.2 were limited to a few enhancements.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>An XML-based format for editable presentation documents, usually with file extension .odp.   Part of the OpenDocument Format (ODF) format family.  Documented in ODF 1.2 Part 1.  Component files are packaged using a constrained version of the ZIP format.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Can be used in any production phase: for creating documents (initial state); for editing and review (middle-state); and for final use or distribution.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000247</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ODF_Family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>OpenDocument Format (ODF) Family, OASIS and ISO/IEC 26300</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000436</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ODF_draw_1_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>OpenDocument Drawing Document Format (ODG), Version 1.2, ISO 26300:2015</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Presentations typically consist of sequences of &quot;drawings,&quot; with each slide represented by a drawing.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Other ODF document categories, such as charts and drawings embedded in individual slides.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Embedded images, sound, or video, in base64 encoding.  <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink> is recommended for bit-mapped images.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000425</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ODF_package_1_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>OpenDocument Package Format, ODF 1.2, ISO 26300-3:2015</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000355</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ZIP_6_2_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>ZIP File Format, Version 6.2.0 (PKWARE)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Various features of the ZIP File Format are not permitted in ODF.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>META-INF/manifest.xml file. This manifest file is mandatory in all ODF packages.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>ODP 1.1, not described separately on this site.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000263</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML_1_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>XML (Extensible Markup Language) 1.0</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment> A normative RELAX NG schema is part of the specification for ODF 1.2, which includes the specification for chart documents.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:preference>As of December 2015, no format preference has been explicitly expressed by the Library of Congress in relation to acquisition of digital presentations for its collections.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>International open standard.  Developed and maintained by <a href="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=office">OASIS Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) TC</a> as part of the OpenDocument Format (ODF) 1.2 specification published by OASIS in 2011.  Also approved as part of the equivalent ISO/IEC 26300-1:2015 by ISO/IEC JTC1/SC34.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>Specifications from OASIS: <a href="https://www.oasis-open.org/standards#opendocumentv1.2">Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) Version 1.2</a>.  Markup specification for ODF 1.2 presentation documents are found primarily in chapters 9 and 10 of Part 1 of the specification.  The technical specification is through a <a href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/office/v1.2/os/OpenDocument-v1.2-os-schema.rng">normative RNG schema for primary component files for ODF documents.</a>.</p>
			<p>The identical specification is published as <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c066376_ISO_IEC_26300-3_2015.zip">ISO/IEC 26300-1:2015, Information technology -- Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) v1.2 Part 1: OpenDocument Schema.</a>
			</p>
			<p>The ODF 1.2 specification is divided into three parts, with the bulk of the markup specification in Part 1: OpenDocument Schema.  The package specification has been moved into a separate Part 3: Packages.</p>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000247">ODF_Family</fddLink> for a listing of namespaces that can be incorporated into any ODF 1.1 or ODF 1.2 document and links to associated specifications.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The major office suites using ODF as primary native format family include special applications for developing presentations and can read and write presentation documents as defined in ODF 1.2:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>LibreOffice uses ODF 1.2 as its native format, according to <a href="https://blog.documentfoundation.org/blog/2015/07/17/open-document-format-odf-1-2-published-as-international-standard-263002015-by-isoiec/">July 17, 2015 blog post</a> from The Document Foundation.  See <a href=" https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/impress/">LibreOffice Impress</a> and <a href="https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/images/a/ae/IG42-ImpressGuide.pdf">LibreOffice 4.2 Impress Guide</a>.</li>
				<li>OpenOffice introduced support for ODF 1.2 in the beta version of 3.0 in 2008, according to <a href="http://www.openoffice.org/marketing/3.0/featurelistbeta.html">Release Notes for OpenOffice 3.0 beta</a>.  <a href="https://www.openoffice.org/product/impress.html">Apache OpenOffice Impress</a> uses ODP as its native format.</li>
				<li>Calligra&apos;s presentation application is <a href="https://www.calligra.org/stage/">Stage</a>.  Calligra Stage uses ODP as the underlying file format.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Microsoft Office has supported direct editing of ODF 1.2 presentation documents since Office 2013.  PowerPoint features not supported or only partially supported in the .odp format are listed in <a href="https://support.office.com/en-us/article/Supported-features-in-OpenDocument-presentation-odp-format-f6d5b015-a417-4096-bf61-a5c3f58d125f">Supported features in OpenDocument presentation (.odp) format</a>.  This list suggests that some types of animation and transition supported in PowerPoint and by PPTX can not be represented in ODP.   There are also a number of vector graphic capabilities and design settings available in PowerPoint, that cannot be used in an ODP file.  <a href="https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/Feature_Comparison:_LibreOffice_-_Microsoft_Office#Presentation_software:_LibreOffice_Impress_vs._Microsoft_PowerPoint">A feature comparison</a> from LibreOffice focuses on the application functionality rather than the format.  See Notes in the description of <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX Transitional (Office Open XML)</fddLink> for a discussion of issues relating to conversion between PPTX and ODP, both issues that have been found in practice, and potential issues based on functionality added recently.</p>
			<p>See Adoption among the Sustainability Factors for <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX Transitional (Office Open XML)</fddLink> for discussion of the market for presentation software.  Additional <a href="#useful">useful references</a> below highlight the crowded market for presentation software, with a recent emphasis on creative ways to leave behind the traditional slide-by-slide flow.  Lists of alternatives to PowerPoint often have no mention of any application using ODP as native format.  Where LibreOffice is recommended, it is often as a largely compatible free alternative to PowerPoint.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000247">ODF-Family</fddLink> for more detail on adoption of ODF in general, and particularly for mandates or recommendations for ODF when exchanging editable documents among government agencies and the individiduals or organizations they serve.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No concerns.  See <fddLink id="fdd000247">ODF_Family</fddLink>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>The structure and text of an ODP file are all represented in XML and hence viewable without special tools, although XML-aware tools that can show the element hierarchy make viewing and interpretation more convenient.  The most commonly used parts, elements, and attributes have recognizable names. Simple documents can be interpreted with very basic tools. However, interpreting the semantics of some elements and the correspondence of some elements and attributes to charting terminology or functionality will require not only understanding of the schema and the specification text, but familiarity with the associated terminology and functionality.</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>As for other members of the ODF 1.2 family, ODF_presentation_1_2 added support for metadata based on RDF (W3C&apos;s Resource Description Framework).  As well as using RDF for metadata for the document package as a whole, RDF can be attached to elements within the document&apos;s content.  The use of &quot;custom&quot; metadata as specified in ODF 1.1 is deprecated in ODF 1.2.</p>
			<p>Pre-defined metadata elements for the document as a whole, stored in an <i>&lt;office:meta&gt;</i> element  include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>From the Dublin core namespace, using the <i>dc:</i> prefix: Title, Creator (of most recent modification), Description, Subject, Date (last modified), Language</li>
				<li>From the ODF specification, using the <i>meta:</i> prefix: Generator (creating software application), Keywords, Initial Creator, Creation Date and Time, Modification Date and Time, Print Date and Time, Document Template, Document Statistics (word count, page count, etc.),</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The pre-defined elements are all optional and repeatable.  However, applications are not required to update multiple occurrences in a specific way to reflect modifications to a document.</p>
			<p>Also supported in both ODF 1.1 and ODF 1.2 is an XML structure for user-defined metadata, based on triplets of name, data type, and value.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>
			<p>Depends on features used.  Presentation documents in ODF_presentation_1_2 format are often self-contained, but may include links to externally stored data.</p>
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>Encryption is supported for files within an ODF 1.1 or ODF 1.2 package.  In addition, an ODF package file may be encrypted during interchange or as part of DRM controlling distribution.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>
				<p>No specific set of factors for assessing quality and functionality of a presentation format has been developed.  This format description uses selected factors for assessing formats for images and text.</p>
				<p>Graphics and text on a slide are structured to scale with monitor size.  Raster images can be incorporated in a slide and &quot;may have an arbitrary format&quot; but the ODF standard recommends use of  <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink>.</p>
			</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>Since slides are intended for display on monitors, support for very high spatial resolution or high-bit-depth is not needed.  For vector graphics and text effects, ODF 1.2 uses the notation #rrggbb and the RGB color model (assuming the sRGB colorspace).</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>There is no support for ICC profiles or other color management mechanisms intended to produce consistent color on different devices.  Accuracy of perceived color is not considered crucial for presentations.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>Excellent support for typographic effects and vector graphics, using all the capabilities supported for <fddLink id="fdd000436">ODF_draw_1_2</fddLink>.</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:multispectral>Not relevant for a format aimed at presentations.</fdd:multispectral>
			<fdd:beyondImage>
				<p>Support for animations, slide transitions, and user interactions during presentations.  Selected elements borrowed from the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2005/REC-SMIL2-20050107/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL) 2.0</a> specification can be used to animate text on a slide.</p>
			</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>Editable document. Textual content is conveniently extractable for quotation and for indexing. Full support for Unicode.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>The ordering of slides and of textual lists on slides is indicated by order of elements.  Relationships between slides and embedded content are indicated by nesting of elements.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>Excellent support for layout choices. Represents entire layout and formatting as intended by an author who used an application for which ODP is a native format. Differences in detail can occur on display if the original fonts used are not available in the system used for viewing.  Bi-directional and vertical display of text can be specified; see <a href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/office/v1.2/os/OpenDocument-v1.2-os-part1.html#__RefHeading__1420402_253892949">Appendix E of the ODF 1.2 specification</a>.</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>Equations can be represented using MathML, either as independent files or as drawing objects that can be embedded in slides.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>
				<p>Selected elements borrowed from the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2005/REC-SMIL2-20050107/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL) 2.0</a> specification can be used to animate text on a slide.</p>
			</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>odp</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>
					<i>.odp</i> is the extension used for an ODF presentation file.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.oasis.opendocument.presentation</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The MIME types for ODF_presentation_1_2  are the same as for earlier versions</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>Magic numbers that apply to ODF document category subtypes incorporate the magic number for  <fddLink id="fdd000354">ZIP_PK</fddLink>,  the string <i>mimetype</i> at position 30, and the MIME subtype string value at position 38.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Indicator for profile, level, version, etc.</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: office:version=&quot;1.2&quot;</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>The four root elements used in the primary files in an ODF package all require an attribute that records the ODF version.  This is the signifier that distinguishes ODF 1.2 packages from earlier versions.  Documents without this attribute are assumed to be from version 1.1 or earlier.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>otp</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The extension <i>.otp</i> is used for a presentation document used as a template.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.oasis.opendocument.presentation-template</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/293</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>For ODP 1.2.  See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pronom/fmt/293">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pronom/fmt/293</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q27204002</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>For OpenDocument Presentation, version 1.2.  See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q27204002">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q27204002</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p> See <a href="http://books.evc-cit.info/books/odbook/ch07.html">OASIS OpenDocument Essentials: Chapter 7. Presentations</a> for examples of markup for transitions, animations, and interactions. Elements borrowed from the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2005/REC-SMIL2-20050107/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL) 2.0</a> specification can be used to animate text on a slide.</p>
			<p>See Notes section in description for <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX Transitional (Office Open XML)</fddLink> for discussion of issues relating to conversion between PPTX and ODP.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000425">ODF_package_1_2</fddLink> for discussion of changes to ODF in general between versions 1.1 and 1.2.  Changes to the markup for presentations between versions 1.1 and 1.2 were primarily enhancements requested by implementers.  <a href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/office/v1.2/os/OpenDocument-v1.2-os-part1.html#__RefHeading__1420418_253892949">Appendix G of the ODF 1.2 schema specification</a> suggests that a functional extension was support for tables in presentations.  No elements or attributes were added to the <i>presentation:</i> namespace.</p>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000247">ODF_family</fddLink> for more on the history ODF in general.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Specifications as published by OASIS</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.oasis-open.org/standards#opendocumentv1.2</link>
							<tag>Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) Specification v1.2</tag>
							<comment>Provides links to all versions of specifications and supporting files for ODF 1.2.  The specification for the chart file and the chart: namespace is in Part 1: Schemas.  The specification for the ODF package is in ODF 1.2, Part 3: Packages (available as ODT, PDF, and HTML.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://docs.oasis-open.org/office/v1.2/os/OpenDocument-v1.2-os-schema.rng</link>
							<tag>Normative RNG schema for mandatory manifest file for an ODF 1.2 package.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Specifications as published by ISO/IEC</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c066363_ISO_IEC_26300-1_2015.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 26300-1:2015, Information technology -- Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) v1.2, Part 1: Schema</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c066376_ISO_IEC_26300-3_2015.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 26300-1:2015, Information technology -- Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) v1.2, Part 3: Packages</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://books.evc-cit.info/books/odbook/ch07.html</link>
					<tag>OASIS OpenDocument Essentials.  Chapter 7. Presentations.  By J. David Eisenberg. 2005</tag>
					<comment>Based on ODF 1.1.  Still applicable to ODF 1.2, since markup changes for presentations were enhancements rather than changes in basics.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://blog.documentfoundation.org/blog/2015/07/17/open-document-format-odf-1-2-published-as-international-standard-263002015-by-isoiec/</link>
					<tag>Open Document Format (ODF) 1.2 published as International Standard 26300:2015 by ISO/IEC</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Documentation for LibreOffice and Apache OpenOffice, applications that use ODF 1.2 formats as their native formats, provides useful examples and background information.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/impress/</link>
							<tag>LibreOffice: Discover /
Impress
</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/images/e/ea/GS4206-GettingStartedWithImpress.pdf</link>
							<tag>Getting Started with LibreOffice Impress</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/images/a/ae/IG42-ImpressGuide.pdf</link>
							<tag>LibreOffice: Impress Guide -- Working with Presentations</tag>
							<comment>Published 26 August 2014. Based on LibreOffice 4.2</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/Feature_Comparison:_LibreOffice_-_Microsoft_Office#Presentation_software:_LibreOffice_Impress_vs._Microsoft_PowerPoint</link>
							<tag>Feature Comparison -- Presentation software: LibreOffice Impress vs. Microsoft PowerPoint</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.openoffice.org/documentation/manuals/userguide3/0500IG3-ImpressGuideOOo3.pdf</link>
							<tag>OpenOffice.org (version 3) Impress Guide</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nouenoff.nl/downloads/LibreOffice_AOO_CompetitiveFeatureMatrix_20150318.pdf</link>
					<tag>Comparing LibreOffice and Apache OpenOffice</tag>
					<comment>Includes timeline of releases and links to release notes as well as detailed comparison of features.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Documents for developers and help files from Microsoft on its support for ODF_presentation_1_2 in Office:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh695327.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OODF3]: Office Implementation Information for ODF 1.2 Standards Support</tag>
							<comment>Applies to both Client and Server implementations of Microsoft Office 2013 and Microsoft Office 2016</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd922722.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OFFDI]: 4. Microsoft PowerPoint Persistence Formats</tag>
							<comment>Lists OpenDocument Format as a persistence format for PowerPoint. Includes ODF 1.2.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd943359.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OFFDI]: 4.4.2 Application and Versions (PowerPoint)</tag>
							<comment>Indicates support for ODF 1.2 in PowerPoint 2013 and later.  Also that if an ODP 1.1 presentation is opened in PowerPoint 2013, it will be saved in ODF 1.2 format.  This likely applies also to Excel 2016.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20170501074530/https://support.office.com/en-us/article/Supported-features-in-OpenDocument-presentation-odp-format-f6d5b015-a417-4096-bf61-a5c3f58d125f</link>
							<tag>Supported features in OpenDocument presentation (.odp) format.</tag>
							<comment>Details for versions of PowerPoint since 2007 SP2.  As of May 2017.  This page is not currently online.  Linked via the Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://support.office.com/en-us/article/use-powerpoint-to-open-or-save-a-presentation-in-the-opendocument-presentation-odp-format-94805e84-1b09-4c98-a8b5-0da2a52242a0</link>
							<tag>Use PowerPoint to open or save a presentation in the OpenDocument Presentation (.odp) format</tag>
							<comment>Support goes back to PowerPoint 2007 SP2.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Reviews and comparisons of presentation software.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.jonobacon.org/2015/10/10/what-libreoffice-impress-needs-to-rock/</link>
							<tag>What LibreOffice Impress Needs To Rock.  Blog post from October 2015</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://slidedog.com/blog/best-powerpoint-alternatives-presentation-tools-2015/</link>
							<tag>Best PowerPoint Alternatives and Presentation Tools of 2015</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ask.metafilter.com/259716/Apple-Keynote-or-OpenOffice-Impress-for-making-Powerpoints</link>
							<tag>Apple Keynote or OpenOffice Impress for making Powerpoints?  Q&amp;A from April 2014.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://blog.bizzabo.com/30-conference-presentation-tools-to-help-speakers-wow-attendees</link>
							<tag>30 Conference Presentation Tools To Help Speakers Wow Attendees.  Blog post from May 2015. </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.techradar.com/us/news/software/business-software/the-best-presentation-software-for-businesses-1256592</link>
							<tag>The best presentation software: top 5 PowerPoint alternatives.  Article from July 2014.</tag>
							<comment>Does not mention Impress.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.powtoon.com/blog/best-free-presentation-software-and-powerpoint-alternative/</link>
							<tag>Free Presentation Software &amp; Best PowerPoint Alternative.  Blog post from 2012.</tag>
							<comment>Does not mention Impress.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.customshow.com/best-powerpoint-alternatives-presentation-programs/</link>
							<tag>27 Presentation Software &amp; Powerpoint Alternatives For 2015.  From January 2015.</tag>
							<comment>Does not mention Impress.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pronom/fmt/293</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for OpenDocument Presentation 1.2</tag>
					<comment> PUID for OpenDocument Presentation 1.2 is fmt/293</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q27204002</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for OpenDocument Presentation, version 1.2</tag>
					<comment>Wikidata Title ID: Q27204002</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See also <fddLink id="fdd000247">ODF_Family</fddLink>.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
