<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000543" titleName="MXF Archive and Preservation Format Registered Disclosure Document (SMPTE RDD 48)" shortName="MXF_RDD48" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>sound</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
				</fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
			</fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>container-wrapper</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2024-06-10</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>MXF Archive and Preservation Format Registered Disclosure Document (SMPTE RDD 48)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>wrapper formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>container formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>RDD 48 is the abbreviated name for the <i>SMPTE RDD 48:2018 MXF Archive and Preservation Format Registered Disclosure Document</i>. (For more about the definition of a <a href="https://www.smpte.org/">SMPTE (Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers)</a> RDD, see <a href="https://www.smpte.org/standards/rdd">Registered Disclosure Documents</a>.) As described in the <a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/rdd48-2018_published.pdf">specification published by SMPTE</a> in 2018, &quot;RDD 48 specifies a vendor-neutral subset of the MXF file format for the long-term archiving and preservation of moving image and other audiovisual content, including all forms of Ancillary Data, together with Associated Materials.  Among other features, RDD 48 defines a means for the carriage and labeling of multiple timecodes and audio tracks; the handling of captions, subtitles, and Timed Text; a minimal core metadata set; program segmentation metadata; and embedded content integrity data." RDD 48 was sponsored and authored by the <a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/">Federal Agencies Digital Guidelines Initiative (FADGI)</a>'s AudioVisual Working Group. See <a href="notes">History</a> for more details about the evolution of the specification over time.</p>
			<p>Some of the key highlights of RDD 48 include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>Support for multiple timecodes, including legacy timecode.</b> As noted in the specification (p. 40), "RDD 48 files can contain many timecodes (one Master Timecode, many Historical Source Timecodes). Each timecode is represented by a Timecode Track, and the timecode data can occur simultaneously in several places. The Master Timecode can be stored in the Material Package, in the Top Level Source Package and in the System Item of an Essence Container. A Historical Source Timecode can be stored in the Top Level Source Package, in the System Item of an Essence Container, in the essence on a picture, sound or data Essence Container essence, or in a Lower Level Source Package." In support of this, one of the outcomes of the RDD 48 authoring process was the registration of new timecode subdescriptors in the <a href="https://registry.smpte-ra.org/apps/pages/published/">SMPTE Metadata Register</a> through the SMPTE TC-31FS (SG Timecode in MXF) working group.
</li>
				<li>
					<b>The carriage of extra information, beyond the basic picture and sound.</b> MXF files are made up of partitions – one is called the Generic Stream Partition.  A GSP can carry text-based (e.g., XML) or binary (e.g., still image) “streams.” The additional data can include EBU STL, Timed Text, other associated data like images of the packaging as well as supplementary metadata.
</li>
				<li>
					<b>Metadata</b>. RDD 48 defines four Descriptive Metadata Schemes (DMS) that can be included in an RDD 48 MXF file: RDD 48 Core Descriptive Metadata Scheme (AS_07_Core_DMS) pertains to the whole file and includes one or more identifiers for the file and its content, a high level description of the file's content (e.g., title or working title), identifies who is responsible for the file (the "keeper" in terms of long-term management), provides basic video characteristic information, identifies if captions are present, defines audio track allocations, and offers high level information about how the file was made; RDD 48 Generic Stream Partition Descriptive Metadata Framework (AS_07_GSP_BD_DMS) defines additional metadata elements for non-essence binary data stream when present; RDD 48 Generic Stream Partition Text-based Data Descriptive Metadata Framework (AS_07_GSP_TD_DMS) defines additional metadata elements for non-essence text-based data streams; and RDD 48 Segmentation Descriptive Metadata Scheme (AS_07_Segmentation_DMS) provides a description of both the individual segmented parts as well as the aggregate group of parts. Each of these is described in Annexes in the specification.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Content integrity data</b>. RDD 48 calls for the embedding of fixity data on the V or value data in the KLV triplets that represent frame-wrapped essences, specifically a Castagnoli CRC-32C hash value. In addition, RDD 48 defines a Cryptographic Context Set metadata scheme. See section 6.7.2. in the specification for details.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Manifest</b>.  RDD 48 defines an XML-based Manifest to support preservation and good housekeeping by offering an inventory of the RDD 48 file&apos;s parts and expresses the relationships between them. Overall, it provides a high level inventory of the parts including their identifiers, data description, MIME type, size and location. This information can help the user to better understand the composition of the file and it will also provide machine-interpretable information for content processing if, for example, an RDD 48-aware application used values in the DataDescription element to quickly locate the correct QC file in a workflow or to delete embedded graphics (binary data) prior to distribution. See section 6.7.1. in the specification for details.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>RDD 48 includes a subset of constraints called a &quot;shim&quot; in convention with AMWA convention called the &quot;Baseband Shim: Single Items from Baseband Video&quot;, and it is intended to support the reformatting of older analog and digital videotapes and, for some organizations, the encoding and packaging of &quot;live&quot; video streams sent to an archive via a serial interface. As described in section 6.2.10.1.1, &quot;RDD 48 Baseband Shim files are for items derived from baseband video, understood to encompass both analog baseband and uncompressed digital video, and encoders will typically process a baseband (uncompressed) signal. For high picture quality the preferred picture encodings for the baseband shim are <fddLink id="fdd000139">JPEG 2000 picture encoding</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000129">uncompressed picture</fddLink>.&quot; The Baseband Shim &quot;is intended to serve the most critical current use case for memory institutions: the reformatting of existing and obsolescent videotapes in their collections. The Baseband Shim is also intended to serve memory institutions (and others) who may be acquiring digital video ingested via serial interfaces, e.g., congressional high definition video transferred to the Library of Congress via HD-SDI or its equivalent. In both of these use cases, memory institutions wish to archive the highest possible quality of image and sound (uncompressed or losslessly compressed), as well as retaining source data such as multiple timecodes, captions and subtitles, and also embed metadata that will support authentication and management of the content for the long term.&quot; </p>
			<p>RDD 48 files employ three standardized MXF Operational Patterns: <fddLink id="fdd000266">OP1a</fddLink>, OP1b, and OP3c. OP1a is the most common implementation for RDD 48 and is used for both single item and segmented item files, OP1b [standardized through ST 391, MXF - Operational Pattern 1b (Single Item, Ganged Packages)] can also be used for both single item and segmented item files while OP3c [standardized through ST 408, Material Exchange Format (MXF) - Operational Patterns 1c, 2c and 3c] is used only for bundled collections of files. Links to purchase both standards are available from the <a href="https://www.smpte.org/standards/document-index/st">SMPTE Store</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>SMPTE RDD 48 specifies a vendor-neutral subset of the MXF file format for the long-term archiving and preservation of moving image and other audiovisual content, including all forms of Ancillary Data, together with Associated Materials.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Middle state</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000013</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MXF</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Material Exchange Format (MXF)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000203</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MXF_OP1a_UNC</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MXF File, OP1a, Uncompressed Images in Generic Container</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Outline only</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000206</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MXF_OP1a_JP2_LL</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MXF File, OP1a, Lossless JPEG 2000 in Generic Container</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000273</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MXF_OP1a_JP2_LSY</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MXF File, OP1a, Lossy JPEG 2000 in Generic Container</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000357</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>WAVE_BWF_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Broadcast WAVE Audio File Format, Version 2</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000359</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>WAVE_BWF_LPCM_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Broadcast WAVE File Format, Version 2, with LPCM Audio</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000258</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MXF_OP1a_D-10</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MXF File, OP1a, D-10 in Generic Container</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Outline only</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000544</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MXF_GC_FFV1</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>MXF Generic Container Mapped to FFV1 Encoding (SMPTE RDD 48 Amd 1)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress had planned to implement RDD 48 as its primary preservation format but lack of tools has slowed this effort. See <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See the Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement for format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/moving.html">moving image works</a>. See also <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard and fully described. RDD 48 was sponsored and authored by the <a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/">Federal Agencies Digital Guidelines Initiative (FADGI)</a>'s AudioVisual Working Group. Published by the Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers (SMPTE), a member of the American National Standards Institute (ANSI).</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>
				<a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/rdd48-2018_published.pdf">SMPTE RDD 48:2018 MXF Archive and Preservation Format Registered Disclosure Document</a>.</p>
			<p>The specification is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 4.0 International License. (CC BY-SA 4.0). The specification notes (p. 2): This document builds upon the <a href="https://static.amwa.tv/as-07-mxf-archive-and-preservation-spec.pdf">AS-07: MXF Archive &amp; Preservation Proposed Specification</a> published by the Advanced Media Workflow
Association (AMWA) in 2016. Following the rules of the CC BY-SA 4.0 license for adapted material, this updated document [RDD 48] continues with the
same CC BY-SA 4.0 license as the 2016 AMWA Proposed Specification document.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Adoption has been slow mostly because of a scarcity of tools and applications. FADGI&apos;s <a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/embARC.html">embARC</a> (metadata embedded for archival content) &quot;enables users to audit and correct embedded metadata to comply with FADGI guidelines. V.1.1.0 added  support for FFV1 in MXF to existing functionality for DPX (Guidelines for Embedded Metadata within DPX File Headers for Digitized Motion Picture Film) and MXF (SMPTE RDD 48: MXF Archive and Preservation Format) files.&quot;</p>
			<p>RDD 48 is included in the Target Format Comparison Tables for <a href="https://www.iasa-web.org/tc06/guidelines-preservation-video-recordings">IASA-TC 06 Guidelines for the Preservation of Video Recordings</a>
			</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>The specification notes "The user’s attention is called to the possibility that implementation and compliance with this specification may require use of subject matter covered by patent rights. By publication of this specification, no position is taken with respect to the existence or validity of any claim or of any patent rights in connection therewith. All responsibilities for identifying patents for which a license may be required or for conducting inquiries into the legal validity or scope of those patents are assumed by the user."</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>RDD 48 permits encryption as described in section 6.7.2.1. &quot;Although the use of encryption will be very rare in RDD 48 files, in order to allow for this rare use and also to remain consistent with ST 429-6:2006, RDD 48 files use that standard&apos;s terminology: Cryptographic Context Set (like a DM Scheme), Cryptographic Framework (like a DM Framework), and Cryptographic Framework DM Tracks. The Cryptographic Context Set implemented in RDD 48 includes three adaptations from the ST 429-6:2006 implementation: (1) the addition of the optional MICCarriage item, (2) specifying the permitted Null value as the default value for the CipherAlgorithm item and (3) specifying 0 (zero) as the default value for the CryptographicKeyID item.&quot;  See also <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>RDD 48 specifies a set of Descriptive Metadata Schemas (DMS) as well as a Manifest - both described in detail in <a href="#identification">Description</a>. See also <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>. <p>
				<b>Accessibility Features</b>
			</p>
			<p>RDD 48 has enhanced features that strongly support digital accessibility with its capacity for multiple timecode, caption and audio language tracks and identifiers. In addition, RDD 48 requires the translation of ANSI/CTA-608-E (CEA-608) and ANSI/CTA-708-E (CEA-708) data to SMPTE ST 2052-1 Timed Text to be carried in a Generic Stream Partition. Teletext, the text-only closed captioning system for European television, is carried in the ANC (Ancillary Data) packet and "the Top Level Source Package shall include a strong reference to the VBI Data Descriptor as detailed in SMPTE ST 436-1:2013. The descriptor shall be associated with a Data Track via the MXF Generic Descriptor (as defined in SMPTE 377-1:2011)." In RDD 48, teletext is considered a form of ANC.RDD 48 files need not include EBU-STL unless it is present in the source file. If EBU-STL is present in the source file, it is to be maintained in the RDD 48 file. See section 6.2.12 Captions, Subtitles, and Timed Text of the specification for specific details.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>See <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:movingImageQF>
			<fdd:normalVideo>Supported</fdd:normalVideo>
			<fdd:clarity>Potentially excellent; depends upon encoding.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:beyondVideo>Strong support for complex timecodes, multiple timecodes including historical ones, as well as strong support for related text and binary supplementary data types.</fdd:beyondVideo>
		</fdd:movingImageQF>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Supported</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>Potentially excellent; depends upon encoding. See <fddLink id="fdd000003">WAVE_LCPM_BWF</fddLink>
			</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>Strong support for multiple audio tracks and channels as defined in the RDD 48 files that conform to the requirements that follow will carry identifiers in the AS_07_Core_DMS_AudioTrackLayout. In addition, section 6.2.11.7.3 of the specification states that &quot;when the audio content in an RDD 48 file consists of SMPTE Multi-Channel Audio (MCA; SMPTE ST 377-4:2012), and when such information is provided by the encoding organization, conformant encoders shall produce files that provide the Descriptors specified in SMPTE ST 377-1:2011 and the Subdescriptors specified for MCA in SMPTE ST 377-4:2012.&quot;</fdd:channels>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>SMPTE Universal Label</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>060e2b34.04010101.0d010701.07010000</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>UL for AS_07_Core_DMS, Required Core Metadata for RDD 48 Archiving and Preservation Format. Additional required ULs for DMSes will be present but this label indicates that the file is an RDD 48 file.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Header partition pack key (MXF)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>06 0E 2B 34 04 01 01 01 0D 01 02 01 01 01 09</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>UL for OP1a Operational Pattern declaration in Header Partition Pack</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>No NARA File Format Preservation Plan ID as of June 2024.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM has no corresponding entry as of June 2024.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata has no corresponding entry as of June 2024.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>A robust set of <a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/MXF_app_sampleFiles.html">sample files</a>, some of which are graded as gold, silver, copper and lead depending on their error tolerance, is available for PAL and NTSC, including for <fddLink id="fdd000544">FFV1 in MXF Generic Container</fddLink> mapping for Amd 1, 2022. These files were created as part of a contract with AVP and their subcontractor EVS, first Product Development Manager Valérie Popie and later Engineering Manager Nicolas Bernard, to create a set of graded sample files in 2016 and 2017 based on RDD 48. These sample files were reviewed by Oliver Morgan of <a href="http://www.metaglue.com/website/index.php">Metaglue, Inc.</a> and Cube-Tec. Sample files starting in 2018 were created by Oliver Morgan of Metaglue. All sample files are in the public domain as the product of US federal government research. If a license is required, an appropriate license is CC0 1.0 Universal license for worldwide use and reuse as this parallels the license used for FADGI guidelines and documents.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>RDD 48 began as the Application Specification for Archiving and Preservation (ASAP) by FADGI. The AS-07 designation was assigned in 2012 when the specification came under <a href="https://www.amwa.tv/">Advanced Media Workflow Association, Inc. (AMWA)</a> auspices. Although AMWA had not yet established its Work in Progress (WIP) category, versions of AS-07 had been shared in a WIP manner with the archiving community five times and once as a Proposed Specification with peer review. The 2017 version was published under FADGI sponsorship, again with community peer review and is the last iteration to carry the AS-07 designation. Starting in 2018, the name is changed to Registered Disclosure Document (RDD) 48 and the document is <a href="https://www.smpte.org/standards/document-index/rdd">published by SMPTE</a>. Links to all published versions of the document are available on the <a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/">FADGI RDD 48 project page</a> in conjunction with a robust set of <a href="https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/MXF_app_sampleFiles.html">NTSC and PAL sample files</a>.</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/MXF_app_spec.html</link>
					<tag>Project page for SMPTE RDD 48:2018 MXF Archive and Preservation Format Registered Disclosure Document</tag>
					<comment>Includes links to earlier versions and sample files</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/rdd48-2018_published.pdf</link>
					<tag>Direct link to SMPTE RDD 48:2018 MXF Archive and Preservation Format Registered Disclosure Document (PDF)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See also <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>
					</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/</link>
					<tag>Federal Agencies Digital Guidelines Initiative (FADGI) homepage</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/MXF_app_sampleFiles.html</link>
					<tag>Federal Agencies Digital Guidelines Initiative (FADGI) MXF Sample Files</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.digitizationguidelines.gov/guidelines/embARC.html</link>
					<tag>Federal Agencies Digital Guidelines Initiative (FADGI) embARC</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.smpte.org/standards/rdd</link>
					<tag>SMPTE Registered Disclosure Documents</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.smpte.org/standards/document-index/st</link>
					<tag>SMPTE Store: Standards Documents</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.metaglue.com/website/index.php</link>
					<tag>Metaglue Inc</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.amwa.tv/</link>
					<tag>Advanced Media Workflow Association</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iasa-web.org/tc06/guidelines-preservation-video-recordings</link>
					<tag>IASA-TC 06 Guidelines for the Preservation of Video Recordings</tag>
					<comment>RDD 48 is included in the format comparison matrix, Part B-App. Appendix to section B.3 </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
