<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000096" titleName="Windows Media 9 Professional Video Codec" shortName="WMV9_PRO" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2010-05-26</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Windows Media 9 Professional Video Codec</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>Windows Media formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Video bitstream produced by the Windows Media 9 professional video codec.</p>
			<p>This format description seems to have been overtaken by events. During 2005, the Microsoft Web site stopped referring to a "professional" codec and instead began promoting an Advanced Profile with features tailored to high definition video content (see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below). During 2006, however, SMPTE finalized the VC-1 standard (421M), thus placing the Microsoft video codec family more in the mainstream. At the same time, a number of profiles and levels were established; for example, see the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VC-1">Wikipedia VC-1 article</a> and this <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/howto/articles/vc1techoverview.aspx">Microsoft information page</a>. At this Library of Congress Web site, the VC-1 connection is highlighted in the description of <fddLink id="fdd000095">WMV9</fddLink>, the fundamental Windows Media video codec. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments</a> on the best way to elucidate this topic are welcome. </p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Video bitstream produced by the Windows Media 9 professional video codec.  Also Windows Media Video Advanced Profile.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Generally used in files that represent a final-state format for end-user delivery.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000100</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>WMV_WMV9</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Windows Media Video file with WMV9 codec</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment/>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:preference>See <fddLink id="fdd000091">WMV</fddLink>
		</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Proprietary.  Developed by Microsoft.
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>Specifications not disseminated. 		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Extent of adoption is not known. </fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>See <fddLink id="fdd000067">ASF</fddLink> for link to pages covering licensing of Windows Media and the Advanced Systems Format.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication to build tools.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Not applicable
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>Not applicable
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:movingImageQF>
			<fdd:normalVideo>Good support.</fdd:normalVideo>
			<fdd:clarity>
				<p>Moderate to excellent, considering this is a compression algorithm, varies according to level selected.</p>
				<p>The Microsoft Windows Media web site codecs page is regularly edited and updated (see links listed in <a href="#useful">Useful references</a> below); in 2004, the text included this note: "For content that requires ultra-high video quality. Windows Media Video 9 Professional defines profiles of the Windows Media Video 9 codec that are automatically applied at higher bit rates and resolutions. Its efficiency can bring high-definition quality to computer users, enabling storage and delivery of a complete movie at 720p resolution (1280 x 720 pixels per frame), with 5.1 digital discrete channel surround sound, on a single standard DVD. In the near future, hardware acceleration of decoding will also make playback of both 720p and 1080p content possible even on midrange Pentium 4 class computers."  WMV9_PRO offers variable bit rate encoding that provides "optimal quality with a lower average bit rate and file size."</p>
				<p>In 2005, the as-then-updated codecs page stated the following regarding the Advanced Profile: "This is a new codec that is included with Windows Media Player 10, the Windows Media Format 9.5 SDK, and the updated codec installation packages. Key features of Windows Media Video 9 Advanced Profile include improved interlaced support and transport format independence." See also <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
				<p>Regarding the professional codec, one user reported in 2004 that he produced constant-bitrate test footage at different bitrates, noticed that 20 Mb/s seemed to be the upper limit offered by the software, and said that he was unable to discern incremental improvements as the bitrate rose above 4 Mb/s. (Private communication.)</p>
			</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:beyondVideo>
				<p>The Microsoft Windows Media web site codecs page is regularly edited and updated (see links listed in <a href="#useful">Useful references</a> below); in 2005, the text stated the following regarding the Advanced Profile: "Transport format independence enables the delivery of Windows Media Video 9 Advanced Profile over systems that are not Windows Media-based, such as standards-based broadcast infrastructures (through native MPEG-2 transport streams), wireless infrastructures (through RTP), or even DVDs. This feature incorporates Windows Media Video 9 Advanced Profile as a next-generation compression technology into emerging standards initiatives, such as those in SMPTE, DVB, ATSC and the DVD-Forum."  See also <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
			</fdd:beyondVideo>
		</fdd:movingImageQF>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:fidelity>Presumably, producers can select WMA compression codecs; their fidelity capabilities are assessed at <fddLink id="fdd000092">WMA9</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000093">WMA9_PRO</fddLink>.</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>	See <fddLink id="fdd000092">WMA9</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000093">WMA9_PRO</fddLink>
			</fdd:channels>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>Not applicable.</fdd:sigValueNA>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>Not applicable.</fdd:sigValueNA>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>Not applicable.</fdd:sigValueNA>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>According to the Wikipedia <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VC-1">VC-1 article</a> (consulted May 26, 2010): &#34;WMVA was the original implementation of WMV Advanced Profile prior to the acceptance of the VC-1 draft by SMPTE. The codec was distributed with Windows Media Player 10 and Windows Media Format SDK 9.5 install packages. There are slight bitstream differences between WMVA and WVC1, so consequently WMVA is handled by a different DirectShow decoder than WVC1. Some 3rd party hardware and software decoders only decode WMVA based content. As of 2006, WMVA is considered a deprecated codec because it is not fully VC-1 compliant.&quot;</p>
			<p>WVC1, also known as Windows Media Video 9 Advanced Profile, implements the Advanced Profile of the VC-1 codec standard. It offers support for interlaced content and is transport independent. With the previous version of the Windows Media Video 9 Series codec, users could deliver progressive content at data rates as low as one-third that of the MPEG-2 codec and still get the same quality as MPEG-2. The Windows Media Video 9 Advanced Profile codec also offers this same improvement in encoding efficiency with interlaced contents.&#34;</p>
		</fdd:general>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VC-1</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia VC-1 article</tag>
					<comment>Consulted May 26, 2010</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/howto/articles/vc1techoverview.aspx</link>
					<tag>Microsoft general information about VC-1</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20120420174010/http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/howto/articles/codecadvancedsettings.aspx</link>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>By early 2012, the Microsoft codecs pages cited above did not exist.  As of October 2013, codec information is available at:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20080724044914/http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/forpros/codecs/video.aspx</link>
							<tag>Microsoft codecs page for Windows Media 9 from 2008 via Internet Archive</tag>
							<comment>URL redirects (since March 2012 at least, and in October 2013) to URL below.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff819508.aspx</link>
							<tag>Windows Media Codecs</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/gg153556.aspx#windows_media_video_9</link>
							<tag>About the Windows Media Codecs:
Windows Media Video 9</tag>
							<comment>More specific information about profiles.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff819505.aspx</link>
							<tag>Windows Media Video 9 Encoder</tag>
							<comment>Technical details including codec identification codes.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20120420174010/http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/howto/articles/codecadvancedsettings.aspx</link>
							<tag>Using the Advanced Settings of the Windows Media Video 9 Codec</tag>
							<comment>Microsoft article from August 2007.  Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/howto/articles/codecs.aspx</link>
							<tag>Encoding Audio and Video with Windows Media Codecs</tag>
							<comment>October 2007</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
