<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000299" titleName="NLAPS Data Format (NDF)" shortName="NLAPS" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-group</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>gis</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2011-10-29</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Partial (low priority for LC)</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>National Landsat Archive Production System (NLAPS) Data Format (NDF)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>georeferenced image formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>raster image formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>NLAPS Data Format (NDF) is a format designed and primarily used by the USGS (EROS Data Center) for distribution of radiometrically and geometrically corrected Landsat data (satellite imagery).  NLAPS is one of the processing systems that has been used to generate U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) Landsat corrected Level 1 products from uncorrected Level 0 images.  The newer system, LPGS, does not generate images in the NDF format.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for more on the history of Landsat imagery distribution.</p>
			<p>NDF datasets consist of several files: a header file with the extension .H1 and one or more associated raw data files (often .I1, .I2, etc., for separate spectral bands).
 Files with supporting metadata may also be present using extensions .WO Work order report), HI (History and processing parameters ).  Header and other supporting files are in ASCII.  DEM (Digital Elevation Model) data may also be included, using extensions .HD and .DD.  If more than one resolution is packaged together, the extensions, .H2, .H3, etc. will be used for the headers for each resolution.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>A raster image data format used by the EROS Data Center for distribution of Landsat Level 1 data, generated by the National Landsat Archive Production System (NLAPS)</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase/>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000306</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>BSQ_enc</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Band SeQuential Image Encoding</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>The format as specified allows for the BIL ordering of pixels.  However, it appears that NDF data was always distributed in band sequential form, usually with separate image files for each band.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Publicly specified by U.S. Geological Survey.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>Specifications for NDF have been published in Data Format Control Books for Landsat imagery products.  NDF is described in <a href="http://landsat.usgs.gov/documents/LS-DFCB-20.pdf">Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM), LEVEL 1 (L1), Data Format Control Book (DFCB)</a>, which refers to the <a href="http://landsat.usgs.gov/documents/NLAPS_II.pdf">NLAPS Systematic Format Description Document</a> for more detail and examples.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Over the years, Landsat Level 1 imagery has been generated on demand from Level 0 images through different generations of processing systems of which NLAPS was the primary system from roughly 1995 to 2004.  All orders for Landsat Level 1 imagery placed via EarthExplorer or GloVis (systems for online search and ordering of USGS data) prior to March 31, 2004 were processed by NLAPS and available in NDF format.  All Landsat 4 Thematic Mapper scenes were processed through NLAPS prior to April 15, 2009.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for information about USGS transition from NLAPS to LPGS (Level 1 Product Generation System), which does not generate data in NDF format.</p>
			<p>NLAPS NDF format is supported for import in several GIS, image processing, remote sensing analysis, and spatial modeling applications, including: <a href="http://www.hexagongeospatial.com/products/remote-sensing/erdas-imagine/literature">ERDAS IMAGINE</a> (see <a href="https://p.widencdn.net/0mjxnb">supported data formats</a>), <a href="http://www.exelisvis.com/docs/ENVI_OPEN_DATA_FILE.html#NLAPS">Envi</a>, <a href="http://www.gdal.org/frmt_various.html#NDF">GDAL</a>, <a href="http://www.pcigeomatics.com/pdf/GDBTechnology.pdf">PCI Geomatics</a> and <a href="http://www.clarklabs.org/products/upload/IDRISI-Selva-GIS-Image-Processing-Specifications.pdf">IDRISI</a>.  Several of these systems note limitations which may be limitations inherent in the format or in the software&apos;s ability to handle format variants.  For example, GDAL documentation states, &quot;The NDF driver only supports 8-bit data. The only supported projection is UTM. NDF version 1 (NDF_VERSION=0.00) and NDF version 2 are both supported.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>None</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>TBD.  Supporting files are in ASCII and employ a self-describing keyword=value format.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>TBD.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None beyond limitations of software support.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>Landsat satellites have been taking images of the earth since 1972.  See <a href="http://landsat.usgs.gov/about_mission_history.php">Landsat Missions Timeline</a>.  Over this period, the systems for processing the imagery for distribution and the formats available have changed.  In general, the procedure has been to store Level 0 (uncorrected images) and generate Level 1 images with various types of correction for distribution.  See <a href="http://landsat.usgs.gov/descriptions_for_the_levels_of_processing.php">What are the descriptions of the levels of processing?</a>
			</p>
			<p>The National Landsat Archive Production System was one of the systems used for generation of Level 1 images from the Level 0R (raw, uncorrected) images based on user requests.  Version 1 of the NLAPS Data Format (NDF) was published in 1995 and became the offical distribution format of the USGS EROS (Earth  Resources Observation and Science Center.  Prior to April 15, 2009, all Landsat 4 TM scenes were processed through NLAPS.  Beginning in September 2010, LPGS (Level 1 Product Generation System) became the primary processing system for all Landsat standard data products.  The LPGS system does not generate images in the NDF format, instead using more widely used formats, including GeoTIFF.  As of January 2011, NLAPS was used only for processing a subset of Landsat 4 and Landsat 5 data.</p>
		</fdd:general>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://landsat.usgs.gov/documents/LS-DFCB-20.pdf</link>
					<tag>Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM),
LEVEL 1 (L1),
Data Format Control Book (DFCB)</tag>
					<comment>Version 5.0,  February 2013.  Presents detailed data formats of the files generated by the National Land Archive Production System
(NLAPS).  Primarily relates to Landsat 4 and Landsat 5.  Refers to NLAPS Systematic Format Description Document (below) for more detail on NDF.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://landsat.usgs.gov/documents/NLAPS_II.pdf</link>
					<tag>NLAPS Systematic Format Description Document</tag>
					<comment>From July 2000, but still referred to by the February 2013 Data Format Control Book.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The Landsat Missions website provides documentation on Landsat missions and the data available.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://landsat.usgs.gov/tools_project_documents.php</link>
							<tag>Landsat Project Documentation</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://landsat.usgs.gov/descriptions_for_the_levels_of_processing.php</link>
							<tag>Landsat Missions FAQ: What are the descriptions of the levels of processing?</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://landsat.usgs.gov/products_IP_LPGSvsNLAPS.php</link>
							<tag>LPGS and NLAPS Processing Systems Comparison</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://landsat.usgs.gov/products_data_at_no_charge.php</link>
							<tag>Opening the Landsat Archive/Product Specifications</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2008/3091/pdf/fs2008-3091.pdf</link>
							<tag>Opening the Landsat Archive</tag>
							<comment>Original announcement of free public availability of Landsat imagery.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://landsat.usgs.gov/documents/LSDS-272.pdf</link>
							<tag>Landsat (L7) Enhanced Thematic Mapper Plus (ETM+),
LEVEL 1 (L1),
Data Format Control Book (DFCB)</tag>
							<comment>Version 17, May 2014.   Describes data formats for Landsat 7.  Version 16 (February 2013) was at http://landsat.usgs.gov/documents/LS-DFCB-04.pdf but is no longer online.  Version 14 (January 2009), included the NLAPS Data Format.  Versions 16 and 17 did not.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://earth.esa.int/c/document_library/get_file?folderId=13019&amp;name=DLFE-764.pdf</link>
							<tag>Landsat (L7) Enhanced Thematic Mapper Plus (ETM+),
LEVEL 1 (L1),
Data Format Control Book (DFCB)</tag>
							<comment>Version 14, January 2009.  NDF was included as a data format for Landsat 7 in this version. This link is to a copy at the European Space Agency.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20090813201208/http://edc.usgs.gov/guides/images/landsat_tm/nlapsgeo2.html</link>
							<tag>NLAPS Precision and Terrain Formats Description Document</tag>
							<comment>Referred to by earlier versions of ETM+ Data Format Control Book for Landsat 7 data (see immediately above).  Undated.  Extensive examples.  Examples show dates in 1997.  Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://books.google.com/books?id=wu7zHtd2LO4C&amp;pg=PA212&amp;lpg=PA212</link>
					<tag>Space image processing, Volume 1
</tag>
					<comment>Julio Sánchez, María P. Canton. CRC Press, 1999.  Description of NDF begins on page 212.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
