<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000125" titleName="PDF/A-1, PDF for Long-term Preservation, Use of PDF 1.4" shortName="PDF/A-1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2019-01-03</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>ISO 19005-1. Document management - Electronic document file format for long-term preservation - Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (PDF/A-1)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>Portable Document Format (PDF)</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>PDF/A formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>PDF/A-1 is a constrained form of Adobe PDF version 1.4 intended to be suitable for long-term preservation of page-oriented documents for which PDF is already being used in practice. The ISO standard [ISO 19005-1:2005] was developed by a working group with representatives from government, industry, and academia and active support from Adobe Systems Incorporated.</p>
			<p>The PDF/A standards attempt to maximize:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Device independence</li>
				<li>Self-containment</li>
				<li>Self-documentation</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The constraints include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Audio and video content are forbidden</li>
				<li>Javascript and executable file launches are prohibited</li>
				<li>All fonts must be embedded and also must be legally embeddable for unlimited, universal rendering</li>
				<li>Colorspaces specified in a device-independent manner</li>
				<li>Encryption is disallowed</li>
				<li>Use of standards-based metadata is mandated</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The PDF/A-1 standard defines two levels of conformance:  conformance level A (known as <fddLink id="fdd000251">PDF/A-1a</fddLink>) satisfies all requirements in the specification; level B (known as <fddLink id="fdd000252">PDF/A-1b</fddLink>) is a lower level of conformance, &quot;encompassing the requirements of this part of ISO 19005 regarding the visual appearance of electronic documents, but not their structural or semantic properties.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>A constrained form of Adobe PDF version 1.4 intended to be suitable for long-term preservation of page-oriented documents for which PDF is already being used in practice. The ISO standard [ISO 19005-1:2005] was developed by a working group with representatives from government, industry, and academia and active support from Adobe Systems Incorporated.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>A final-state format for delivery to end users and long-term preservation of the document as disseminated to users.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000030</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Portable Document Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000122</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF_1_4</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF Version 1.4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000318</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF/A, PDF for Long-term Preservation</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000251</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A-1a</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF for Long-term Preservation, Based on PDF 1.4, Level A Conformance</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000252</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A-1b</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF for Long-term Preservation, Based on PDF 1.4, Level B Conformance</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000319</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF/A-2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF for Long-term Preservation, Use of ISO 32000-1 (PDF 1.7)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>LC was represented on the working group for the original PDF/A-1 standard and continues to be active in the development of new versions.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>Open standard, approved in May 2005 and published by ISO in October 2005.  Developed under the the working group ISO/TC 171 SC2, Document Imaging Applications, Application Issues, for which <a href="http://www.aiim.org/">AIIM</a> (The Association for Information and Image Management) acted as secretariat to the US TAG for ISO/TC 171 until 2017.  <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020924005329/http://www.npes.org:80/">NPES</a> (now the Association for Print Technologies), secretariat to US TAG for ISO/TC 130,
was a co-sponsor.</p>
			<p>For maintenance of the PDF/A series of standards, ISO established a Joint Working Group (ISO/TC 171/SC 2/WG 5), which also includes representation from ISO/TC 46 SC1 (Archives/Records Management), ISO/TC 130 (Graphics Technology), and ISO/TC 42 (Photography).  As of mid-2017, this working group operates through the non-profit <a href="http://3dpdfconsortium.org/pdf-a/">3d PDF Consortium</a>, now the secretariat for ISO/TC 171 SC2, which is responsible for maintenance of PDF standards, including PDF/A-1.</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/38920.html">ISO 19005-1:2005.	Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -- Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (PDF/A-1)</a>. The standard cannot be used without <a href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/pdf_reference_archives/PDFReference.pdf">PDF Reference, Third Edition, Version 1.4</a>, which it uses as a normative reference.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Since the standard was published in late 2005, tools for creation, conversion, and validation of PDF/A-1 reached the market steadily.  Adobe's own Acrobat Professional 7.0, released in 2004, allowed saving files in a form compliant with the draft standard.  Acrobat 8 (2006) and later versions support the standard as published.  Microsoft Office 2007 supported creation of PDF/A files through <i>Save as PDF</i>, originally an add-on module.   Open Office introduced support for PDF/A in release 2.4 (in early 2008).  LibreOffice can export documents as PDF/A-1; as of version 6.0.7.3 (current as of early 2019), this is the only version of PDF/A that can be generated.</p>
			<p>Many commercial companies with products aimed at large enterprises, have produced products supporting the creation, migration, and validation of PDF/A files.  Pioneers included Apago, Inc., Visioneer (for scanning paper to <fddLink id="fdd000252">PDF/A-1b</fddLink>), Callas Software, Compart Systemhaus, Luratech, Nuance, and PDF Tools AG.  Many of these companies are based in Europe, where the growing requirements from the EU for use of digital formats that are formal (preferably ISO) standards has produced more market pressure than in the U.S.  Starting with version 0.93 (released in January 2007), the widely used open source <a href="https://xmlgraphics.apache.org/fop/1.1/pdfa.html">Apache FOP</a> (Formatting Object Processor, based on the W3C's XSL-FO standard) introduced support for the minimal PDF/A profile, PDF/A-1b.  Apache FOP 1.1 (released in October 2012) added some support for PDF/A-1a as part of improved support for accessibility.  A large number of supporting products can be found at <a href="http://www.pdfa.org/products/">http://www.pdfa.org/products/</a> from the PDF Association.</p>
			<p>The standards development process involved active participation on behalf of communities whose endorsement or adoption would create significant momentum for wider adoption in the sense of requirement or preference for PDF/A over generic PDF for archival deposit or submission. Important groups are government agencies and legislative and judicial institutions.  <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110903123033/http://www.aiimhost.com/DLM/DLMHelsinki_MarcStraat.pdf">Adobe reported</a> migration of legacy "report silos" at several (un-named) financial institutions at a meeting of the European DLM (Document Lifecycle Management) Forum in Helsinki in November 2006.  An increasing number of libraries and other archival institutions are recommending or requiring PDF/A.  For pragmatic reasons, when PDF/A is mandated, PDF/A-1b is usually acceptable.  Full PDF/A-1a compliance, with tagged document structure, is hard to achieve except in a workflow that anticipates that objective from initial document creation.  Libraries and archives recommending or mandating PDF/A for textual documents deposited in a digital repository soon after the standard was published included: <a href="http://etd.vt.edu/howto/accept.html">Virginia Tech for electronic theses</a>; the <a href="https://www.arkivverket.no/sok/_/attachment/inline/eb3f91e6-10cf-4eb6-a855-90baadcad7bc:99d66752ac201be40573cd8a5e90134f7fc178a1/Rundskriv%20om%20PDF-A%20av%2022.1.2009.pdf">National Archives of Norway</a>; and the <a href="https://repositories.lib.utexas.edu/pages/policies_recommended_formats">University of Texas Libraries</a>.  The United States Patent and Trademarks Office (USPTO) has <a href="https://www.uspto.gov/patents-application-process/applying-online/efs-web-pdf-guidelines">requirements for PDFs</a> that it accepts for electronic filing; the requirements are based on the PDF/A specification.  Documents conforming to PDF/A-1 meet the USPTO requirements.  In February 2014, PDF/A-1 was declared a preferred format for textual documents, scanned text, presentations, and posters for <a href="https://www.archives.gov/records-mgmt/policy/transfer-guidance-tables.html">transfer of permanent electronic records to the U.S. National Archives</a>.  For scanned text, additional image quality guidance is given.</p>
			<p>According to an <a href="https://www.pacer.gov/announcements/general/pdfa.html">announcement</a> available on the PACER (Public Access to Court Electronic Records -- for U.S. Federal Courts) web site in February 2011, "The Judiciary is planning to change the technical standard for filing documents in the Case Management and Electronic Case Filing (CM/ECF) system from PDF to PDF/A."</p>
			<p>A list of entities recommending or requiring use of PDF/A was found at <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20130502134821/http://www.adobe.com/enterprise/standards/pdfa/">http://www.adobe.com/enterprise/standards/pdfa/</a> from Adobe between 2010 and early 2013 (link now via Internet Archive).  Another list of entities recommending or requiring use of PDF/A by 2011 was found at <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160907102523/http://www.pdfa.org/2011/06/recommendations-for-pdfa/">http://www.pdfa.org/2011/06/recommendations-for-pdfa/</a> (link now via Internet Archive) from the PDF Association, an alliance of vendors.</p>
			<p>Funded under the EU&apos;s PREFORMA program as a project from 2015 to 2017, <a href="http://verapdf.org/home/">veraPDF</a> was developed as a software tool and open-source library to support validation of PDF/A files against all the parts and profiles in ISO 19005.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>Adobe has a number of patents covering technology that is disclosed in the Portable Document Format (PDF) Specification, version 1.3 and later, and hence in the ISO 19005-1 specification by reference.  As an ISO standard, the compliance of ISO 19005-1 with the <a href="http://isotc.iso.org/livelink/livelink/fetch/2000/2122/3770791/Common_Policy.htm">ISO/IEC/ITU common patent policy</a> has been vetted.</p>
			<p>A summary of relevant information on the Adobe Web site in December 2010 at <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20101220080159/http://partners.adobe.com:80/public/developer/support/topic_legal_notices.html">http://partners.adobe.com/public/developer/support/topic_legal_notices.html</a> (link now via Internet Archive) follows.  Note that all the patents listed on this Adobe page have probably expired as of 2019-01-01.</p>
			<p>To promote the use of PDF for information interchange the following patents are licensed by Adobe on a royalty-free, non-exclusive basis for the term of each patent for developing software that produces, consumes, and interprets PDF files : 5,634,064 (filed 1996-08-02, granted 1997-05-27, probably expired as of 2019-01-01); 5,737,599 (filed 1995-12-07, granted 1998-04-07, probably expired as of 2019-01-01); 5,781,785 (filed 1995-09-26, granted 1998-07-14, probably expired as of 2019-01-01); 5,819,301 (filed 1997-09-09, granted 1998-10-06, probably expired as of 2019-01-01); 6,028,583 (filed 1998-01-16, granted 2002-02-22, probably expired as of 2019-01-01); 6,289,364 (filed 1997-12-22, granted 2001-09-11, probably expired as of 2019-01-01); 6,421,460 (filed 1999-05-06, granted 2002-07-16, probably expired as of 2019-01-01).  Patent 5,860,074 (filed 1997-08-14, granted 1999-01-12, probably expired as of 2019-01-01) is similarly licensed on a royalty-free, non-exclusive basis for its term but only for the purpose of developing software that produces PDF files (thus specifically excluding software that consumes and/or interprets PDF files).</p>
			<p>In association with the adoption of PDF, version 1.7 as an ISO standard (ISO 32000-1:2008), Adobe issued a <a href="https://www.adobe.com/pdf/pdfs/ISO32000-1PublicPatentLicense.pdf">Public Patent License</a>, granting "every individual and organization in the world the royalty-free right, under all Essential
Claims that Adobe owns, to make, have made, use, sell, import and distribute Compliant
Implementations." </p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon compliant software tools to read. Building tools requires sophistication. PDF/A does not permit encryption.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Support for embedding any form of metadata for a document is extremely good.  Use of XMP is mandatory for basic descriptive and identifying metadata.  Other XMP metadata packages can be embedded.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>PDF/A is constrained to avoid external dependencies.  All necessary fonts must be embedded.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>PDF/A does not permit encryption.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>Good support is possible, particularly for files complying with the <fddLink id="fdd000251">PDF/A-1a</fddLink> profile but not guaranteed.  The PDF/A-1 format does not preclude creating documents from scanned page images using the <fddLink id="fdd000252">PDF/A-1b</fddLink> conformance profile; such files do not necessarily support indexing of the document text or extraction of text for quotation.  See <a href="https://www.pdfa.org/pdfa-faq/">PDF/A FAQ</a> from the PDF Association.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>The logical structure of a document is only represented in a PDF/A file if the creator or process during creation takes steps to incorporate structural tagging.  The PDF/A standard recommends the representation of structural hierarchy.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>PDF is designed to represent the layout of page-oriented documents.</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>Can be represented by embedded graphics.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>Annotations may be embedded.  Bookmarks may be provided.</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>pdf</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The standard does not indicate that a different extension should be used to distinguish PDF from PDF/A.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/pdf</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Media type <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8118">registered with IANA</a>. See also  <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF Family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>According to the PDF/A-1 specification, &quot;Neither the version number in the header of a PDF file nor the value of the Version key in the document catalog dictionary shall be used in determining whether a file is
in accordance with this part of ISO 19005.&quot;  Hence, although the magic number in the header will usually be &quot;%PDF-1.4&quot; (see <fddLink id="fdd000122">PDF_1_4</fddLink>), it should not be relied on.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Indicator for profile, level, version, etc.</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>The standard specifies that the PDF/A version and conformance level of a file shall be specified using the PDF/A Identification extension schema defined in the standard.  This schema has two mandatory elements: pdfaid:part (integer) and pdfaid:conformance (closed list of text values).  A PDF/A-1 file should have the integer value 1 for pdfaid:part.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>There is no PRONOM entry specifically for PDF/A-1.  See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/95">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/95</a> for profile  <fddLink id="fdd000251">PDF/A-1a</fddLink> and <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/354">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/354</a> for <fddLink id="fdd000252">PDF/A-1b</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>There is no Wikidata Title ID specifically for PDF/A-1.  See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1547957">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1547957</a> for all versions and profiles of PDF/A.   See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26541013">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26541013</a> for profile <fddLink id="fdd000251">PDF/A-1a</fddLink> and <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26543628">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26543628</a> for <fddLink id="fdd000252">PDF/A-1b</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>PDF/A was developed to address the issue that large bodies of official documents and important information are maintained in PDF, but that PDF is not suitable as an archival format. The Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts was a driving force in forming a U.S. Committee to initiate an ISO standard based on PDF. The activity was started in October 2002 under the joint auspices of AIIM (Association for Information and Image Management) and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020924005329/http://www.npes.org:80/">NPES</a> (National Printing Equipment Suppliers, aka the Association for Suppliers of
Printing and Publishing Technologies, and recently renamed the <a href="https://www.printtechnologies.org/about-us/about-us/">Association for Print Technologies</a>).  NPES had sponsored the development of the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20021004161035/http://www.npes.org:80/news/whatsnew.html#standard">PDF/X standard</a> for prepress graphics exchange, published by ISO in March 2002 as <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/34607.html">ISO 15929:2002</a> and continued to be engaged in the development and maintenance of <fddLink id="fdd000124">PDF/X</fddLink> standards in the many parts of ISO 15930.</p>
			<p>A <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20021211100512/http://198.77.178.130:80/standards/form.cfm">call for participation in the joint AIIM/NPES project</a> was published online in late 2002.  Useful details of the standardization process, including a timeline, are in a <a href="https://slideplayer.com/slide/2320111/">presentation</a> from a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20061001211021/http://www.archivists.org/conference/neworleans2005/no2005prog-Session.asp?event=1433">session</a> at the annual meeting of the Society of American Archivists in July 2005, when ISO 19005-1 had been approved but not yet published.  ISO 19005-1 was published in October 2005.</p>
			<p>Part 2 of ISO 19005, PDF/A-2 (<a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/50655.html">ISO 19005-2:2011</a>) extended the capabilities of PDF/A-1.   <fddLink id="fdd000319">PDF/A-2</fddLink> is based on PDF version 1.7 (as defined in ISO 32000-1) rather than PDF version 1.4. </p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>ISO 19005-1 was originally published in 2005.  Two sets of corrections and clarifications have been issued.  Although the main standard must be purchased, the entire contents of the corrections documents can be viewed online using the Preview function.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/38920.html</link>
							<tag>ISO 19005-1:2005.  Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -- Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (PDF/A-1)</tag>
							<comment>Reviewed and confirmed in 2015</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/45613.html</link>
							<tag>ISO 19005-1:2005/Cor 1:2007</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/60603.html</link>
							<tag>ISO 19005-1:2005/Cor 2:2011</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:bookReference>
					<bookRefDetail rel="aucorp">Adobe Systems Incorporated</bookRefDetail>.  <bookRefDetail rel="btitle">PDF Reference, Third Edition, Version 1.4.</bookRefDetail>  Addison-Wesley, <bookRefDetail rel="date">2001</bookRefDetail>. ISBN: <bookRefDetail rel="isbn">0-201-75839-3</bookRefDetail>.  Also available online as <a href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/pdf_reference_archives/PDFReference.pdf">http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/pdf_reference_archives/PDFReference.pdf</a>.</fdd:bookReference>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://3dpdfconsortium.org/pdf-a/</link>
					<tag>PDF/A page from 3d PDF Consortium (Secretariat for PDF standards since July 2017)</tag>
					<comment>In January 2019, this site has little public information.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDF/A</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for PDF/A</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.adobe.com/devnet/pdf/pdf_reference_archive.html</link>
					<tag>PDF Reference Archives</tag>
					<comment>Documentation for Adobe versions of PDF prior to the current version, including PDF 1.4.  Includes access to errata and supplements.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The veraPDF tool for validating PDF/A files was released in 2017.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://verapdf.org/home/</link>
							<tag>Home page for veraPDF project</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://docs.verapdf.org/</link>
							<tag>Documentation for veraPDF</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://github.com/verapdf</link>
							<tag>Github repository for veraPDF</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://verapdf.org/roadmap/</link>
							<tag>Roadmap and timeline for veraPDF project</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.pdfa.org/pdfa-faq/</link>
					<tag>PDF/A FAQ from the PDF Association</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>While AIIM was the secretariat responsible for development and maintenance of the PDF/A sequence of standards, it maintained a number of useful and publicly accessible resources.  The links below are to pages harvested by the Internet Archive:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160104190300/http://www.aiim.org:80/Research-and-Publications/Standards/PDF_Standards</link>
							<tag>AIIM | PDF Standards</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20040725085745/http://www.aiim.org:80/pdf_a/</link>
							<tag>PDF-Archive Committee site (as of July 2004)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060715162341/http://www.aiim.org:80/standards.asp?id=25013</link>
							<tag>PDF-Archive Committee site (as of July 2006)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080527161837/http://www.aiim.org:80/standards.asp?ID=25013</link>
							<tag>PDF-Archive Committee site (as of May 2008)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20121111005904/http://www.aiim.org/Research-and-Publications/Standards/Committees/PDFA</link>
							<tag>PDF/A Committee website (as of November 2012)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20180318231830/https://pdf.editme.com/PDFA</link>
							<tag>PDF/A WG Committee website (as of March 2018)</tag>
							<comment>Supported by AIIM.  Mainly used for collaborative work by authorized users. Some public information on PDF/A.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20140210204309/http://www.aiim.org:80/documents/standards/19005-1_FAQ.pdf</link>
							<tag>ISO 19005-1 (PDF/A-1) Frequently Asked Questions</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20110903123033/http://www.aiimhost.com/DLM/DLMHelsinki_MarcStraat.pdf</link>
							<tag>Preserving documents into the future: PDF/A Update</tag>
							<comment>Presentation at the European Document Lifecycle Management (DLM) Forum in November 2006, by Marc Straat, Head of Standards Development Europe, Adobe Systems Europe Limited (www.aiimhost.com/DLM/DLMHelsinki_MarcStraat.pdf)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20151219180108/http://www.aiim.org:80/Research-and-Publications/Standards/Articles/PDFA-Compliant-Products</link>
							<tag>List of compliant applications compiled by AIIM. From 2014 or earlier.</tag>
							<comment>Compliance was asserted by vendors, not independently tested.  Link now via Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>NPES also provided access to information about PDF/A.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20150702094210/http://www.npes.org/programs/standardsworkroom/toolsbestpractices/pdfa.aspx</link>
							<tag>NPES Standards Workroom | Tools and Best Practices: PDF/A</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20061004054326/http://www.npes.org/standards/Tools/19005-1_FAQ.pdf</link>
							<tag>ISO 19005-1 (PDF/A-1) Frequently Asked Questions (July 2006)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.archives.gov/records-mgmt/policy/transfer-guidance-tables.html</link>
					<tag>NARA 2014-04: Appendix A, Revised Format Guidance for the Transfer of Permanent Electronic Records – Tables of File Formats </tag>
					<comment>Since February 2014, PDF/A-1 has been a preferred format for textual documents, scanned text, presentations, and posters.  For scanned text, additional image quality guidance is given.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.uspto.gov/patents-application-process/applying-online/efs-web-pdf-guidelines</link>
					<tag>US Patent and Trademark Office | EFS-Web PDF Guidelines </tag>
					<comment>For electronic filing of patent applications.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Other useful references no longer available online.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20150428052200/http://fclaweb.fcla.edu/content/pdfa-1</link>
							<tag>Florida Digital Archive file format details: PDF/A-1 (now via IA)</tag>
							<comment>From Florida Center for Library Automation.  Included Guidelines for Creating Archival Quality PDF Files</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20141021150037/http://www.pdfa.org/competence-centers/pdfa-competence-center/</link>
							<tag>PDF/A Competence Center (within PDF Association) as of October 2014</tag>
							<comment>The PDF Association is an alliance of vendors of products and services.  The PDF/A Competence Center supports the creation and use of PDF/A documents.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20120210140000/http://www.pdfa.org/2011/06/recommendations-for-pdfa/</link>
							<tag>Recommendations for PDF/A:  June 2011 survey from PDF Association</tag>
							<comment>From PDF Association.  Link via Internet Archive</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20130502134821/http://www.adobe.com/enterprise/standards/pdfa/</link>
							<tag>Governments adopting PDF/A and PDF for official use (list from 2013)</tag>
							<comment>Starting in 2010, Adobe listed governments adopting PDF/A or PDF as recommended, mandatory or acceptable. Link to early 2013 version from Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources from the PDF Association:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.pdfa.org/products/</link>
							<tag>Products that support PDF/A, PDF/X, etc.</tag>
							<comment>From PDF Association.  Has filters by standard, etc.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.pdfa.org/member/</link>
							<tag>PDF Association members | Many offer PDF/A-compliant products</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc8118.txt</link>
					<tag>The application/pdf Media Type</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/95</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/95</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM on PDF/A-1a.  PUID: fmt/95.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/354</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/354</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM on PDF/A-1b.  PUID: fmt/354.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26541013</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q26541013</tag>
					<comment>Information in WikiData about PDF/A-1a. WikiData Title ID: Q26541013</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26543628</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q26543628</tag>
					<comment>Information in WikiData about PDF/A-1b. WikiData Title ID: Q26543628</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See also <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A</fddLink>.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
