<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000513" titleName="Open XML Paper Specification, (OpenXPS), ECMA-388 (.oxps)" shortName="OpenXPS" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
			</fdd:gdfrGenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-02-10</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Open XML Paper Specification, (OpenXPS), ECMA-388 (June 2009)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS) is an open specification for a fixed, page-oriented, platform-independent document format and page description language.  OpenXPS was approved by Ecma International as international standard ECMA-388 in June 2009.  OpenXPS, using the .oxps extension, was based on Microsoft&apos;s proprietary XML Paper Specification (<fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>), which uses the .xps extension. However, Ecma International&apos;s Technical Committee 46 (TC46) introduced substantive changes.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for a list of the most important changes. Windows Vista and Windows 7 used XPS for printing to a file with the <i>Microsoft XPS Document Writer</i>, while Windows 8 and subsequent versions of Windows have used OpenXPS as the default format for that purpose.  Open XPS has also been the basis for the Windows &quot;XPS print path&quot; since the release of Windows 8 in 2012.  See <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/desktop/wpf/advanced/printing-overview?view=netframeworkdesktop-4.8#xps-print-path">Windows Presentation Foundation: Printing Overview</a> and <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/printdocs/documents">XPS Documents</a>, aimed at developers of applications for Windows.</p>
			<p>The OpenXPS specification was designed to support the tasks of distributing,
archiving, rendering, and processing documents.  The diagram on page 3 of <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/wp-content/uploads/TC46-XPS-White-Paper.pdf">Ecma OpenXPS White Paper (April 2009)</a> from Ecma TC46 emphasizes that OpenXPS was not intended to support writing and editing.  Among the high-level goals for the Open XPS specification listed in the white paper were that it should provide:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>A Page Description Language for communicating document content to and from document peripherals such as printers and scanners.</li>
				<li>A spool file format for processing and temporary caching within an operating system when interoperating with document peripherals such as scanners and printers.</li>
				<li>An electronic paper format for publication, sharing, storage and long term archiving of document content in a form that provides a facsimile of the physical paper representation.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>According to the same OpenXPS white paper from TC46, the primary features that differentiated OpenXPS from other document formats (in 2009) were:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Fixed layout representation of page content</li>
				<li>All resources must be included in the package</li>
				<li>XML-based mark-up used to define page content, file structure, and metadata</li>
				<li>Feature set limited to only that required for efficient electronic paper</li>
				<li>Minimal implementation requirements</li>
				<li>Minimal threat footprint for malicious code</li>
				<li>Supports fine-grained streaming and random access</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The design objectives and the technical implementation of OpenXPS correspond closely to these of the proprietary predecessor from Microsoft. This format description will focus on the small but substantive differences.  See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink> for details on the structure and supported functionality of the OpenXPS variant.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Substantive differences between Microsoft&apos;s XPS format and OpenXPS:</b>  The differences listed below are in addition to many editorial changes, including re-organization to follow Ecma editorial practices and to allow removal of proprietary references, emphasizing that OpenXPS was designed for implementation independent of platform.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>Recommendations for identifying OpenXPS:</b> To avoid confusion with the conventions used with XPS, OpenXPS recommends the use of .oxps as a filename extension and  application/oxps as the content type.

[Note: .xps and application/vnd.ms-xpsdocument have been used to identify XPS documents.]</li>
				<li>
					<b>Namespace URI changes:</b> the namespace URIs for the FixedPage markup and other parts of the specification were changed.  In particular, <i>http://schemas.openxps.org/oxps/v1.0</i> is the namespace URI for markup for the primary FixedDocumentSequence, FixedDocument, and
FixedPage parts.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Removal of references to Windows-specific features and schemas:</b> The Microsoft Print Schema was dropped as a normative reference and as the only format for PrintTicket parts to convey user intent and device configuration settings to print systems.  The requirement to support the Windows Color System (WCS) profile embedded as a private tag was removed.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Improved color profile interoperability:</b> OpenXPS producers and consumers are required to support color management
using International Color Consortium (ICC) profiles conforming to the requirements of the ICC Color Profile
specification, <a href="https://www.color.org/ICC_Minor_Revision_for_Web.pdf">ICC.1:2001-04</a>. Optionally, ICC profiles complying to <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/40317.html">ISO 15076-1:2005</a> (equivalent to the later ICC specification, <a href="https://color.org/ICC1v42_2006-05.pdf">ICC.1:2004-10</a>) can also be included.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Support for embedding raster images in JPEG XR format:</b> Rather than permitting raster images in the Windows Media Photo (<fddLink id="fdd000243">WMP</fddLink>) format to be embedded, OpenXPS supports embedding of <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/project/jpeg-xr/">JPEG XR</a>, the successor of WMP adopted as a standard by ITU (International Telecommunication Union) in March 2009 and by ISO/IEC in August 2009.  Through 2016, several new editions were published with minor corrections and changes that would not have affected the use of JPEG XR in OpenXPS.  The 4th edition (from 2019) of the JPEG XR specification adds support for additional color encodings.  The compilers of this resource assume that the new color encodings are not supported in OpenXPS files or implementations.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Support for new version of font format specification:</b>  The version of font format used by the OpenXPS format is <a href="https://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c043466_ISO_IEC_14496-22_2007(E).zip">ISO/IEC 14496-22:2007. Information technology — Coding of
audio-visual objects —
Part 22:
Open Font Format</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Support for embedding 3D models in X3D format:</b> OpenXPS added support for the <fddLink id="fdd000490">X3D</fddLink> standard to represent 3D content within the document. This support is implemented using the Markup Compatibility and Extensibility Specification standardized as Part 5 of ECMA-376 (OOXML) to ensure that there were no additional implementation requirements on existing applications that had already implemented support for XPS.  <p>The OpenXPS specification states that it allows incorporation of a 3D model in the X3D format, compliant with  <i>Interoperability</i> conformance level as specified in ISO/IEC 19775-1:2008 (Architecture and base components), ISO/IEC
19776-1:2005 (XML encoding), or ISO/IEC 19776-3:2007 (Compressed binary encoding).  [Note: ISO/IEC 19775-1:2013 does not mention an &quot;interoperability&quot; conformance level, but does specify an &quot;Interchange Profile.&quot;  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
					<p>OpenXPS files that include 3D content must include a &apos;fallback&quot; 2D alternative.  The compilers of this resource have not located any examples of OpenXPS files that include 3D content. Nor have they explored whether particular viewers support display of 3D content. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
					<p>Autodesk, developer of AutoCAD and other design products that incorporate 3D modeling functions, was represented in the TC46 working group that developed the OpenXPS specification.  However, it is not apparent that Autodesk has used OpenXPS.  One of the AutoCAD export formats is DWFx, which is described as based on the XML Paper Specification but not openly documented by Autodesk.  All the DWFx files examined by the compilers of this resource used the XML namespaces associated with Microsoft&apos;s XPS format rather than those for OpenXPS.  Some of these included resources that appeared to be in a <a href="https://www.okino.com/conv/exp_hsf.htm">3D stream format</a> that originated with HOOPS and is also found in DWF files; within the first few characters of the 3D part in the were &quot;HSF V12.15&quot; and &quot;W3D&quot;.  The compilers of this resource have found no evidence of use of OpenXPS with embedded 3D resources.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>An open, platform-independent specification for a fixed, page-oriented document format and page description language. OpenXPS, using the .oxps extension, was approved in June 2009 as an international standard by Ecma International (ECMA-388). Starting with Windows 8 (released in 2012), the Windows operating system used OpenXPS in place of the predecessor proprietary XPS format when printing to the Microsoft XPS Document Writer.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>The OpenXPS format was designed as a final-state format, for printing and distribution to end users for viewing.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>OpenXPS is a subtype of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200721010354/http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%202%20(PDF).zip">ECMA-376, Edition 1: Part 2, Open
Packaging Conventions</a> (December 2006), which is a predecessor to OPC/OOXML as described on this website.  Edition 1 of <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376</a> has not been described separately on this website.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for information on the version of OPC that is the basis for both OpenXPS and its predecessor XPS. The differences between that version and <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink> are minor. </fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000355</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ZIP_6_2_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>ZIP File Format, Version 6.2.0 (PKWARE)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Various features of the ZIP File Format are not permitted in OPC.  Details on the use of ZIP in OPC are in section 9 and Annex C of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200917204317/https://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/ECMA-376,%20Fourth%20Edition,%20Part%202%20-%20Open%20Packaging%20Conventions.zip">ECMA-376, Edition 1: Part 2, Open Packaging Conventions</a>. Available via Internet Archive.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000396</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MCE/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (Office Open XML)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Formally, an OpenXPS document may employ markup from the Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (MCE) schema defined in ECMA-376 1st edition Part 5 (December 2006). Edition 1 of <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376</a> has not been described separately on this website. Between 2006 and 2015, there was no change in the MCE format significant to the OpenXPS or XPS formats.  All editions of ECMA-376 and ISO/IEC 29500-3 through 2015 use the same namespace for MCE: <i>http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/markup-compatibility/2006</i>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000514</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MS-XPS</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Microsoft XML Paper Specification, (XPS)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress is not aware of any documents in this format in its digital collections.  In particular, no files with the .oxps extension have been acquired through web crawling.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See the Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement for format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/text.html">textual works</a> and <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/stillimg.html">still image works</a>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>International standard, developed under the auspices of Technical Committee 46 (<a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/technical-committees/tc46/?tab=general">TC46</a>) of <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/">Ecma International</a>.  Ecma publications, including standards, are made available online for free download.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications-and-standards/standards/ecma-388/">ECMA-388:
Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS), June 2009</a>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Starting with Windows 8, the Microsoft XPS Document Writer available as a virtual printer has, by default, created an OpenXPS file, with extension .oxps.</p>
			<p>As for the predecessor XPS format from Microsoft, there was little adoption other than in Windows.  See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>A number of tools have been developed for viewing and converting XPS documents.  See <a href="#useful">Useful References below</a>.</p>
			<p>Support for OpenXPS and XPS was dropped in 2018 in some applications or operating systems where they were supported previously.  <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/deployment/planning/windows-10-removed-features">Features and functionality removed in Windows 10</a> indicates that starting with the April 2018 release, the XPS Viewer utility would require special action for installation in Windows.  Adobe&apos;s Acrobat Pro (for Windows) used to import XPS files, but has withdrawn default support.  <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/acrobat/kb/unable-convert-xps-to-pdfs.html">Unable to convert XPS files to PDFs</a> states, &quot;With December 2018 release of Acrobat, converting XPS files to PDFs is disabled.&quot;  Support can be re-enabled using the Windows Registry Editor.</p>
			<p>As of early 2020, the virtual printer, Microsoft XPS Document Writer, continues to be available in Windows and to generate files in the OpenXPS format.  Also, OpenXPS continues to be the basis for the newer of two primary Windows print paths.  See <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/drivers/print/windows-print-path-overview">Windows Print Path Overview</a>.  Also, see <a href="https://mspoweruser.com/google-chrome-uses-xps-print-api/">Printing experience in Google Chrome is expected to improve as Google embraces Microsoft’s XPS Print API for printing on Windows 10</a> for a November 2019 article indicating that Google Chrome was moving to use the newer print path based on OpenXPS.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>No concerns.  The Ecma International <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/policies/by-ipr/code-of-conduct-in-patent-matters/">patent policy</a> at the time OpenXPS was standardized was summarized as &quot;The General Assembly of Ecma shall not approve recommendations of Standards which are covered by patents when such patents will not be licensed by their owners on a reasonable and non-discriminatory basis.&quot;  Implementation of the OpenXPS specification is royalty-free because Microsoft&apos;s intent in submitting its XPS technology for standardization was to encourage wide use and interoperability.</p>
			<p>Prior to submitting the XPS specification to Ecma International for standardization, Microsoft offered a royalty-free <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060627035414/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpscopyright.mspx">copyright license</a> to copy and distribute the specification and a royalty-free <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20070314061209/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpspatentlic.mspx">patent license</a> to implement and use XPS technology. See <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20061106063225/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpslicense.mspx">XML Paper Specification Licensing Overview (from 2006)</a> and <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/windows/hardware/design/dn641614(v=vs.85)#licensing">XML Paper Specification Licensing Overview (as online in early 2020)</a>.</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Document-level descriptive metadata is optional. An OpenXPS document may contain the <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC </fddLink> part with the name Core Properties. This part has fifteen elements, all optional and all non-repeatable. Six are selected from the main Dublin Core Metadata Initiative (DCMI) set (title; creator; description; subject; identifier; language) and two from the supplementary dcterms vocabulary (created; modified).  Compilers of this resource have used Word 2016 for Windows to print to Microsoft XPS Document Writer.  This created an OpenXPS file without a Core Properties part.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>. Note that OpenXPS allows embedding of raster images in the JPEG XR format rather than the Windows Media Photo format as supported in MS-XPS.  JPEG XR (not separately described on this website) was formerly known as HD Photo and Windows Media Photo (see <fddLink id="fdd000243">WMP</fddLink>).</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>OpenXPS producers and consumers must support a variety of color data formats for vector graphics and for raster images. These include grayscale, sRGB (IEC 61966:1999),
scRGB (IEC 61966:2003), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CMYK_color_model">CMYK</a>, N-channel color data (for independent control of inks), and named colors.  OpenXPS Documents may include associated ICC profiles in separate parts or embedded in any image format (according to the restrictions of the image
file format) with any color space.  For color spaces other than sRGB and scRGB, OpenXPS producers must provide color management
using ICC profiles conforming to the requirements of the ICC Color Profile
specification, <a href="https://www.color.org/ICC_Minor_Revision_for_Web.pdf">ICC.1:2001-04</a>.  This is to be interoperable with earlier implementations of Microsoft&apos;s XPS format.  Optionally, ICC Profiles complying to ISO 15076-1:2005 (equivalent to the later ICC specification, <a href="https://color.org/ICC1v42_2006-05.pdf">ICC.1:2004-10</a>) can also be included.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:beyondImage>
				<p>The OpenXPS specification allows incorporation of a 3D model in the X3D format, requiring a &apos;fallback&quot; 2D alternative for printing. See <a href="#identification">Description</a> above.</p>
			</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>
				<p>The OpenXPS format (like its predecessor XPS format published by Microsoft) is not designed to support wordprocessing or document design.  See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</p>
			</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>
				<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>. </p>
				<p>In place of Microsoft&apos;s own specification of the OpenType Font Format from 2004, the OpenXPS specification (ECMA-388) incorporates the successor format adopted as an international standard, published as <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/43466.html">ISO/IEC 14496-22: 2007: Information technology — Coding of audio-visual objects — Part 22: Open Font Format</a>.  ECMA-388 states, &quot;The Open Font Format is considered to be equivalent to the OpenType font format.&quot;  The 2007 version of the Open Font Format is <a href="https://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c043466_ISO_IEC_14496-22_2007(E).zip">downloadable</a> from the ISO/IEC Information Technology Task Force (ITTF).</p>
			</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>oxps</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>In specification. See also <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/oxps">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/oxps</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>In specification. See also <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/oxps">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 50 4B 03 04</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: P K etx eot</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>This 4-byte magic number applies to all formats based on the <fddLink id="fdd000354">ZIP-PK</fddLink> format. The OpenXPS specification indicates &quot;First four bytes correspond to the local file header signature defined in the .ZIP File
Format Specification from PKWARE, Inc., version 6.2.0 (2004).&quot;  See also <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/oxps">IANA registration for OpenXPS</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>XML namespace declaration</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>http://schemas.openxps.org/oxps/v1.0</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>This namespace declaration occurs in the mandatory FixedDocumentSequence part that serves as the root of the content in an OpenXPS file (package). In ECMA-388, the extension <i>fdseq</i> is recommended but not mandated for this part.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Type=&quot;http://schemas.openxps.org/oxps/v1.0/fixedrepresentation&quot;</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>This type declaration will occur in the top-level Relationships part (<i>\_rels\.rels</i>) in the OPC package representing an OpenXPS document, as an attribute of a &lt;Relationship&gt; element within the &lt;Relationships&gt; element.  In an OpenXPS document that follows the naming scheme recommended in ECMA-388, the target of this relationship will have the extension <i>fdseq</i>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/657</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/657">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/657</a>.  Note that, as of March 2020, this PRONOM entry for Open XML Paper Specification gives the MIME type as application/oxps but .xps for the file extension.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q977900</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q977900">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q977900</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>Version of OPC on which OpenXPS is based:</b> See <fddLink id="fdd000514">MS-XPS</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Formats allowed for embedded resources:</b>  The raster image formats that can be embedded in an OpenXPS document were selected for their wide support: JPEG in <fddLink id="fdd000018">JFIF</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000147">EXIF</fddLink> containers; <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink>; <fddLink id="fdd000022">TIFF</fddLink> (compressed and uncompressed); and JPEG XR (formerly known as HD Photo and Windows Media Photo, see <fddLink id="fdd000243">WMP</fddLink>).</p>
			<p>Fonts are stored in font parts. OpenXPS permits the use of font formats as defined in <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/43466.html">ISO/IEC 14496-22:2007</a> (Information technology — Coding of audio-visual objects — Part 22: Open Font Format), including TrueType and CFF fonts. To support portability,
the use of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode_font">Unicode fonts</a> is recommended in the specification.  Fonts
may be subsetted based on usage in the document. Although a subsetted font does not contain all
the glyphs in the original font, it must be a valid Open Font Format file according to ISO/IEC 14496-22:2007.  Fonts that may not be legally embedded may be obfuscated as a means of preventing casual misappropriation of embedded
fonts. The specification specifies a method for obfuscation and recommends that the extension of an obfuscated Font
part name be “.odttf” for TrueType fonts and “.odttc” for
TrueType collections.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>The OpenXPS format was based on Microsoft&apos;s proprietary XML Paper Specification (XPS).  XPS was introduced with Windows Vista in 2005.  In September 2007, Microsoft submitted a version of the XPS specification to Ecma International as an initial draft for a neutral international standard. This version and several intermediate drafts are available at <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/technical-committees/tc46/?tab=activities">TC46 - Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS): Documents</a>.  The OpenXPS standard, <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications-and-standards/standards/ecma-388/">ECMA-388</a>, was officially adopted by the Ecma General Assembly in June 2009.</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.ecma-international.org/publications-and-standards/standards/ecma-388/</link>
					<tag>ECMA-388:
Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS), June 2009</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>OpenXPS is based on the Open Packaging Conventions (OPC) and Markup
Compatibility and Extensibility (MCE) parts of the OOXML standard, which were published in December 2006 as parts of <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications-and-standards/standards/ecma-376/">ECMA-376</a> and in 2008, with minor changes, as parts of ISO/IEC 29500.  Formally, OpenXPS is based on the first ECMA editions of OPC and MCE.  The descriptions of <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000396">MCE</fddLink> on this website are based on the 2012 editions of ISO/IEC 29500.  Links below are to the specification versions that are normative references for the ECMA-388 specification for OpenXPS.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20200721010354/http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%202%20(PDF).zip</link>
							<tag>ECMA-376, 1st edition, Office Open XML File Formats (December 2006), Part 2, Open Packaging Conventions. Available via Internet Archive.</tag>
							<comment>PDF with 2 annexes in ZIP file.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20200917212702/http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Office%20Open%20XML%201st%20edition%20Part%205%20%28PDF%29.zip</link>
							<tag>ECMA-376, 1st edition, Office Open XML File Formats (December 2006), Part 5, Markup Compatibility and Extensibility</tag>
							<comment>PDF in ZIP file. Available via Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.ecma-international.org/wp-content/uploads/TC46-XPS-White-Paper.pdf</link>
					<tag>Ecma OpenXPS Whitepaper (TC46) April 2009</tag>
					<comment>Informal but thorough introduction to OpenXPS.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_XML_Paper_Specification</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for Open XML Paper Specification</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Miscellaneous articles about support for OpenXPS and XPS in Windows.  These are listed roughly chronologically, with the newest first.  Support for OpenXPS was introduced with Windows 8 in 2012.  In April 2018, Microsoft eliminated the XPS viewer utility from the default distribution package for Windows 10, suggesting that Microsoft does not expect to continue full support for XPS or OpenXPS.  </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/deployment/planning/windows-10-removed-features</link>
							<tag>Features and functionality removed in Windows 10</tag>
							<comment>Starting with update 1803 (April 2018), the XPS Viewer utility required special administrative action for installation in Windows.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://support.office.com/en-us/article/save-or-convert-to-pdf-or-xps-in-project-desktop-d85416c5-7d77-4fd6-a216-6f4bf7c7c110#ID0EAADAAA=Windows</link>
							<tag>Save or convert to PDF or XPS | from Microsoft Office support site</tag>
							<comment>As of early 2020, the only Office applications for Windows with a Save As XPS option appear to be Access, Project, and Word, </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.windowscentral.com/how-get-xps-viewer-app-back-windows-10-april-2018-update</link>
							<tag>How to access XPS Viewer in the Windows 10 April 2018 Update | from Windows Central</tag>
							<comment>States that &quot;Microsoft is finally retiring support for the file format and removing the XPS Viewer app on new installations.&quot;</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://windowsreport.com/handle-xps-files-windows-10/</link>
							<tag>How to Handle XPS Files In Windows 10 (2018) | from Windows Report</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.howtogeek.com/148499/what-is-an-xps-file-and-why-does-windows-want-me-to-print-to-one/</link>
							<tag>What Is an XPS File and Why Does Windows Want Me to Print to One? (2017) | from How-To Geek</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.rawinfopages.com/tips/2015/10/print-to-pdf-in-windows-10-and-forget-xps/</link>
							<tag>Print to PDF in Windows 10 and forget XPS (2015) | from Raw Computing</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-8-OpenXPS-the-Latest-PDF-Killer-226721.shtml</link>
							<tag>Windows 8 OpenXPS, the Latest PDF Killer | from Softpedia News</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/printdocs/documents</link>
							<tag>XPS Documents | from Windows Dev Center</tag>
							<comment> Illustrates the move to add support for OpenXPS to Windows starting with Windows 8</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/printdocs/app-support-for-openxps-printing</link>
							<tag>App Support for OpenXPS Printing</tag>
							<comment>Despite being dated 05/30/2018, this relates to Windows 8 (released in 2012)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/windows/hardware/design/dn641615(v=vs.85)</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification: Overview</tag>
							<comment>Despite being dated 05/31/2017, the resources linked from this page date from as early as 2005</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20190112024614/https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/windows/hardware/design/dn641615(v=vs.85)</link>
							<tag>XML Paper Specification: Overview | via Internet Archive</tag>
							<comment>Included because the resource immediately above is no longer supported and may be removed. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources about the use of OpenXPS as the basis for a primary &quot;print path&quot; available in Windows to application developers through the XPS Print API.  The print path based on OpenXPS was introduced in 2012 with Windows 8 and is recommended over the earlier GDI Print API.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/drivers/print/windows-print-path-overview</link>
							<tag>Windows Print Path Overview | from Microsoft Hardware Dev Center</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-hardware/drivers/print/driver-support-for-openxps</link>
							<tag>Driver Support for OpenXPS | from Microsoft Hardware Dev Center</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://mspoweruser.com/google-chrome-uses-xps-print-api/</link>
							<tag>Printing experience in Google Chrome is expected to improve as Google embraces Microsoft’s XPS Print API for printing on Windows 10 (Nov 25, 2019) | from MSPoweruser blog</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources comparing OpenXPS with XPS</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/xps/hello-ecma-388-1st-edition</link>
							<tag>Hello Ecma-388 1st Edition (July 2009) | from XPS Team Blog</tag>
							<comment>Describes substantive changes between the XPS specification as submitted to Ecma for standardization and the published ECMA-388.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ecma-international.org/technical-committees/tc46/?tab=activities</link>
							<tag>TC46 - Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS): Documents Overview</tag>
							<comment>Links to a sequence of working drafts, starting with the specification as submitted by Microsoft</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ecma-international.org/wp-content/uploads/TC46-XPS-White-Paper.pdf</link>
							<tag>Ecma OpenXPS White Paper (April 2009) | from Ecma Technical Committee TC46</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources comparing OpenXPS/XPS with PDF</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_OpenXPS_and_PDF</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for Comparison of OpenXPS and PDF</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://digitalhumanities101.wordpress.com/2012/10/30/standards-pdf-vs-openxps-in-a-hello-world-example/</link>
							<tag>[Standards] PDF vs OpenXPS in a Hello World example (2012) | from Digital Humanities 101</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to submission of XPS as international standard:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/adrianford/minor-milestone-xps-goes-to-ecma</link>
							<tag>Minor Milestone - XPS goes to Ecma (2007) | from a Microsoft blog on XPS et cetera</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ecma-international.org/wp-content/uploads/XPS-Standard.pdf</link>
							<tag>Working draft 1.0.1 (September 2007) for XML Paper Specification as submitted to TC46 by Microsoft.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2006/10/7992/</link>
							<tag>Microsoft’s PDF-killer heads towards standards body (2006) | from Ars Technica</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://news.softpedia.com/news/Microsoft-to-Standardize-PDF-Killer-XPS-58802.shtml</link>
							<tag>Microsoft to Standardize PDF Killer - XPS  (2007) | from Softpedia News</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to JPEG XR.  This format was originally developed by Microsoft and formerly known as HD Photo and Windows Media Photo (<fddLink id="fdd000243">WMP</fddLink>).  After submission as a potential international standard in 2007,  JPEG XR was approved as ITU-T T.832 in March 2009 and has since been maintained and published by <a href="https://www.itscj.ipsj.or.jp/sc29/29w42901.htm#JpegXR">ISO/IEC SC29/WG1</a> as &quot;twinned&quot; standards as ITU-T T.832 and ISO/IEC IS 29199-2. The OpenXPS specification uses the original version from 2009 as a normative reference.  Several editions with minor corrections were published through 2016.  The 2019 edition added support for additional colour formats.  For full text of editions through 2019 of JPEG XR specifications, see <a href="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/13914">http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/13914</a>. </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPEG_XR</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for JPEG XR</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/project/jpeg-xr/</link>
							<tag>JPEG XR | background on development by Microsoft Research</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://jpeg.org/jpegxr/</link>
							<tag>Overview of JPEG XR | from jpeg.org</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/51609.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC IS 29199-2:2009
Part 2: JPEG XR image coding specification</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/11471</link>
							<tag>ITU-T T.832 (01/2012)</tag>
							<comment>This version incorporates minor corrections to the original 2009 standard.  Full text available.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/13914</link>
							<tag>ITU-T T.832 (V4) (06/2019)</tag>
							<comment>Full text available. The 2019 edition of the JPEG XR format specification added support for additional colour formats.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to the International Color Consortium (<a href="https://www.color.org/index.xalter">ICC</a>) profiles for color management as supported in OpenXPS.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.color.org/ICC_Minor_Revision_for_Web.pdf</link>
							<tag>ICC.1:2001-04.  File Format for Color Profiles</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://color.org/ICC1v42_2006-05.pdf</link>
							<tag>ICC.1:2004-10. Image technology colour management — Architecture, profile format, and data structure</tag>
							<comment>With errata incorporated, 5/22/2006.  Equivalent to ISO 15076-1:2005.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to the Open Font Format, the font specification incorporated into the OpenXPS format.  The ISO Open Font Format (ISO/IEC 14496-22) was based on Microsoft&apos;s OpenType specification.  </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenType</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for OpenType</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/43466.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 14496-22:2007. Information technology — Coding of audio-visual objects — Part 22: Open Font Format</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/74461.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 14496-22:2019. Information technology — Coding of audio-visual objects — Part 22: Open Font Format</tag>
							<comment/>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/</link>
							<tag>OpenType overview | from Microsoft</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/otspec140/</link>
							<tag>OpenType specification version 1.4</tag>
							<comment>  the foundation for the development of ISO/IEC 14496-22 Open Font Format standard. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://mpeg.chiariglione.org/sites/default/files/files/standards/docs/w13995.zip</link>
							<tag>White paper on ISO/IEC 14496-22: Open Font Format (2013) | by Vladimir Levantovsky</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Windows 10 introduced a Print to PDF virtual printer.  The articles below argued for use of PDF as opposed to either Open XPS or XPS.  </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.rawinfopages.com/tips/2015/10/print-to-pdf-in-windows-10-and-forget-xps/</link>
							<tag>Print to PDF in Windows 10 and forget XPS | from Raw Computing</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://allanjsmithie.wordpress.com/2016/01/21/how-to-understand-xps-format/</link>
							<tag>How-to: Understand XPS format (2016) | by Allan J. Smithie</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Tools for viewing or converting OpenXPS files</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.gnome.org/action/show/Projects/libgxps</link>
							<tag>libgxps | GObject based library for handling and rendering XPS documents. </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.online-convert.com/file-format/oxps</link>
							<tag>Online-Convert: OXPS, OpenXPS File (.oxps)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://convertio.co/oxps-xps/</link>
							<tag>Convertio: OXPS to XPS Converter</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.aconvert.com/format/oxps/</link>
							<tag>Aconvert: Convert OXPS Online</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://rootrisetech.com/product/xpsview</link>
							<tag>XPSView  (for Mac and IOS) | from RootRise Technologies</tag>
							<comment>Renders files in Microsoft&apos;s XPS  and OpenXPS formats.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://rootrisetech.com/product/xps-to-pdf</link>
							<tag>XPS-to-PDF | from RootRise Technologies</tag>
							<comment>Batch conversion of XPS and OpenXPS to PDF, available for Mac OS and Windows</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.novapdf.com/convert-xps-to-pdf-kb.html</link>
							<tag>NovaPDF: Convert XPS/OXPS to PDF</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/657</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/657</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM from UK National Archives about Open XML Paper Specification (OpenXPS).  PUID: fmt/657.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q977900</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q977900</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about Open XML Paper Specification.   Wikidata Title ID: Q977900</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
