<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><fdd:FDD id="fdd000581" titleName="Transmission X-Ray Microscopy (TXM)" shortName="TXM" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">	<fdd:properties>		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>			<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>		<fdd:formatCategories>			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>		</fdd:formatCategories>		<fdd:updates>			<fdd:date>2023-04-17</fdd:date>		</fdd:updates>		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>	</fdd:properties>	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>		<fdd:fullName>Transmission X-Ray Microscopy (TXM), ZEISS proprietary microscopy data format</fdd:fullName>		<fdd:keywords>			<fdd:keyword>3D formats</fdd:keyword>			<fdd:keyword>X-ray formats</fdd:keyword>		</fdd:keywords>		<fdd:description>			<p>TXM/TXRM are proprietary <a href="http://www.theobjects.com/dragonfly/dfhelp/4-1/Content/Key%20Features/Supported%20File%20Formats.htm">microscopy data files</a> created by ZEISS 3D X-Ray Microscopes.As described in <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZEISS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and File Storage</a>, 2014-2016, &quot;Datasetsthat contain a collection of projection images are saved as *.txrm files. Each *txrm file containsmultiple images...When used, Reconstructor manually reconstructs images stored in each *txrmfile to form a set of reconstructed slices. A slice is a 2D section of the 3D reconstructed volumethat is oriented in the X/Z plane. Slices generated from each *.txrm file are stored in a *.txmfile.&quot;</p>			<ul>				<li>Tomography, as described by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tomography">Wikipedia</a>, &quot;imaging by sections or sectioning that usesany kind of penetrating wave.&quot;</li>			</ul>			<p>The <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZEISS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and File Storage</a>, 2014-2016, Table B-1, ZEISS Filedescribes the package of files used in the program. Name extensions include:</p>			<ul>				<li>RCP - Xradia Versa parameter values for recipe points.</li>				<li>TXRM - Referred to as tomography dataset, 2D projection images acquired using Scout-and-Scan Control System program.</li>				<li>XRM - image acquired with Single and Continuous acquisition modes, save using Scout-and-Scan.</li>				<li>TXM - Referred to as an output reconstruction file, 3D tomography volume dataset file inproprietary ZEISS format, a stack of 2D reconstructed images, saved as a contiguousvolume.</li>				<li>TXM-EXM &amp; TXM-EXM-OOC (Out-of-Core format) - XM3DViewer previously savedfiles, store additional information for faster loading.</li>			</ul>			<p>Xradia Versa&#39;s Scout-and-Scan System is used to manage the process of data acquisition, fromsetting up, loading, scouting the region of interest (ROI), scanning, and acquiring thetomography.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/jmor.20938">XMReconstructor</a>, that accompanies ZEISS Xradia X-Ray CT scanners, is used to reconstructTXRM projections, producing TXM image stack files.</p>			<p>Per ZEISS&#39; Press Release, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220526013143/https://www.zeiss.co.in/microscopy/dynamic-content/news/2013/acquisition-xradia.html">ZEISS is Shaping the Future of Microscopy by Acquiring Xradia</a>, July2013, &quot;The unique optical design allows the ZEISS Xradia Ultra and Versa series to cover alarge resolution range, enabling the user to easily find the region of interest by zooming intolarger samples (Scout-and-Zoom).&quot;</p>			<p>				<b>Transmission X-Ray Microscopy (TXM):</b>			</p>			<p>As defined by Royal Society of Chemistry, Transmission X-Ray Microscopy is &quot;an imagingtechnique where a finely focused beam of X-rays is directed at the specimen and the energies andintensities of the transmitted X-rays are measured as a function of position.&quot;</p>			<p>According to Stephanie Spence in <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1361-6528/ac17ff">Transmission X-ray Microscopy and Its Applications inBattery Material Research--A Short Review</a>, 2021, &quot;...X-rays have the advantage of highpenetration power and are capable of looking at internal structures in bulk materials...TXMmeasured the transmitted X-rays after passage through the sample. X-rays interact with electronsin the matter when passing through a sample...The intensity, energy and directions of thetransmitted X-rays carry the sample information.&quot;</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZIESS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and File Storage, 2014-2016</a>, states &quot;X-ray microscopesform images based on the X-rays transmitted by the sample. Where the sample absorbs more X-rays, the image is darker; where it transmits more X-rays, the image is brighter. Absorptionincreases with density and thickness, and is also generally higher for elements with a higheratomic number in the periodic table. Magnification in X-ray microscopes is typically achievedeither by using a projection geometry with a point source (as in the Xradia Versa), or by usingoptical elements similar to a regular visible light microscope (as in the Xradia Ultra)...In X-rayComputed Tomography (CT), the sample is images from different directions...A single image atone particular angle is referred to as a projection. Computer algorithms can be used toreconstruct the internal, 3-dimensional (3D) structure of the sample from a series of projections.The reconstructed volume can be visualized in different ways.&quot;</p>			<p>Per ZEISS&#39; Press Release, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220526013143/https://www.zeiss.co.in/microscopy/dynamic-content/news/2013/acquisition-xradia.html">ZEISS is Shaping the Future of Microscopy by Acquiring Xradia</a>, July2013, &quot;This acquisition further strengthens the position of the ZEISS Microscopy businessgroup, the only manufacturer of light, electron and X-ray microscopes, with unique solutions forresearch and routine inspection in materials and life sciences application fields...X-raymicroscopes show unique capabilities in materials research, allowing for 3D imaging of theinternal structure of materials. Spatial resolution down to 50 nanometers can be achieved on alaboratory-based system. The non-destructive nature of X-ray imaging enables the observationand quantification of microstructural evolution in the same region of a single sample over time,or under changing environmental conditions.&quot;</p>			<p>				<b>TXM/TXRM Files:</b>			</p>			<p>According to the TXM Document, <a href="https://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/txm/sites/default/files/documents/txm-wizard_help.pdf">TXM Wizard Help</a>, from TXM Team at StanfordSynchrotron Radiation Lightsource (no date found), &quot;TXRM is a standard Xradia file formatwhich is usually an image stack taken with a certain motor scan (e.g. focus series, and/or tomography data). A reference image may be included in the file. A header containing theinformation about the motor positions and etc. is also included in the &#39;.txrm&#39; file.&quot;</p>			<p>				<a href="https://about.gitlab.com/">GitLab.com</a> user <a href="https://gitlab.gbar.dtu.dk/mskan">Martin Anderson personal project</a>, <a href="https://gitlab.gbar.dtu.dk/mskan/txrmtools">txrmtools</a>, 2019, &quot;The purpose of thisPython module is to extract information from .txrm data files from ZEISS Xradia Versa 3D X-ray microscopy scanners. The file format is essentially a Microsoft OLE2 container with aproprietary hierarchical structure that is specific to a family of ZEISS scanners...Disclaimer -This module is based on reverse engineering rather than a formal specification—users shouldexercise caution when using this module.&quot;. Note: the compilers of this resouce have not found other documentation to support this. <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			<p>In the <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/">ResearchGate.net</a> post, <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/post/Attributions_to_enter_in_Dragolfly_software_for_raw_images_obtained_from_micro_ct_scan/628679e61da20644cc247931/citation/download">Re: Attributions to Enter in Dragonfly software for Raw ImagesObtained from Micro CT Scan?</a>, May 2022, user Mike Marsh states, “TXRM files are input for3D reconstruction algorithm. The output of that reconstruction is a TXM image or DICOM stackor TIFF stack of CZI image which can be postprocessed in Dragonfly Pro.”</p>			<p>				<b>Uses of TXM/TXRM Files:</b>			</p>			<p>As described on <a href="https://www.zeiss.com/microscopy/en/products/x-ray-microscopy/xradia-versa.html#">ZEISS.com&#39;s X-Ray Microscopy Products page</a>, &quot;3D X-Ray Microscopes(XRM) provide superior 3D image quality and data for a wide range of materials and workingenvironments.&quot; Application examples include:</p>			<ul>				<li>Material Sciences, such as observing failure mechanisms and/or internal defects.</li>				<li>Life Sciences, such as 3D imaging of biological samples.</li>				<li>Electronics &amp; Semiconductors, such as analyzing printed circuit boards for reverseengineering.</li>				<li>Raw Materials, such as automated mineralogy in 3D</li>				<li>Additive Manufacturing (AM), such as shape, size, and volume distribution analysis ofparticles.</li>				<li>Lithium Ion Batteries, such as recipe development and supply chain control.</li>			</ul>						Stated in the <a href="https://journals.iucr.org/s/">Journal of Synchrotron Radiation</a> article, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3284347/">TXM-Wizard: A Program for AdvancedData Collection and Evaluation in Full-Field Transmission X-Ray Microscopy</a>, 2012, “Theunique capability of imaging three-dimensional structure with spatial resolution down to a fewtens of nanometers over a field of view of several tens of micrometers has made TXM a well-recognized tool for research ranging from materials science to biological studies.”																																			</fdd:description>		<fdd:shortDescription>TXM/TXRM are proprietary 3D data files created for ZEISS Xradia 3D X-Ray Microscopes. TXRM files store multiple 2D images that are reconstructed and generated into a set of slices that are stored in a 3D tomography volume dataset file, TXM.</fdd:shortDescription>		<fdd:productionPhase>Middle to final state. TXM/TXRM files are used by the ZEISS Xradia 3D X-Ray Microscopes,TXRM files containing a collection of dataset images are used by the Reconstructor software toform 2D slices that are stored as TXM files. TXM files can be loaded into format supportivesoftware to visualize and analyze the data.</fdd:productionPhase>	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>	<fdd:localUse>		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress has a small number of TXM files in its collections.</fdd:experience>		<fdd:preference>See the Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement for format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/design3D.html">3D content</a>.</fdd:preference>	</fdd:localUse>	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>		<fdd:disclosure>			Proprietary dataset format. As stated in the <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZIESS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File andFile Storage, 2014-2016</a>, TXM is a &quot;3D tomography volume dataset file in proprietaryZEISS format.&quot;				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.		</fdd:disclosure>		<fdd:documentation>			<p>No formal specification but informal information on format obtained in the <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZIESS XradiaVersa&#39;s User Guide, File and File Storage, 2014-2016</a>.</p>			<p>Other useful TXM/TXRM format information found:</p>			<ul>				<li>					<a href="https://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/txm/sites/default/files/documents/txm-wizard_help.pdf">TXM-Wizard Help PDF</a>				</li>				<li>					<a href="http://paulbourke.net/dataformats/">Paul Bourke Personal Collection of References - Xradia X-Ray Transmission Image Data</a> as stored by Xradia scanners.</li>			</ul>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:documentation>		<fdd:adoption>			<p>According to Xianghui Xiao in <a href="https://journals.iucr.org/s/issues/2022/01/00/rv5158/rv5158.pdf">TXM-Sandbox: An Open-Source Software forTransmission X-Ray Microscopy Data Analysis</a>, 2021, “TXM data processing dependson the type of data. Different types of TXM require different analysis processes andprerequisites for each individual process step...There are a few software programs eitherdedicated to or capable of TXM data analysis.”</p>			<ul>				<li>TXM-Wizard – toolbox that supports Xradia TXM file format, latest updateSeptember 2018.<br/>(<a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/txm-wizard/">https://sourceforge.net/projects/txm-wizard/</a>)</li>				<li>PyXAS – open-source package for 2D X-Ray Analysis.<br/>(<a href="https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1601344">https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1601344</a>)</li>				<li>MANTiS – free and open-source tool build with Python for spectromicroscopydata analysis.<br/>(<a href="https://spectromicroscopy.com/">https://spectromicroscopy.com/</a>)</li>				<li>TXM-Sandbox – open-source software for TXM data analysis.<br/>(<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1107/S1600577521011978">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1107/S1600577521011978</a>)<br/>(<a href="https://github.com/xianghuix/TXM_Sandbox">https://github.com/xianghuix/TXM_Sandbox</a>)</li>			</ul>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			<p>Other TXM/TXRM post-processing software:</p>			<ul>				<li>Open Xradia - plugin for Fiji (ImageJ) for reading XRM, TXRM, TXM imagefiles (from Xradia XRM systems), opens them as a stack.<br/>(<a href="https://forum.image.sc/t/open-xradia-zeiss-microct-xrm-files-in-fiji/44466">https://forum.image.sc/t/open-xradia-zeiss-microct-xrm-files-in-fiji/44466</a>)</li>				<li>XRM_Reader - dxchange reader for ZEISS proprietary data format TXRM toPython lists, imports metadata for reconstructing data from file header.<br/>(<a href="https://pypi.org/project/xrmreader/">https://pypi.org/project/xrmreader/</a>)<br/>(<a href="https://github.com/mrsutherland/XRM_Reader/releases/tag/v1.0.0">https://github.com/mrsutherland/XRM_Reader/releases/tag/v1.0.0</a>)</li>				<li>Dragonfly-Pro – visualization and analysis software using Python scriptingexclusively from ZEISS.<br/>(<a href="https://info.dragonfly-pro.com/Features.html">https://info.dragonfly-pro.com/Features.html</a>)<br/>(<a href="http://www.theobjects.com/dragonfly/dfhelp/4-1/Content/Key%20Features/Supported%20File%20Formats.htm">http://www.theobjects.com/dragonfly/dfhelp/4-1/Content/Key%20Features/Supported%20File%20Formats.htm</a>)</li>				<li>ctutils 0.3 - utilities for analyzing data in CT scans, such as Xradia&#39;s TXM format.<br/>(<a href="https://ctutils.readthedocs.io/en/release-0.3/">https://ctutils.readthedocs.io/en/release-0.3/</a>)<br/>(<a href="https://pypi.org/project/ctutils/">https://pypi.org/project/ctutils/</a>)</li>				<li>TXM3DViewer – ZEISS software for viewing and analyzing 3D volumetric data.<br/>				</li>			</ul>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:adoption>		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>			<p>Per <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZIESS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and File Storage</a>, 2014-2016, “Carl Zeiss X-Ray Microscopy retains the patent rights to any and all processes and inventionsdeveloped during the course of performing work for the customer, unless specificallyidentified to the contrary in advance by the customer. The fact that this guide includes acopyright notice does not in any way affect the proprietary status of this guide... Raad andScout-and-Scan are trademarks and Xradia Ultra, Xradia Versa, ZEISS, Carl Zeiss, andthe ZEISS logo are registered trademarks of CARL ZEISS AG CORPORATION.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>		<fdd:transparency>			<p>				<a href="https://confluence.nanofab.ualberta.ca/">nanoFAB Knowledge Base&#39;s ZEISS Xradia Versa 620 Workflow - Staff Analysis</a>, lastmodified May 2022, provides staff with instructions for sample submitting and dataprocessing when using the Xradia Versa 620. The workflow describes the &quot;other file formats available: 2D projection files (.xrm), reconstructed raw files (.txm), projectiondataset (.txrm) and recipe file (.rcp). Most of these files are Zeiss proprietary and needspecial versions of software to open.&quot;</p>			<p>See Adoption for more information on software that can open, read, and analyzeTXM/TXRM data files.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:transparency>		<fdd:selfDocumentation>			<p>TXM/TXRM files contain some form of metadata, but limited information found aboutthe metadata contained.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://zenodo.org/">Zenodo.org</a>, a general-purpose open repository for related digital artefacts, <a href="https://zenodo.org/record/4822516#.ZFMZiezMIWp">HDTomoTXRM Micro-CT Datasets</a>, May 2021, has a collection of 6 individual micro ComputedTomography datasets, stating files contains &quot;all raw projection and reconstructed volumedata both in the native ZEISS TXRM/TXM format...The TXRM contains the rawprojection data as well as metadata specifying the scan geometry. The TXM contains thevendor volume reconstruction.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:selfDocumentation>		<fdd:externalDependencies>			<p>Per <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZEISS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and File Storage, 2014-2016</a>, &quot;The XradiaVersa includes the hardware and software needed to create and view tomographyimages.&quot;Comments welcome.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:externalDependencies>		<fdd:techProtection>			<p>Per <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">ZEISS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and File Storage, 2014-2016, ProprietaryNotice</a>, &quot;The material contained herein consists of information that is the property of CarlZeiss X-ray Microscopy, and intended solely for customer use in operating the system(Xradia Versa) described in this guide. This guide or any part of it must not be translated,reproduced or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic or mechanical,including photocopying, recording, or by any information or retrieval system. Violatorswill be prosecuted...The use of general descriptive names, registered names, trademarks,etc. in this guide does not imply, even in the absence of a specific statement, that suchnames are exempt from the relevant protective laws and regulations and therefore free forgeneral use. Software programs will fully remain the property of Carl Zeiss X-rayMicroscopy. No program, documentation, or subsequent upgrade thereof may bedisclosed to any third party, unless prior written consent of Carl Zeiss X-ray Microscopy has been procured to do so, nor may they be copied or otherwise duplicated, even for thecustomer’s internal needs apart from a single backup copy for safety purposes.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:techProtection>	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>		<fdd:otherQF>			<fdd:factor>				<fdd:tag>3D Model Geometry</fdd:tag>				<fdd:note>					<p>According to the ZEISS Catalog, Maintain High Resolution at Large Working Distances, 2021 (<a href="https://asset downloads.zeiss.com/catalogs/download/mic/59f564ec-a757-4f23-9607-b4ae6d91c05e/EN_product-info_Xradia-510-Versa_rel-1.2.pdf">Downloadable PDF Link)</a>, the “Dragonfly Pro program supports regular and unstructured surface meshes and contains advanced editing tools to create regions of interest from a mesh and vice versa.”</p>					<p>Limited information on specifics relating to other programs.</p>					<p>						<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>				</fdd:note>			</fdd:factor>			<fdd:factor>				<fdd:tag>3D Model Appearance</fdd:tag>				<fdd:note>					<p>According to the ZEISS Catalog, Maintain High Resolution at Large Working Distances, 2021 (<a href="https://asset downloads.zeiss.com/catalogs/download/mic/59f564ec-a757-4f23-9607-b4ae6d91c05e/EN_product-info_Xradia-510-Versa_rel-1.2.pdf">Downloadable PDF Link)</a>, the Dragonfly Pro software tools can be trailered for optimal workflow, allowing users to “control registration, map differences, and customize the appearance” of TXM files.</p>					<p>Limited information on specifics relating to other programs.</p>					<p>						<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>				</fdd:note>			</fdd:factor>			<fdd:factor>				<fdd:tag>3D Model Scene</fdd:tag>				<fdd:note>					<p>Little to no information is found on 3D model scene, light source, camera, or position. Different post-processing software may have different options or settings.</p>					<p>						<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>				</fdd:note>			</fdd:factor>			<fdd:factor>				<fdd:tag>3D Model Animation</fdd:tag>				<fdd:note>					<p>Little to no information is found on 3D model animation. Different post-processingsoftware may have different options or settings for animation.</p>					<p>						<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>				</fdd:note>			</fdd:factor>		</fdd:otherQF>	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>		<fdd:signifiersGroup>			<fdd:filenameExtension>				<fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:sigValue>txm</fdd:sigValue>				</fdd:sigValues>				<fdd:note>ZEISS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and FileStorage, 2014-2016, Table B-1. See <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf</a>.</fdd:note>			</fdd:filenameExtension>			<fdd:filenameExtension>				<fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:sigValue>txrm</fdd:sigValue>				</fdd:sigValues>				<fdd:note>ZEISS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and FileStorage, 2014-2016, Table B-1. See <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf</a>.</fdd:note>			</fdd:filenameExtension>			<fdd:filenameExtension>				<fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:sigValue>xrm</fdd:sigValue>				</fdd:sigValues>				<fdd:note>ZEISS Xradia Versa&#39;s User Guide, File and FileStorage, 2014-2016, Table B-1. See <a href="https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf">https://www.physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/Xradia_Versa_Users_Guide_v11x_510.pdf</a>.</fdd:note>			</fdd:filenameExtension>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>					<fdd:note>No Pronom PUID as of May 2023.</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>					<fdd:note>No Wikidata entry as of May 2023</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>		</fdd:signifiersGroup>	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>	<fdd:notes>		<fdd:history>			<p>Per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Zeiss_AG">Carl ZEISS AG Wikipedia page</a>, ZEISS, the manufacturer of optical systems andoptoelectronics, was founded in Germany in 1846 by optician Carl Zeiss, joined later by ErnstAbbe, and Otto Schott. The company is multi-national and is active business segments IndustrialQuality and Research, Medical Technology, Consumer Markets, and SemiconductorManufacturing Technology.</p>		</fdd:history>	</fdd:notes>	<fdd:formatSpecifications/>	<fdd:usefulReferences>		<fdd:urls>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>ZEISS <a href="https://www.zeiss.com/microscopy/en/home.html">(https://www.zeiss.com/microscopy/en/home.html)</a>					</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://physics.purdue.edu/xrm/new-users/training/TXM3DViewer-UsersGuide.pdf</link>							<tag>Carl Zeiss X-ray Microscopy Inc. TXM3DViewer Workstation 1.2, User Guide</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.zeiss.com/microscopy/en/about-us.html</link>							<tag>A Long Story of Success</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.zeiss.com/microscopy/en/products/x-ray-microscopy/xradia-versa.html</link>							<tag>ZEISS Xradia Versa X-ray Microscopes</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.zeiss.com/microscopy/en/products/software/zeiss-zen/czi-image-file-format.html</link>							<tag>CZI Image Format for Microscopes</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20220526013143/https://www.zeiss.co.in/microscopy/dynamic-content/news/2013/acquisition-xradia.html</link>							<tag>ZEISS is Shaping the Future of Microscopy by Acquiring Xradia(Web.Archive.org)</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Info.Dragonfly-Pro.com <a href="https://info.dragonfly-pro.com/home.html">(https://info.dragonfly-pro.com/home.html)</a>					</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://info.dragonfly-pro.com/home.html</link>							<tag>Dragonfly Pro Exclusive to ZEISS</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>http://www.theobjects.com/dragonfly/dfhelp/4-1/Content/Key%20Features/Supported%20File%20Formats.htm</link>							<tag>Dragonfly Key Features – Supported File Formats</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://microtomography.blogspot.com/2020/06/fiji-plugin-to-read-xrm-files.html</link>					<tag>Microtomography.Blogspot.com - Fiji plugin to read Xradia files</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://quantum3d.com/mantis/</link>					<tag>Quantum3D.com - Fiji plugin to read Xradia files</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>http://paulbourke.net/dataformats/txm/</link>					<tag>PaulBourke.net - TXM file format (Xradia)</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://journals.iucr.org/s/issues/2022/01/00/rv5158/</link>					<tag>Journal of Synchrotron Radiation - TXM-Sandbox: an open-source software for transmission X-ray microscopy dataanalysis</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Stanford Synchrotron Radiation Lightsource <a href="https://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/txm/">(https://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/txm/)</a>					</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/txm/sites/default/files/documents/txm-wizard_help.pdf</link>							<tag>TXM-Wizard Help PDF</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/txm/node/1</link>							<tag>Full-Field Transmission X-Ray Microscopy</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/content/beam-lines/bl6-2c#:~:text=Beam%20line%206-2c%20is,resolution%20down%20to%2030%20nm</link>							<tag>Experimental Station 6-2c</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1361-6528/ac17ff</link>					<tag>IOPScience.iop.org - Transmission X-Ray Microscopy and Its Applications in Battery MaterialResearch—A Short Review</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-981-10-6156-1_96</link>					<tag>Link.Springer.com - Scanning Transmission X-Ray Microscopy</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://github.com/data-exchange/dxchange/pull/38</link>					<tag>GitHub.com - Make Metadata Available From Xradia Microscopes #38</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://sourceforge.net/projects/txm-wizard/</link>					<tag>SourceForge.net - TXM-Wizard</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://sites.google.com/sheffield.ac.uk/sheffieldtomographycentre/access-costs/faq</link>					<tag>Sheffield Tomography Centre - FAQs</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.ala.org/acrl/sites/ala.org.acrl/files/content/publications/booksanddigitalresources/digital/9780838939147_3D_OA.pdf</link>					<tag>American Library Association - 3D Data Creation to Curation: Community Standards for 3D Data Preservation</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Wikipedia.org</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X-ray_absorption_near_edge_structure</link>							<tag>X-Ray Absorption Near Edge Structure</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zenodo</link>							<tag>Zenodo</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>		</fdd:urls>	</fdd:usefulReferences></fdd:FDD>