<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000298" titleName="Raster Product Format" shortName="RPF" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-group</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>gis</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2011-10-27</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Raster Product Format (RPF)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>geospatial data formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>georeferenced image formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>raster image formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The Raster Product Format (RPF) is a standard
data structure developed in 1994 as a U.S. Military Standard for geospatial databases composed of rectangular
arrays of pixel values (e.g. in digitized maps or images) in
compressed or uncompressed form. Its intended use was to govern the design of a family of digital data interchange products that comprise digital maps, images, and other geographic data for military applications.</p>
			<p>It was designed as a general, adaptable
format to encompass raster products in compressed or uncompressed
form.  The intent was to enable
application software to use the data in RPF format on computer readable
interchange media (e.g. CD-ROM) directly without further manipulations
or transformation.  The format is characterized by a hierarchical directory structure with a table of contents file, sometimes referred to as an A.TOC file, and one or more directories of files representing frames of raster data.  Optionally, lookup tables for color palettes may be stored as separate files under RPF/LOOKUP.  Frames are divided into subframes (tiles).  File-naming follows the 8.3 convention.  The root directory is named RPF.  File naming and extension conventions are documented fully in section 4.5.4 of the <a href="http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/2411/2411_RPF.pdf">specification</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>RPF is a data structure for geospatial databases composed of rectangular arrays of pixel values (e.g., in digitized images)</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase/>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Affinity to</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000282</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ADRG</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Arc Digitized Raster Graphic</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>RPF was specifically intended to support interchange in a common format of ADRG raster maps and ARC Digital Raster Imagery (ADRI).  ADRI is not described separately on this website.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Unclassified United States military standard.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>Military Standard:
<a href="http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/2411/2411_RPF.pdf">Raster Product Format</a> MIL-STD-2411
6 OCTOBER 1994.</p>
			<p>Each product category representing a subtype of
RPF was to be described in
a separate product specification referring to the RPF standard.  Supplementary documentation is in <a href="http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/2411/2411_1.pdf">MIL-STD-2411-1</a>,
which defines registered data values to be used with RPF files and <a href="http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/2411/2411_2.pdf">MIL-STD-2411-2</a>,
Integration of Raster Product
Format Files into the National
Imagery Transmission Format.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The Raster Product Format (RPF) was defined in 1994 as a format for interchange of raster data between producers of such data in DoD and users of the data, to help facilitate interoperability among mission-critical systems. Products based on RPF remain in use today. Controlled Image Base (CIB), Compressed ARC Digitized Raster Graphic (CADRG), and Digital Point Positioning Data Base (DPPDB) are three products incorporating this standard.</p>
			<p>RPF is used for non-polar and polar raster maps transformed from DMA's ARC Digitized Raster Graphics (ADRG) maps, as specified in MIL-A-89007;imagery transformed from ARC Digital Raster Imagery (ADRI), as specified in MIL-A-89027.</p>
			<p>
				<a href="http://www.aviation.dla.mil/rmf/products_digital.htm##4">The Controlled Image Base (CIB)</a> is an RPF product. CIB started as a product called Arc Digital Raster Image (ADRI). This was a large orthomosaic and was difficult to use with the computer capacities of the times. This product was converted to a Raster Product Format (RPF) and was named CIB.</p>
			<p>At its current 1 meter resolution, CIB is used by Mission Planners, FEMA, and in cockpit displays. CIB is considered a very important foundation based product by the National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency (NGIA).  Controlled Image Base and CIB are registered trademarks of NGIA.  The final product can only be released to the DoD, its contractors, and other Executive Agencies supporting DoD activities.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No known license or patent concerns for generation and use of the format.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome.</a>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>TBD</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>TBD</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>TBD</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>The format allows for security classification as metadata, but does not appear to employ technical protection as part of the format.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>The tiled approach supports panning performance.</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>In practice, RPF-based products have specified spatial and bit-depth characterastics.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>TBD</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>A raster product, with no support for vector graphics or typographical effects.</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:multispectral>
				<p>An image may be band sequential or band interleaved.  An image may be band-interleaved by pixel, or by line, or by subframe.  Each spatial data subsection in a frame contains one or more spectral groups; within each spectral group, each subframe may contain
one or more spectral band tables; each spectral band table is composed of one or more image rows; each image row is composed of one or more spectral band lines; and each spectralband line is composed of one or more image codes.</p>
				<p>In the band interleaved by pixel (<fddLink id="fdd000305">BIP_enc</fddLink>) case, there will be one spectral group; within the spectral group, each subframe table will contain one spectral band table, and each image row will contain one spectral band line. Each pixel will comprise a series of data element values -- one for each spectral band represented.</p>
				<p>In the band interleaved by line (<fddLink id="fdd000304">BIL_enc</fddLink>) case, there will be one spectral group; within the spectral group, each subframe table will contain one and only one spectral band table, and each image row will contain multiple spectral band lines. </p>
				<p>In the band interleaved by subframe case, there will be one spectral group; within the spectral group, each subframe table will contain multiple spectral band tables, and each image row in each spectral band table will contain one and only one spectral band line. In the case of a subframe-level band sequential RGB image, three such tables would be used -- oneeach for red, green, and blue data.</p>
				<p>In the band sequential (<fddLink id="fdd000306">BSQ_enc</fddLink>) case, there will be multiple spectral groups (one per band: three spectral groups in the RGB case); each subframe table within each spectral group will contain one spectral band table, and each image row will contain one spectral band line.</p>
				<p>The specification for a given RPF-based product will specify the spectral band format of the spatial data.</p>
			</fdd:multispectral>
			<fdd:beyondImage>The format is designed to support convenient replacement of a single frame file, retaining an update history, and to allow for explicitly missing data.  It was also designed to be extensible, allowing for new fields and record types.</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:gisQF>
			<fdd:normalGIS>The horizontal datum for RPF data is WGS-84.  The vertical datum for RPF data is defined in the individual RPF product specifications.
Scale and geographical coverage for the full resource and for individual frames is recorded.</fdd:normalGIS>
			<fdd:metadataGIS>The accuracy of individual RPF-compatible data products are specified in the individual RPF product specifications.</fdd:metadataGIS>
		</fdd:gisQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup/>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/2411/2411_RPF.pdf</link>
					<tag>Raster Product Format </tag>
					<comment>Military Standard,
MIL-STD-2411
6 OCTOBER 1994</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/2411/2411_1.pdf</link>
					<tag>Registered Data Values for RPF</tag>
					<comment>Military Standard,
MIL-STD-2411-1
30-Aug-94.  This document is a companion document to the
Raster Product Format (RPF), MIL-STD-2411.
It contains all registered data values referenced in the standard.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/2411/2411_2.pdf</link>
					<tag>Integration of Raster Product
Format Files Into the National
Imagery Transmission Format</tag>
					<comment>Military Standard,
MIL-STD-2411-2
26 AUGUST 1994. This standard is intended to provide a common
interchange format for users of RPF data and of NITF data.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The Federation of American Scientists has descriptions and a copy of the specification for CIB and DPPDB, applications of RPF.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.fas.org/irp/program/core/cib.htm</link>
							<tag>Controlled Image Base (CIB)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.fas.org/irp/program/core/mil-c-89041-cib.htm</link>
							<tag>Specification for Controlled Image Base (CIB)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.fas.org/irp/program/core/dppdb.htm</link>
							<tag>Digital Point Positioning Data Base</tag>
							<comment>From Federation of American Scientists.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>A number of military geospatial specifications, including those for CADRG and CIB, which are based on RPF, are available via a NIMA page that looks as though it is not currently maintained (as of October 2011).</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/</link>
							<tag>NIMA Geospatial Standards and Specifications</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/89038/89038_CADRG.pdf</link>
							<tag>Compressed ADRG (CADRG)
</tag>
							<comment>October 6, 1994</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/89038/89038A2.pdf</link>
							<tag>CADRG, Amendment 2</tag>
							<comment>March 28, 2000.  Supersedes Amendment 1.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/89041/89041.pdf</link>
							<tag>Controlled Image Base (CIB)</tag>
							<comment>May 15, 1995</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/89041/89041am1.pdf</link>
							<tag>CIB Amendment 1</tag>
							<comment>July 31, 1995</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://earth-info.nga.mil/publications/specs/printed/89041/PRF89041.pdf</link>
							<tag>CIB Revision A</tag>
							<comment>March 28, 2000</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.aviation.dla.mil/rmf/products_digital.htm##4</link>
					<tag>Defense Logistics Agency -- Mapping Customer Operations -- Digital Products: Controlled Image Base</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://wiki.hexagongeospatial.com/index.php?title=Raster_Product_Format</link>
					<tag>Hexagon Geospatial Wiki: Raster Product Format</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
