<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000020" titleName="Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG), Version 1.1" shortName="SVG_1_1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-03-10</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.1</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>vector graphic formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>SVG is a language for describing two-dimensional graphics in XML.  The XML DTD for SVG (version 1.x) allows for three types of graphic objects: vector graphic shapes (e.g., paths consisting of straight lines and curves), raster graphics (raster images), and text. Graphical objects can be grouped, styled, transformed and composited into previously rendered objects.  The feature set includes nested transformations, clipping paths, alpha masks, filter effects and template objects.  SVG may also be used for animations; see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>SVG is a language for describing two-dimensional graphics in XML. SVG allows for three types of graphic objects: vector graphic shapes (e.g., paths consisting of straight lines and curves), raster graphics (raster images), and text. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Generally a final-state (end-user delivery) format. </fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000075</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>XML (EXtensible Markup Language)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG), Version 1.0 (2001), not described at this Web site.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG), Version 2. This update is under development. As of March 2020, a W3C Candidate Recommendation, issued October 4, 2018,  is available at <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG2/">http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG2/</a>. The most recent editor&apos;s draft can be found at <a href=" https://svgwg.org/svg2-draft/">https://svgwg.org/svg2-draft/</a>.  Not described at this website at this time.  Work on a Version 1.2 of the full SVG standard has been abandoned.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has modified version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000043</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>SVG_Tiny_1_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) Tiny, Version 1.2</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>SVG Profile intended for implementation on a range of devices, including cellphones and PDAs as well as laptops and personal computers.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Two reduced profiles of SVG 1.1 for mobile devices: SVG Basic 1.1 and SVG Tiny 1.1, not described separately at this website.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000278</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>EPUB, Electronic Publication, Version 2</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>EPUB_2 readers are required to recognize and display embedded SVG images.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000308</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_3</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Electronic Publication, Version 3</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>EPUB_3 uses a restricted subset of SVG 1.1 to represent inline vector graphics in documents based on XHTML and in standalone SVG-based EPUBs.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000247</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ODF_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>OpenDocument Format (ODF) Family, OASIS and ISO/IEC 26300</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>ODF uses the svg: prefix for elements and attributes compatible with SVG 1.1.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>None</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) includes SVG as a preferred format for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/stillimg.html">other graphic images in digital form</a>. The RFS does not specify a version of SVG.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard from W3C.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/">Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.1 (Second Edition)</a>. SVG_1_1 was originally published in 2003.  The Second Edition includes clarificatons and corrections for errata but no new features, released on August 16, 2011.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Many enthusiastic users and groups; see <a href="#useful">Useful references</a> below.  SVG is supported in Adobe tools, Visio (Microsoft), Corel Draw 11, and as an export format by ESRI ArcGIS. There are several open source applications and software libraries that can read and write SVG images. SVG is listed in <a href="https://libraries.flvc.org/documents/181844/502298/Recommended+Data+Formats/">Recommended Data Formats for Preservation Purposes in the Florida Digital Archive</a> in the column for formats for which the archive has high confidence level for preservation.  Browser support has varied with many complaints about lack of support by Internet Explorer.  <a href="https://psdtowp.net/svg.html">An infographic from late 2014</a> indicates that support is full in Safari, Firefox, Chrome, and Opera; support in IE started with IE 9 and support in Android with version 4.  A more <a href="http://caniuse.com/#cats=SVG">detailed presentation of SVG feature support</a> is available from caniuse.com.  A feature support comparison is also available at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_layout_engines_%28Scalable_Vector_Graphics%29">Comparison of layout engines (Scalable Vector Graphics)</a> on Wikipedia.  However the Wikipedia table may not have been kept up to date.  <a href="http://www.hongkiat.com/blog/test-svg-format-browser-engines/">Testing SVG support across browser engines</a> explores support by the engines used in various browsers on a test SVG file.  What these tables and tests suggest is that some features are less widely supported than others.  Support for ICC profiles and some font-related capabilities may be examples of less widely supported features.  In some contexts, animations and audio are not rendered.</p>
			<p>The October 2011 <fddLink id="fdd000308">EPUB_3</fddLink> specification for Electronic Publications uses a restricted subset of SVG_1_1 as a content document format for graphics, including use as a top-level format for comics and graphic novels.  Not supported in EPUB_3 are animations and embedding of &quot;foreign objects&quot; in forms other than XHTML.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No special issues.  As of January 2004, the SVG Working Group was not aware of any royalty-bearing patents they believe to be essential to SVG.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Based on XML, hence inherently transparent.
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Includes &lt;metadata&gt; element designed to hold elements from other XML namespaces.  Hence an SVG file can contain rich descriptive or administrative metadata using any other DTD.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>Good support.</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>Scalable.  Optional settings for rendering hints: <i>crispEdges</i> and <i>geometricPrecision</i>.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>SVG colors are specified in the sRGB color space.  SVG content can specify an alternate color specification using a profile as defined by the <a href="http://www.color.org/">International Color Consortium (ICC)</a>.  See the <a href="http://www.color.org/ICC1v42_2006-05.pdf">ICC Profile Format Specification. ICC.1:2004-10</a>.  If ICC-based colors are provided and the SVG user agent supports ICC color, then the ICC-based color takes precedence over the sRGB color specification.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>Rich support.</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:multispectral>Not applicable.</fdd:multispectral>
			<fdd:beyondImage>Support for animations.  Text in alternate languages for labels, etc.</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>svg</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>image/svg+xml</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Proposed in standards documentation.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>image/svg-xml</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Found in practice.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/92</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/92">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/92</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q2078</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>No version declared. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2078">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2078</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>Animations in SVG:</b>  SVG markup can be used to present <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/animate.html">animations</a> on the web in several ways: including using SVG&apos;s animation elements, using CSS, or by scripting.  The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SVG_animation">Wikipedia entry for SVG animation</a> offers a number of examples using different approaches.</p>
			<p>In 2013, most web sites presented simple animations as <fddLink id="fdd000133">GIF_89a</fddLink> files and more complex animations and interactives as Flash <fddLink id="fdd000130">SWF_7</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000248">SWF_8</fddLink> files (or later versions). Commentators with an interest in animation, including advocates for SVG as a publicly disclosed format, compared SVG and SWF but noted that the powerful authoring software available for Flash gave SWF the edge.  Since then, the Flash plugin has been recognized as a persistent security risk and <fddLink id="fdd000481">HTML 5</fddLink> has provided other means for embedding video in web pages.  See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML5#%22Thoughts_on_Flash%22">Thoughts on Flash</a> from Wikipedia entry for HTML5.  In early 2020, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GIF#Animated_GIF">animated GIFs</a> are still very popular on the web, including for advertising.  The compilers of this resource have not attemped to determine whether SVG animations are used more widely now that most browsers support them.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>SVG was originally developed through a process that began in 1996, with a call for responses to <a href="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/ScalableReq">W3C Scalable Graphics Requirements</a>.  According to <a href="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/WG/wiki/Secret_Origin_of_SVG">Secret Origin of SVG</a>, there were six proposals submitted by 1998, and SVG was particularly influenced by VML (Vector Markup Language), already deployed in Microsoft products, and PGML, a proposal from a partnership led by Adobe and using the same imaging model as in Postscript and PDF.</p>
			<p>Version 2 of SVG has been under development for several years.  As of March 2020, a W3C Candidate Recommendation, issued October 4, 2018,  is available at <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG2/">http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG2/</a>. The most recent editor&apos;s draft can be found at <a href=" https://svgwg.org/svg2-draft/">https://svgwg.org/svg2-draft/</a>. See also <a href="https://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/WG/wiki/SVG2_Requirements_Input">SVG2 Requirements Input</a>.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/</link>
					<tag>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.1 (Second Edition)</tag>
					<comment>Multi-page HTML presentation</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/single-page.html</link>
					<tag>Single page view of Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.1 (Second Edition)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/animate</link>
					<tag>W3C SVG animation specifications</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources from W3C related to SVG.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/</link>
							<tag>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG)</tag>
							<comment>Hub page for W3C SVG activities</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG12/</link>
							<tag>2005 working draft of Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.2 Specification</tag>
							<comment>Work on SVG 1.2 Full appears to have been abandoned soon after this.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.w3.org/TR/SVGMobile/</link>
							<tag>Mobile SVG Profiles: SVG Tiny and SVG Basic.  W3C Recommendation 14 January 2003</tag>
							<comment>Initial profiles of SVG suited to displaying vector graphics on small devices.  Edited in place 15 June 2009</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.w3.org/TR/SVGMobile12/</link>
							<tag>Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) Tiny 1.2 Specification, W3C Recommendation 22 December 2008</tag>
							<comment>A profile of SVG suited both to small devices and personal computers.  </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/2002/Talks/www2002-svgtut-ih/hwtut.pdf</link>
							<tag>SVG Tutorial (2002) | by David Duce, Ivan Herman, Bob Hopgood</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/WG/wiki/SVG2_Requirements_Input</link>
							<tag>SVG2 Requirements Input | from W3C</tag>
							<comment>Includes discussion and records working group decisions, with links to minutes as appropriate.  Only one change since July 2012.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scalable_Vector_Graphics</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia article on Scalable Vector Graphics</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SVG_animation</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia article on SVG Animation</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20100208221439/http://www.svg.org/</link>
					<tag>Archived page for SVG.org.</tag>
					<comment>Enthusiast site. Active page not found on February 8, 2012; many pages archived by the Internet Archive, including this 2010 example.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>LearnSVG (offline as of early 2020) was a site with links to tutorials and other resources related to SVG.  The initial site (first archived by the Internet Archive in 2003) was based on the content of the book &quot;Learn SVG – The Web Graphics Standard&quot; by Jon Frost, Stefan Goessner and Michel Hirtzler.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20030722112937/http://learnsvg.com/</link>
							<tag>LearnSVG site as of July 2003</tag>
							<comment>Has outline and extracts of chapters from the LearnSVG book.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20160324001146/http://www.learnsvg.com/</link>
							<tag>LearnSVG site as of March 2016</tag>
							<comment>The front page was now a rich menu of links to resources related to SVG.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.codeproject.com/Articles/5485/Learn-SVG-The-Web-Graphics-Standard</link>
							<tag>Learn SVG: The Web Graphics Standard - Chapter 7</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://tavmjong.free.fr/INKSCAPE/MANUAL/html/Web.html</link>
					<tag>SVG and the Web, Chapter 23 of Inkscape: Guide to a Vector Drawing Program</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3schools.com/graphics/svg_intro.asp</link>
					<tag>SVG Tutorial | from w3schools.com</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://psdtowp.net/svg.html</link>
					<tag>Scalable Vector Graphics Infographic (2015)</tag>
					<comment>Includes information on support in browsers, on mobile devices, etc.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://svg-wow.org/index.html</link>
					<tag>SVG-WOW | gallery of SVG examples</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://old.carto.net/</link>
					<tag>OLD.carto.net</tag>
					<comment>Website (with content in English and German) devoted to cartography. This section (no longer maintained) focused on the use of SVG for mapping applications.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Adobe Systems has been actively involved in the development of SVG and supports SVG in several products.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://helpx.adobe.com/illustrator/how-to/export-svg.html</link>
							<tag>Export high-quality, optimized SVG | from Help files for Adobe Illustrator</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://helpx.adobe.com/illustrator/using/saving-artwork.html#save_in_svg_format</link>
							<tag>Save in SVG format  | from Help files for Adobe Illustrator.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20121130224658/http://www.adobe.com/devnet/svg.html</link>
							<tag>Adobe SVG Developer Center | as of November 2012</tag>
							<comment>Link via Internet Archive</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to support for SVG in browsers and browser engines.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://caniuse.com/#cats=SVG</link>
							<tag>Can I Use. Analysis of browser support for SVG features</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.hongkiat.com/blog/test-svg-format-browser-engines/</link>
							<tag>Testing SVG Support Across Web Browser Engines [Case Study]</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_layout_engines_%28Scalable_Vector_Graphics%29</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia article on Comparison of Layout Engines (Scalable Vector Graphics)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3023.txt</link>
					<tag>XML Media Types</tag>
					<comment>Section 8.19 concerns SVG.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.color.org/</link>
					<tag>International Color Consortium</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.color.org/ICC1v42_2006-05.pdf</link>
					<tag>Specification ICC.1:2004-10, File Format for Color Profiles, Profile Version 4.2.0.0</tag>
					<comment>Normative reference for SVG 1.1 (Second edition).  First edition cited the 1998 ICC Spec. with a 1999 amendment.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to the early history of SVG.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.w3.org/Graphics/ScalableReq</link>
							<tag>
W3C Scalable Graphics Requirements</tag>
							<comment>1996 call for proposals.  This call brought in six proposals and led to the formation of the W3C group that developed SVG. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/WG/wiki/Secret_Origin_of_SVG</link>
							<tag>Secret Origin of SVG</tag>
							<comment>Describes proposals from 1998 that influenced the development of SVG.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pronom/fmt/92</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/92</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM from UK National Archives about SVG (1.1). PUID: fmt/92.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2078</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q2078</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about Scalable Vector Graphics, no version declared. Wikidata Title ID: Q2078.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
