<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000550" titleName="3D Tiles Archive File Format, Version 1.0" shortName="3D_Tiles_1.0 " xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>dataset</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>gis</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>cad/cam</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2023-01-03</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>3D Tiles Archive File Format, Version 1.0</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>gis formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>3D formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>geospatial formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>3D Tiles, standardized in the <a href="https://www.ogc.org/">Open Geospatial Consortium</a> (OGC) document <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a> is &quot;designed for streaming and rendering massive 3D geospatial content such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photogrammetry">Photogrammetry</a>, 3D Buildings, BIM/CAD [<a href="https://knowledge.autodesk.com/support/revit/learn-explore/caas/video/youtube/lesson/143344-courseId-100332.html">Building Information Modeling/Computer-Aided Design</a>], <a href="https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles/blob/main/specification/TileFormats/Instanced3DModel/README.md">Instanced Features</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Point_cloud">Point Clouds</a>. It defines a hierarchical data structure and a set of tile formats which deliver renderable content.&quot;  <a href="https://cesium.com/blog/2015/08/10/introducing-3d-tiles/">Cesium GS</a>, Inc. first introduced 3D Tiles in 2015 and shepherded its acceptance as an OGC Community Standard in 2019 with version 1.0.  The specification and supporting information is also held at the <a href="https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles">CesiumGS 3D Tiles GitHub public repository</a> which is updated more frequently than the OGC site.  Note that a new draft version of the specification is under development in 2022. <a href="https://portal.ogc.org/files/102132">3D Tiles, version 1.1</a>, with the OGC document number 22-025r2, is a &quot;Work Item Draft.&quot; In addition, development is also underway for 3D Tiles Next. See <a href="#notes">History</a> for more information.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Benefits of 3D Tiles</b>
			</p>
			<p>Some of the benefits of 3D Tiles, according to <a href="https://cesium.com/blog/2015/08/10/introducing-3d-tiles/">Cesium</a>, include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>interactive selection and styling which allows for individual model interaction such as highlighting on mouseover, or removing a 3D building;</li>
				<li>adaptive spatial subdivision which can subdivide a dataset, for example, based on the cost of rendering each model and the distribution of models, resulting in a balanced data structure;</li>
				<li>flexible refinement options allowing for both replacement refinement (in which visible map tiles are replaced with new higher-resolution map tiles as a viewer zooms in) and additive refinement (in which only new buildings are streamed when a viewer zooms in);</li>
				<li>full-precision geometry to avoid jittering artifacts;</li>
				<li>time-dynamic visualizations, such as of satellites and unmanned aerial vehicles (UAV or drone).</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				<b>Structure of 3D Tiles</b>
			</p>
			<p>The 3D Tiles specification defines a hierarchical data structure and a set of tile formats which deliver renderable content. In this context, a <i>tileset</i> is a set of <i>tiles</i> organized in a spatial data structure, the <i>tree</i>. A <i>tile</i> is defined as "a subset of a tileset containing a reference to renderable content and the metadata, such as the content’s bounding volume, which is used by a client to determine if the content is rendered." Each tileset is described by at least one tileset <fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink> file containing tileset metadata and a tree of tile objects. Tile objects can be one of four types of renderable data content as described in the <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">OGC specification</a>:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Batched 3D Model: Heterogeneous 3D models. E.g. textured terrain and surfaces, 3D building exteriors and interiors, massive models.</li>
				<li>Instanced 3D Model: 3D model instances... [According to section 10.2 of <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a>, instanced models or features &quot;refer to a large number of models, called instances, with slight variations. In the simplest case, the same tree model, for example, may be located—or instanced—in several places. Each instance references the same model and has per-instance properties, such as position. Using the core 3D Tiles spec language, each instance is a feature.
In addition to trees, Instanced 3D Model is useful for exterior features such as fire hydrants, sewer caps, lamps, and traffic lights, and for interior CAD features such as bolts, valves, and electrical outlets.&quot;] </li>
				<li>Point Cloud: Massive number of points [in which each point is defined by a position and by optional properties used to define its appearance, such as color and normal, as well as optional properties that define application-specific metadata. See section 10.3 of <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a> for more details.]</li>
				<li>Composite: Concatenate tiles of different formats into one tile.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Both the Batched 3D Model and Instanced 3D Model formats are built on <fddLink id="fdd000500">glTF (GL Transmission Format) 2.0</fddLink> in which the tile's model geometry and texture information is embedded as a glTF asset. Point Cloud does not embed glTF.</p>
			<p>Tiles are organized in a tree structure, following the concept of Hierarchical Level of Detail (HLOD) which means support for "decreasing the complexity of a 3D representation according to metrics such as object importance or distance from the tile to the observation point or camera position" for optimal rendering of spatial data.  <a href="https://cesium.com/blog/2015/08/10/introducing-3d-tiles/">Enabling HLOD</a> means that &quot;only visible tiles are streamed - and only those tiles which are most important for a given 3D view.&quot; Each tile has a bounding volume, an object defining a spatial extent completely enclosing its content. The tree has spatial coherence; the content for child tiles are completely inside the parent’s bounding volume.</p>
			<p>More granularly, each tile has a 28-byte header which contains the 4-byte ANSI string magic number of the tile object data type (b3dm, i3dm, pnts and cmpt respectively), version number of the tile data format, length of the tile and more. This header is immediately followed by the body section, composed of a Feature Table and Batch Table. [A Feature Table describes position and appearance properties required to render each feature in a tile whereas the Batch Table contains additional, application-specific properties for each feature which are not necessarily used for rendering.] For Batched 3D Model and Instanced 3D Model data, the embedded glTF asset comes next in the structure.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>3D Tiles is an open, streamable, optimized format designed for massive heterogeneous GIS datasets and standardized by the Open Geospatial Consortium.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase/>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000381</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>JSON</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>JSON (JavaScript Object Notation)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000500</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>glTF_2_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>glTF (GL Transmission Format) 2.0</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>glTF 2.0 is embedded for Batched 3D Model and Instanced 3D Model referenced data.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>3D Tiles version 1.1. Not described separately at this time because it is in OGC <a href="https://portal.ogc.org/files/102132">Work Item Draft</a> status as of this writing. However, some version updates are noted throughout the text. See <a href="#notes">History</a> for more information.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>3D Tiles Next. Not described separately at this time. Under development in the <a href="https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles/tree/main/next">Cesium 3D Tiles Next GitHub repository</a> which states that these features may be incorporated into 3D Tiles 2.0 in the future. The relationship between 3D Tiles Next and 3D Tiles version 1.1 is unclear. <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>None. </fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See the Recommended Formats Statement for the Library of Congress format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/geo-carto.html">GIS, Geospatial and Non-GIS Cartographic</a>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Fully documented, open format. The 3D Tiles specification for tilesets, associated tile formats, and the associated styling specification are open formats that are not dependent on any vendor-specific solution, technology, or products.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>3D Tiles version 1.1 is standardized via the <a href="https://www.ogc.org/">Open Geospatial Consortium</a> (OGC) document <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a>. This is supported by the <a href="https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles">CesiumGS 3D Tiles GitHub public repository</a> which is updated more frequently than the OGC site.
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>3D Tiles is widely adopted in 3D geospatial content applications including leading software, service, and data providers across industry and government, and by developers building end-user applications. <a href="https://cesium.com/platform/">Cesium</a>, a major open 3D platform provider and sponsor of the 3D Tiles specification work, is built on 3D Tiles integration. Their products support the Australian New South Wales <a href="https://nsw.digitaltwin.terria.io/">Spatial Digital Twin</a> project which incorporates 3D Tiles into 'web-mapping and visualizing data in 3D + time (the ability to look forward and back in time) to build a real-world ‘digital twin’ prototype" for use during <a href="https://algorithm.data61.csiro.au/nsw-digital-twin-to-inform-emergency-responders-this-bushfire-season/">emergencies</a> such as brush fires. This facilitates mapping the locations of telecommunication towers and assets which can enable emergency service organizations to better understand and protect these vital locations before and during an emergency event. Other adopters include <a href="https://www.revealtech.ai/">Reveal Technology's Farsight</a> software which, according to a August 1, 2022 <a href="https://cesium.com/blog/2022/08/01/farsight-strengthens-mission-planning-with-3d-tiles/">press release</a> uses 3D Tiles to enable Farsight users "to explore areas of interest in greater detail and complexity without slowing down operations. 3D Tiles support rapid map creation and interoperability with various viewers, enhancing situational awareness and collaboration." Adoption is across multiple domains including technology companies such as <a href="https://www.nearmap.com/us/en/aerial-view-blog/cesium-3d-tiles-helping-cities-stream-3d-models">Nearmap</a>, offering high-resolution aerial imager; <a href="https://www.safe.com/integrate/cesium-3d-tiles/">Safe Software</a>, creators of FME, a data integration platform; and <a href="https://documentation.maptiler.com/hc/en-us/articles/4414421667217-Custom-LIDAR-data-and-Cesium">MapTiler</a>, a mapping platform for developers; gaming industries such as <a href="https://venturebeat.com/games/epic-games-teams-up-with-cesium-to-bring-3d-geospatial-data-to-unreal/">Epic Gaming</a>, a leading interactive entertainment company and <a href="https://80.lv/articles/cesium-for-open-3d-engine-released/">O3DE</a>, a cross-platform 3D engine. </p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>None</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Well defined. OGC document <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a> describes Objects and Properties required to implement 3D Tiles. Conformance is relative to these elements and as partly expressed via the associated 3D Tiles JSON schema documents. See also <fddLink id="fdd000500">glTF (GL Transmission Format) 2.0</fddLink> and  <fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink>.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Limited descriptive metadata. See also <fddLink id="fdd000500">glTF (GL Transmission Format) 2.0</fddLink> and  <fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink>. </fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None beyond availability of supporting software.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None known although the <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip">IANA registration for vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip</a> states that &quot;because of the various content types that can be embedded in 3tz container files, application/vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip may describe content that poses security implications beyond those noted here. However, only in cases where the processor recognizes and processes the additional content, or where further processing of that content is dispatched to other processors, would security issues potentially arise. In such cases, matters of security would fall outside the domain of this registration document.
The content types may or may not provide integrity or confidentiality protection, but the vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip format does not.&quot;</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:gisQF>
			<fdd:normalGIS>According to the OGC specification, &quot;3D Tiles uses a right-handed Cartesian coordinate system in which the cross product of x and y yields z. 3D Tiles defines the z axis as up for local Cartesian coordinate systems. A tileset’s global coordinate system will often be in a WGS 84 earth-centered, earth-fixed (ECEF) reference frame (EPSG 4979), but it doesn’t have to be, e.g., a power plant may be defined fully in its local coordinate system for use with a modeling tool without a geospatial context.
An additional tile transform may be applied to transform a tile’s local coordinate system to the parent tile’s coordinate system.
The region bounding volume specifies bounds using a geographic coordinate system (latitude, longitude, height), specifically EPSG 4979.&quot;
</fdd:normalGIS>
			<fdd:metadataGIS>3D Tiles has very limited support for metadata as recommended by <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/53798.html">ISO 19115-1:2014
Geographic information — Metadata — Part 1: Fundamentals</a> or <a href="https://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/iso-standards">FDGC ISO Geospatial Metadata Standard</a>.
3D Tiles is mentioned in the <a href="https://www.fgdc.gov/standards/monthlyStandardsUpdate/2016-08/2016-08-standardsupdate.pdf">FGDC.gov Standards Update</a>, Aug 2016, but it announces 3D Tiles as the first new “community standard” developed by communities external to the OCG that OGC members wish to bring into the OGC process, with no information about supported GIS metadata.
</fdd:metadataGIS>
			<fdd:grids>3D Tiles enables uniform, non-uniform, and overlapping grids by supporting an arbitrary number of child tiles. 
3D Tiles takes advantage of empty tiles: those tiles that have a bounding volume, but no content. Since a tile’s content property does not need to be defined, empty non-leaf tiles can be used to accelerate non-uniform grids with hierarchical culling. This essentially creates a quadtree or octree without hierarchical levels of detail (HLOD).
</fdd:grids>
			<fdd:beyondGIS>None.</fdd:beyondGIS>
		</fdd:gisQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>json</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Tileset files and tileset style files use the json file extension. Tile content files use the file type and MIME format specific to their tile format specification. Explicit file extensions are optional. Valid implementations may ignore it and identify a content’s format by the magic field in its header. See <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>b3dm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Optional file extension value for Batched 3D Model tiles. Explicit file extensions are optional. Valid implementations may ignore it and identify a content’s format by the magic field in its header.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>i3dm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Optional file extension value for Instanced 3D models tiles. Explicit file extensions are optional. Valid implementations may ignore it and identify a content’s format by the magic field in its header.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>pnts</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Optional file extension value for Point Cloud tiles. Explicit file extensions are optional. Valid implementations may ignore it and identify a content’s format by the magic field in its header.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>cmpt</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Optional file extension value for Composite tiles. Explicit file extensions are optional. Valid implementations may ignore it and identify a content’s format by the magic field in its header.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/json</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Tileset files and tileset style files use application/json. See <fddLink id="fdd000381">JSON</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/octet-stream</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Media type for all tile content types</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip">IANA registration</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>b3dm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>4-byte ANSI string magic number in the tile header
for Batched 3D Model tiles. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>i3dm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>4-byte ANSI string magic number in the tile header
for Instanced 3D model tiles. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>pnts</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>4-byte ANSI string magic number in the tile header
for Point Cloud tiles. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>cmpt</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>4-byte ANSI string magic number in the tile header
for Composite tiles. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 50 4B 03 04</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: P K etx eot</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip">IANA registration</a> which lists the magic number for <fddLink id="fdd000354">ZIP</fddLink>. Not included in <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a>. <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Mac OS file type</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>ZIP</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip">IANA registration</a> but not included in <a href="https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">18-053r2</a>. <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM has no corresponding entry as of January 2023.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata has no corresponding entry as of January 2023.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>Cesium introduced the 3D Tiles initiative in 2015 at <a href="https://www.siggraph.org/about/">SIGGRAPH</a>, a special interest group of the <a href="https://www.acm.org/">Association for Computing Machinery</a> (ACM). 3D Tiles gained traction and earned several adoptions, leading to Cesium submitting 3D tiles for an OGC vote to start the Community Standard in 2016. The OGC document 18-053r2 Version 1.0 3D Tiles Specification 1.0 is the current standard, which was submitted in 2018 and published in 2019.</p>
			<p>While <a href="https://portal.ogc.org/files/102132">3D Tiles, version 1.1</a>, with the OGC document number 22-025r2, is a &quot;Work Item Draft.&quot; and still under development as of this writing in late 2022, there are some potentially impactful changes in the draft. Most notable is the sunsetting of the four tiles types from version 1.0 (Batched 3D Model [b3dm]; Instanced 3D Model [i3dm]; Point Cloud [pnts]; Composite [cmpt]) - all of which are superseded by the <a href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF">glTF Tile Format</a> (see also <fddLink id="fdd000500">glTF (GL Transmission Format) 2.0</fddLink>).  Other significant changes to version 1.1 include updating of the Annexes with Annex A describing the Objects and Properties required to implement 3D Tiles, Annex B defining the 3D Tiles JSON Schema and more. A list of changes is documented in the <a href="https://portal.ogc.org/files/100660">3D Tiles v1.1 Community Standard Justification document</a> (PDF download). See also <a href="https://www.ogc.org/standards/requests/245">Public comment requested: proposed v1.1 update to 3D Tiles Community Standard</a> from OGC.</p>
			<p>In addition, 3D Tiles Next is under development in the <a href="https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles/tree/main/next">Cesium 3D Tiles Next GitHub repository</a>, which states that these features may be incorporated into 3D Tiles 2.0 in the future. The relationship between 3D Tiles Next and 3D Tiles version 1.1 is unclear. <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html</link>
					<tag>Open Geospatial Consortium 3D Tiles Specification 1.0</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Open Geospatial Consortium</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ogc.org/</link>
							<tag>Open Geospatial Consortium homepage</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.ogc.org/files/102132</link>
							<tag>Open Geospatial Consortium DRAFT 3D Tiles Specification 1.1</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://portal.ogc.org/files/100660</link>
							<tag>Open Geospatial Consortium Community Standard Justification: 22-006</tag>
							<comment>3D Tiles 1.1 Community Standard Justification</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ogc.org/standards/requests/245</link>
							<tag>Open Geospatial Consortium Public comment requested: proposed v1.1 update to 3D Tiles Community Standard</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Cesium</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://cesium.com/blog/2015/08/10/introducing-3d-tiles/</link>
							<tag>Introducing 3D Tiles - blog post from August 15, 2015</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://cesium.com/platform/</link>
							<tag>The Cesium Platform</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles</link>
							<tag>CesiumGS 3D Tiles GitHub repo</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles/blob/main/specification/TileFormats/Instanced3DModel/README.md</link>
							<tag>CesiumGS 3D Tiles GitHub repo: Instanced3DModel/README.md</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://github.com/CesiumGS/3d-tiles/tree/main/next</link>
							<tag>CesiumGS 3D Tiles Next GitHub repo</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://cesium.com/blog/2022/08/01/farsight-strengthens-mission-planning-with-3d-tiles/</link>
							<tag>Blog post: Farsight Strengthens Mission Planning with 3D Tiles. August 1, 2022</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photogrammetry</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry on Photogrammetry</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Point_cloud</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry on Point Cloud</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://knowledge.autodesk.com/support/revit/learn-explore/caas/video/youtube/lesson/143344-courseId-100332.html</link>
					<tag>Autodesk: Understanding the Difference Between BIM and CAD</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://nsw.digitaltwin.terria.io/</link>
					<tag>New South Wales Spatial Digital Twin</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://algorithm.data61.csiro.au/nsw-digital-twin-to-inform-emergency-responders-this-bushfire-season/</link>
					<tag>NSW Digital Twin to inform emergency responders this bushfire season</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.revealtech.ai/</link>
					<tag>About Reveal</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.nearmap.com/us/en/aerial-view-blog/cesium-3d-tiles-helping-cities-stream-3d-models</link>
					<tag>Nearmap blog post: Cesium 3D Tiles, Helping Cities Stream 3D Models. May 2019</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.safe.com/integrate/cesium-3d-tiles/</link>
					<tag>Safe Software: Integrate Cesium 3D Tiles Using FME</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://documentation.maptiler.com/hc/en-us/articles/4414421667217-Custom-LIDAR-data-and-Cesium</link>
					<tag>Map Tiler: Custom LIDAR data and Cesium</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://venturebeat.com/games/epic-games-teams-up-with-cesium-to-bring-3d-geospatial-data-to-unreal/</link>
					<tag>Games Beat Summit blog post: Epic Games teams up with Cesium to bring 3D geospatial data to Unreal. March 30, 2021</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://80.lv/articles/cesium-for-open-3d-engine-released/</link>
					<tag>Solv blog post: Cesium for Open 3D Engine Released. Feb 17, 2022</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip</link>
					<tag>IANA registration for application vnd.maxar.archive.3tz+zip. </tag>
					<comment>Registered 2022-02-01, last updated 2022-02-01</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/53798.html</link>
					<tag>ISO 19115-1:2014
Geographic information — Metadata — Part 1: Fundamentals</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/iso-standards</link>
					<tag>FDGC ISO Geospatial Metadata Standard </tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.fgdc.gov/standards/monthlyStandardsUpdate/2016-08/2016-08-standardsupdate.pdf</link>
					<tag>FDGC Federal Geographic Data Committee Standards Update
August 2016</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.acm.org/</link>
					<tag>Association for Computing Machinery</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.siggraph.org/about/</link>
					<tag>About ACM SIGGRAPH</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF</link>
					<tag>Khronos Group glTF GitHub repo</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
