<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000398" titleName="XSLX (Office Open XML), ISO 29500:2008-2012, ECMA-376, Editions 1-4" shortName="XSLX/OOXML_2012" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-0.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>spreadsheet</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2014-10-26</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>XSLX, (Office Open XML, Spreadsheet ML) ISO 29500:2008-2012, also ECMA-376, Editions 1-4.</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>dataset formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>markup languages</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The Open Office XML-based spreadsheet format using .xslx as a file extension has been the default format produced for new documents by versions of Microsoft Excel since Excel 2007.  The format was designed to be equivalent to the binary .xls format produced by earlier versions of Microsoft Excel.   For convenience, this format description uses XSLX to identify the corresponding format.  The primary content of a XSLX file is marked up in SpreadsheetML, which is specified in parts 1 and 4 of <i>ISO/IEC 29500, Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats (OOXML)</i>.  This description focuses on the specification in <i>ISO/IEC 29500:2012</i> and represents the format variant known as &quot;Transitional.&quot;  Although editions of ISO 29500 were published in 2008 and 2011, the specification has had very few changes other than clarifications and corrections to match actual usage in documents since SperadsheetML was first standardized in ECMA-376, Part 1 in 2006, this description can be read as applying to all SpreadsheetML versions published by ECMA International and by ISO/IEC through 2012.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for more detail on the chronological versions and minor differences.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>A format for spreadsheet documents in the Open Office XML (ISO 29500) format family, developed originally by Microsoft and used as the default format used by Microsoft Excel 2007 and later versions.  Specified in parts 1 and 4 of ISO/IEC 29500, Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- Office Open XML File Formats (OOXML).</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Can be used in any production phase: for creating documents (initial state): for editing and review (middle-state); and for final distribution.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000395</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>OOXML Family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>OOXML (ISO/IEC 29500) Format Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000363</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>OPC/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Open Packaging Conventions (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-2:2008-2012</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000396</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName> MCE/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-3:2008-2012, ECMA-376, Editions 1-4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000075</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>TBD</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>TBD</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>International open standard.  Maintained by ISO/IEC JTC1 SC34/WG4.  Originated by Microsoft Corporation and first standardized through ECMA International in 2006.  Approval as ISO/IEC 29500 was in 2008.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>
				<i>ISO/IEC 29500-1, Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Part 1: Fundamentals and Markup Language Reference</i>   and <i>ISO/IEC 29500-4, Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Part 4: Transitional Migration Features</i>.  Latest version (dated 2012 as of August 2014) is available from <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/">ISO/IEC Publicly Available Standards</a>.</p>
			<p>All editions of the OOXML standards as published by ECMA are available from <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376: Office Open XML File Formats</a>.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for version chronology.</p>
			<p>The Transitional variant of DOCX is specified by applying the differences described in Part 4 (Transitional Migration Features) to the specification in Part 1. Part 4 cannot be read without detailed reference to subclauses in Part 1.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>DOCX was originally developed by Microsoft as an XML-based format to replace the proprietary binary format that uses the .doc file extension.</p>
			<p>
				<a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>MORE TO COME</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>The specification originated from Microsoft Corporation. Current and future versions of ISO/IEC 29500 and ECMA-376 are covered by Microsoft&apos;s <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/openspecifications/en/us/programs/osp/default.aspx">Open Specification Promise</a>, whereby Microsoft &quot;irrevocably promises&quot; not to assert any claims against those making, using, and selling implementations of any specification covered by the promise (so long as those accepting the promise refrain from suing Microsoft for patent infringement in relation to Microsoft&apos;s implementation of the covered specification).</p>
			<p>Features introduced into DOCX through the MCE mechanism may be subject to patent protection.  However, Microsoft&apos;s <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/openspecifications/en/us/programs/interop/interoperability-principles/default.aspx">interoperability principles</a> indicate &quot;Microsoft will also make available a list of any of its patents that cover any extensions, and will make available patent licenses on reasonable and non-discriminatory terms.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>For transparency of the package containing the constituent parts of the DOCX file, see <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>Transparency of DOCX parts TBD</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>For basic self-documentation of the package containing the constituent parts of the DOCX file, see <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>Self-doc specific to DOCX TBD</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>Good. TBD.  Full support for Unicode and bi-directional and vertical text.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>Good through use of Styles. TBD</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>Good.  TBD</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>
				<p>ISO/IEC 29500 defines Office Math Markup Language, a mathematical markup language that can be embedded in WordprocessingML. Microsoft has published XSLT transformations to convert between MathML and Office Math Markup Language.  Key reasons given for not using MathML directly in DOCX include:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Word supports equations embedded within paragraphs and MathML&apos;s presentation markup is designed for independent presentation of mathematical expressions.</li>
					<li>Use of MathML would not allow tracking for changes within mathematical expressions.</li>
				</ul>
			</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>TBD.  Lots of stuff: tracked revisions, comment threads and other annotations, content controls, etc. Supports embedding of other OOXML content (including spreadsheetML, presentationML,  DrawingML, and Office Mathematical Markup Language).  Supports embedding of media objects (in binary formats) and links to external media objects, such as images, audio, or video. </fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>docx</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>XML namespace declaration</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>This namespace declaration is for the Transitional variant of DOCX.  It occurs in the mandatory Main Document part of a DOCX file (package) with the name <i>/word/document.xml</i> and is mapped to the prefix <i>w</i>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Other</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Target=&quot;word/document.xml&quot;</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Will occur in the top-level Relationships part (<i>\_rels\.rels</i> part in an OPC package in the &lt;Relationships&gt; element of a Transitional DOCX file.  It will be the target of a relationship of type <i>http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/officeDocument/2006/relationships/officeDocument</i>.  See root namespace and source relationship for Main Document Part in ISO/IEC 29500-4:2012, ยง9.1.10, which refers to ISO/IEC 29500-1:2012, ยง11.3.10.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general/>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The original DOCX specification was published in ECMA-376, Part 1 in 2006.  Between then and 2012, the main change to the specification for WordprocessingML has been the split between WML Strict (as defined in Part 1) and WML Transitional (as defined in Part 4 in conjunction with Part 1).  Editions of ISO/IEC 29500 and ECMA 376 between 2008 and 2012 related to wordprocessingML have primarily been corrections and clarifications.  The chronology of editions specifying DOCX/OOXML_2012 is:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ECMA-376, Part 1, 1st edition (December 2006)</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500-1:2008; ISO/IEC 29500-4:2008</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, Part 1, 2nd edition (December 2008) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-1:2008]; ECMA-376, Part 4, 2nd edition (December 2008) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-4:2008]</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500-1:2011; ISO/IEC 29500-4:2011</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, Part 1, 3rd edition (June 2011) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-1:2011]; ECMA-376, Part 4, 3rd edition (June 2011) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-4:2011]
</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500-1:2012; ISO/IEC 29500-4:2012</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, Part 1, 4th edition (December 2012) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-1:2012]; ECMA-376, Part 4, 4th edition (December 2012) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-4:2012]</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The latest versions of ISO/IEC 29500 are made available at no charge from ISO. The formal titles of the two parts that together specify the Transitional variant of DOCX are <i>Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Part 1:  Fundamentals and Markup Language Reference</i> (which specifies the Strict variant) and <i>Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Part 4: Transitional Migration Features</i>.  The schemas for the Transitional variant described here are available as <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061798_ISO_IEC_29500-4_2012_Electronic_inserts.zip">electronic inserts</a> to Part 4.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/index.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC Publicly Available Standards</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061750_ISO_IEC_29500-1_2012.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-1:2012, specification document</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061798_ISO_IEC_29500-4_2012.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-4:2012, specification document</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061798_ISO_IEC_29500-4_2012_Electronic_inserts.zip</link>
							<tag>Schemas in W3C XML Schema language and in RELAX NG for the Transitional variant of DOCX.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm</link>
					<tag>ECMA-376: Office Open XML File Formats</tag>
					<comment>Provides access to all chronological published versions.  </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/412</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/412</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM from UK National Archives about DOCX.   PUID: fmt/412</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document</link>
					<tag>IANA registration for MIME media type for DOCX (wordprocessingML) files.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Microsoft provides various documentation pages related to DOCX.  Much of this documentation is aimed at programmers writing applications that manipulate WordprocessingML markup directly, perhaps using the Open XML SDK.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/bb448854.aspx</link>
							<tag>Welcome to the Open XML SDK 2.5 for Office</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/aa212812.aspx</link>
							<tag>Overview of WordprocessingML [Word 2003 XML Reference]</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=101</link>
							<tag>Office 2003: XML Reference Schemas</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/gg278308.aspx</link>
							<tag>Structure of a WordprocessingML document (Open XML SDK)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/gg278327.aspx</link>
							<tag>Working with WordprocessingML Documents</tag>
							<comment>Introduces basic topics for working with WordprocessingML (.docx) files through program code.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/ff433640.aspx</link>
							<tag>Using Open XML WordprocessingML Documents as Data Sources</tag>
							<comment>Introduces &quot;content controls&quot; and how their use to define structured areas within a document can facilitate tasks that involve entering text or data in a form for convenient later extraction.  </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/ff629396.aspx</link>
							<tag>Identifying Open XML Word-Processing Documents with Tracked Revisions</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://blogs.msdn.com/b/murrays/archive/2006/10/07/mathml-and-ecma-math-_2800_omml_2900_-.aspx</link>
							<tag>MathML and Ecma Math (OMML)</tag>
							<comment>By Murray Sargent in his Math in Office blog.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.microsoft.com/openspecifications/en/us/programs/interop/interoperability-principles/default.aspx</link>
							<tag>Interoperability Principles</tag>
							<comment>Indicates that Microsoft will document extensions to standards implemented in its high-volume products on its website.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/news/presskits/eu-msft/docs/microsoftinteroperabilityundertaking16dec2009.doc</link>
							<tag>Microsoft Interoperability Undertaking, Dec 16, 2009</tag>
							<comment>Public undertaking to address competition concerns from the European Commission.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c045245_ISO_IEC_TR_29166_2011.zip</link>
					<tag>ISO/IEC TR 29166:2011 Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- Guidelines for translation between ISO/IEC 26300 and ISO/IEC 29500 document formats</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
