<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000526" titleName="High Efficiency Image File Format, HEIC/HEIX brands" shortName="HEIF_HEIC" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-11-02</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>High Efficiency Image File Format, HEVC compression encoding, HEIC/HEIX brands</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>raster image formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The High Efficiency Image File Format (<fddLink id="fdd000525">HEIF</fddLink>) is an international standard defined by MPEG-H Part 12 (ISO/IEC 23008-12), first published by ISO in 2017.  It is designed as a container for photographic images in any image encoding. HEIF is a special case of the general <fddLink id="fdd000079">ISO_BMFF</fddLink> format, in which all data is encapsulated in typed boxes, with a mandatory <i>ftyp</i> box that is used to indicate particular file types. The initial specification for HEIF provided usage details for three compression schemes, the widely supported <fddLink id="fdd000017">JPEG</fddLink> encoding for still raster images and two video encodings that are also applicable to still image items, namely Advanced Video Coding (<fddLink id="fdd000081">AVC</fddLink>, aka MPEG-4, Part 10 and H.264) and High Efficiency Video Coding (<fddLink id="fdd000530">HEVC</fddLink> aka MPEG-H Part 2 and H.265).  This format description focuses on a subset of HEIF image types using HEVC encoding, with an emphasis on what the compilers of this resource have learned about implementations in cameras and mobile devices as of November 2020.</p>
			<p>The ISO_BMFF mechanism for distinguishing among file types is based on 4-character codes known as <i>brands</i>; brands are registered at <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">mp4ra.org</a>. An ISO_BMFF file type is defined by the major brand, which comes first in its <i>ftyp</i> box. Also in the <i>ftyp</i> box is a list of brand codes identifying brands which with the file is declared to be compatible.  This format description is primarily for HEIF files with the brands <i>heic</i> or <i>heix</i> either as major brand or a compatible brand.  As of November 2020, <i>heic</i> is the most widely used brand for HEIF files with HEVC encoding because it is the variant chosen by Apple as the default format in iPhones, starting with the iPhone 7 in 2017.  Apple uses the .heic extension (and pronounces it &quot;heek&quot; to rhyme with &quot;leek&quot;) for such image files, which are sometimes referred to as HEIC files.  HEIF files with a subset of encoding features from HEVC are used for image capture in supported devices and versions of Apple&apos;s iOS (starting with iPhone 7 and iOS 11) when the default &quot;High Efficiency&quot; is selected as the storage option in the iPhone&apos;s Format/Camera Capture settings. When the alternative &quot;Most Compatible&quot; option is chosen, JPEG is used. See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for more details on Apple&apos;s use of the format for files generated by cameras in its mobile devices, based largely on details provided at Apple&apos;s WWDC 2017 developer conference.  Some high-end Android phones, for example the <a href="https://thedroidguy.com/reduce-file-size-of-photos-and-videos-on-galaxy-s10-1114198">Samsung Galaxy S10</a> series, when used with a <a href="https://www.androidcentral.com/android-p-features-we-love-hdr-and-heif-support">new enough version of Android</a>, also generate .heic files.  In 2020, Canon and Sony brought out cameras which generate photos with the <i>heix</i> brand and the extension .hif.   The key distinction between the <i>heic</i> and <i>heix</i> brands is that <i>heic</i> should only be used for the two most basic profiles of HEVC, namely Main or Main Still Picture; these profiles are limited to 8-bit color and 4:2:0 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chroma_subsampling">chroma subsampling</a>.  <i>heix</i> is primarily applied when the profile used extends either the bit-depth to 10 bits or more per color channel, or chroma subsampling to 4:2:2 or 4:4:4.  For more details on brands associated with HEVC encoding in HEIF files, and examples of how the brands are represented in some example files, see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
			<p>A paper titled <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275836640_Objective_Performance_Evaluation_of_the_HEVC_Main_Still_Picture_Profile">Objective Performance Evaluation of the HEVC Main Still Picture Profile</a>, presented at the May 2015 IEEE conference on Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology, analyzed and discussed the
compression performance of the HEVC Main Still Picture profile in comparison to the
intra-only coding mode of the <fddLink id="fdd000215">H.264/MPEG-4 AVC High
Profile</fddLink>, the proprietary video coding schemes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">VP8</a>
and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP9">VP9</a>, and coding
technologies used specifically in the still image application domain, such as
<fddLink id="fdd000140">JPEG 2000 lossy compression</fddLink> (using the irreversible floating point 9-7 wavelet transform), <fddLink id="fdd000244">JPEG XR</fddLink>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebP">WebP</a>, and <fddLink id="fdd000149">Baseline JPEG</fddLink>.  The objective performance measures were based on the peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR) and associated average bit-rate savings. The experimental
results clearly show the superior performance of HEVC Main Still Picture Profile with
average bit-rate savings ranging from 10% relative to VP9 up
to 44% relative to Baseline JPEG.  The results from a later study comparing still image coding using HEVC in the HEIF format with the JPEG 2000 standard by a team from Nokia was reported at the 2016 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP 2016) in a paper titled <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7532321">HEVC still image coding and high efficiency image file format</a>.  Based on the test set of images (with 16 bits per color channel in an ASCII-based uncompressed format) provided for the ICIP 2016 image compression grand challenge, HEVC still image compression was found to be superior to JPEG 2000, providing on average about 25% bitrate reduction for the same quality (measured by peak signal-to-noise ratio, PSNR).  The paper includes a useful summary of the HEVC features particularly applicable to still image encoding.  Table I in the paper lists the following important picture characteristics from HEVC as defined in <a href="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/12455">edition 3 of ITU-T H.265 (2015)</a> for supporting &quot;high dynamic range&quot; (HDR) and &quot;wide color gamut&quot; (WCG).  These characteristics are listed below, supplemented by information from elsewhere in the paper:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Support for several color gamut systems, color primaries, transfer characteristics, and color conversion matrices</li>
				<li>8, 10, 12, 16-bit color.  Improved &quot;intra&quot; (within image) coding methods compared to AVC. These methods can model more accurately different directional structures and can smooth regions that have gradually changing sample values. They help avoid introduction of artificial edges with potential blocking effects.  The HEVC standard includes specific profiles for still images.</li>
				<li>Support for several chroma subsampling patterns: 4:2:0, 4:2:2, and 4:4:4.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>HEVC features highlighted in the paper from Nokia mentioned above as supporting advanced imaging use cases include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>Tiles</b>: Support parallelized encoding and decoding of rectangular subsets of an image partioned according to a grid.  Apple, Canon, and Sony all take advantage of this feature. Apple captures in 512 x 512 pixel tiles for high performance when panning and zooming.  See <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-511/?time=1457">demo</a> from presentation at Apple&apos;s WWDC 2017 on &quot;Working with HEIF and HEVC.&quot;</li>
				<li>
					<b>&quot;Inter&quot; prediction</b>: Takes advantage of similarity from one picture to the next in a set of images.  Helpful in many multi-picture use cases, such as focal and exposure stacks, image bursts, &quot;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinemagraph">cinemagraphs</a>&quot; (and similar animated images, known by a variety of names, including &quot;Live Photo&quot; from Apple and &quot;Motion Photos&quot; from Samsung).</li>
				<li>
					<b>Auxiliary pictures</b>: HEVC has standardized flags, codes, and supplemental enhancement information (SEI) message payloads (three mechanisms sometimes referred to together as &quot;metadata signalling&quot;) for some categories of auxiliary images, in particular for transparency (alpha) planes, depth maps, and overlays.  Overlays are covered in Annexes D and F of the HEVC specification.  The details for alpha planes and depth maps are in Annex B.2.4 of the HEIF specification and Annexes D, F, and G of the HEVC specification.  For a demo of how a depth map can be used to edit an image, see <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-511/?time=1363">section</a> from presentation at Apple&apos;s WWDC 2017 on &quot;Working with HEIF and HEVC.&quot;</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Among the features of the HEIF format that support advanced imaging use cases are:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>The ability to include any number of still images in a HEIF file.  They can be categorized as master images, thumbnails, auxiliary images, etc.  If tiles are used, each tile is a separate image, flagged as &quot;hidden&quot; and associated with a derived image with type <i>grid</i> that assembles all the tiles into a single image for display.  A HEIF file can incorporate an image sequence, that may simply specify an order, but may be associated with timing intended to guide display.  The track feature of ISO_BMFF is used to carry information about an image sequence.  A HEIF file may also hold a collection of images with no implied order.  Descriptive metadata can be applied to individual images and to the collection or sequence as a whole.  EXIF metadata can be attached to every image. HEIF also supports any XMP-based metadata schema, and can be extended to handle other metadata schemas or schema languages.</li>
				<li>The original coded images in a file can be left alone, while a new image is derived by applying a transformation.  This is known as non-destructive editing.  HEIF specifies generic structures to define derivations and specifies a basic set of simple derivations relevant to all image encodings.  For example, a composite HDR image derived from a set of exposure-bracketed individual images, will have references of type <i>base</i> to each of the source images.  Other specified types for derived images include <i>grid</i>, for assembling tiles and <i>iovl</i>, for assembling layered overlays.  A slightly different mechanism is used for images derived by cropping, rotation, or mirroring.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>a format that uses HEVC (High Efficiency Video Coding) for image compression in a HEIF (High Efficiency Image File Format) container.  Adopted by Apple as its default internal photo format starting with IPhone 7.  Built-in format option for selected Canon and Sony cameras since 2020. Supported for selected Android phones with high-end camera systems since Android Pie (2018).</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>May be applied in initial-state picture creation in cameras or used for middle- and final-state archiving or end-user delivery.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000525</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HEIF</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>High Efficiency Image File (HEIF) Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000530</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HEVC</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>High Efficiency Video Coding (HEVC) Family, H.265, MPEG-H Part 2</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress has a handful of images in the HEIC format (a subtype of the HEIF format) in its digital storage system.  These are likely to have been acquired in the course of archiving websites.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>Neither HEIC nor any of other HEIF subtypes are listed in the Library of Congress <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/stillimg.html#photodigital">Recommended Formats Statement (RFS) for Still Image</a> content in its collections.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>International standard, fully disclosed. Developed and maintained under the auspices of the Motion Picture Experts Group (MPEG), which functioned as ISO/IEC JTC1/SC 29/WG11.  Depends on HEIF (High Efficiency Image File Format) standard (<a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/66067.html">ISO/IEC 23008-12</a>) for its file format structure and HEVC (High Efficiency Video Coding, aka H.265, ITU ) standard (<a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/75484.html">ISO/IEC 23008-2</a>) for its compression encoding. After re-organization of SC 29 in 2020, maintenance of the HEVC standard will be by a new working group WG5 (MPEG Joint Video Coding Team(s) with ITU-T SG 16).</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>For HEIF:  MPEG-H Part 12.  See <a href="https://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c066067_ISO_IEC_23008-12_2017.zip">ISO/IEC 23008-12:2017</a> from the ITTF list of publicly available standards for full text and <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/66067.html">ISO/IEC 23008-12:2017 catalog record and preview</a> for the initial specification. </p>
			<p>For HEVC:  MPEG-H Part 2, aka ITU H.265: High efficiency video coding.  See <a href="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.265-201911-I/en">ITU Recommendation H.265 (approved 11/2019)</a> for full text of Version 7.  See <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/75484.html">ISO/IEC 23008-2:2020 catalog record and preview</a> for the equivalent ISO/IEC specification published in August 2020.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The HEIF file format has been adopted as an in-camera format for a number of cameras and mobile devices.  In June 2017, Apple announced the adoption of HEIF at its WWDC 2017 developer conference.  Built-in support for the format was introduced for capture on new iOS 11 phones.  Qualcomm announced its first system on a chip (SOC) supporting HEIF in late 2018.  See <a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/qualcomm-snapdragon-855-chip-gives-android-phones-iphone-photo-packing-ability/">With Snapdragon 855 chip, Android phones get iPhone&apos;s photo-packing ability</a>.  In January 2020, Qualcomm introduced the lower-end SOC, <a href="https://www.qualcomm.com/media/documents/files/qualcomm-snapdragon-662-mobile-platform-product-brief.pdf">Snapdragon 662</a>, which also supports HEIF.  Samsung introduced support for HEIF capture in its Galaxy S10 phones in 2019.  See <a href="https://r2.community.samsung.com/t5/Galaxy-S/Here-s-how-to-make-Galaxy-S10-camera-photos-take-less-storage/td-p/1304386">Here’s how to make Galaxy S10 camera photos take less storage space</a>. Canon&apos;s <a href="https://www.usa.canon.com/internet/portal/us/home/explore/product-showcases/cameras-and-lenses/1dx-mark-iii">EOS-1D X Mark III</a> camera, introduced in January 2020, has the option of using HEIF internally as do the EOS <a href="https://www.canon.co.uk/cameras/eos-r5/specifications/">R5</a> and <a href="https://www.canon.co.uk/cameras/eos-r5/specifications/">R6</a> cameras, introduced later in 2020.  See <a href="https://camerajabber.com/tutorials/how-to-shoot-in-heif-format-on-canon-cameras/">HOW TO... shoot in HEIF format on Canon cameras</a> from Camera Jabber.  Sony supports HEIF with HEVC encoding for still images captured with its <a href="https://www.sony.com/electronics/interchangeable-lens-cameras/ilce-7sm3/specifications">A7S III movie camera</a>.  Both Canon and Sony are using the .hif extension for their HEIF images and offering options for 8-bit and 10-bit color as well as other advanced options.</p>
			<p>The first versions of Apple&apos;s operating systems to support viewing, editing, and conversion of HEIC images were iOS 11 and Mac OS 10.13 (High Sierra), released in 2017.  See <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT207022">Using HEIF or HEVC media on Apple devices</a>.   Support is available in Windows 10, but not without an explicit choice to add codecs. See <a href="https://www.technipages.com/windows-10-add-support-for-heic-to-photos-app">Windows 10: Add Support for HEIC to Photos App</a>.  In <a href="https://www.irfanview.com/faq.htm#PAGE6">Frequently Asked Questions about IrfanView</a>, the answer to &quot;How to load  HEIC files in IrfanView? &quot; offers equivalent advice.  <a href="https://medium.com/@hritikchaudhary/heif-heic-support-for-linux-ubuntu-quick-guide-9a70f4d29352">HEIF (.HEIC) Image Support for Linux/Ubuntu [quick guide]</a> describes a mechanism for handling HEIF/HEIC files in Linux/Ubuntu, using the <a href="https://packages.debian.org/unstable/graphics/heif-gdk-pixbuf">heif-gdk-pixbuf</a> package.</p>
			<p>Mac OS applications that have built-in support for .heic files, include <a href="https://www.apple.com/macos/photos/">Photos</a>, <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/preview/view-pdfs-and-images-prvw11470/mac">Preview</a> and <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/view-and-edit-files-with-quick-look-mh14119/10.15/mac/10.15">Quick Look</a>.  These applications can render/display images that have characteristics beyond those found in Apple-generated images (see <a href="#notes">Notes below</a>), for example, images with 10-bit color from Canon and Sony cameras.   For support in third party image editing software, see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Efficiency_Image_File_Format#Image_editing_software">Wikipedia entry for HEIF</a>, bearing in mind that use of such software in Mac OS later than High Sierra (10.13) will typically work as it comes, but for Windows applications it is typically necessary to install the codec extensions mentioned in the previous paragraph.  For example, Adobe Photoshop can open .heic files on recent Mac OS versions and hardware, but not on Windows 10 without the codec extensions.</p>
			<p>As of writing, in November 2020, there is no browser-based support for HEIF images; see <a href="https://caniuse.com/heif">https://caniuse.com/heif</a>.  Hence, many photographs captured in HEIF format are converted into <fddLink id="fdd000017">JPEG</fddLink> encoding in <fddLink id="fdd000018">JFIF</fddLink> files for use on the web or as email attachments, often without the user who took the photo realizing the conversion has happened. For example, the option to email pictures using the Photos app on an iPhone sends JPEG/JFIF files  with <fddLink id="fdd000147">EXIF</fddLink> metadata in the size chosen by the user.</p>
			<p>For software libraries for the HEIF/HEVC combination of file format and encoding, see <fddLink id="fdd000525">HEIF</fddLink>.  Most software that says it supports the HEIF format for reading/decoding or writing/encoding supports some profile(s) of the HEVC (H.265) encoding standard, typically including the profiles used in Apple-generated .heic files.</p>
			<p>Canon and Sony provide support for editing their own variants of HEIF/HEVC combination.  See <a href="https://support.usa.canon.com/kb/index?page=content&amp;id=ART176556&amp;cat=CAMCORDERS&amp;actp=LIST&amp;showDraft=false">Working with files saved in HEVC format</a> from Canon with information on use of its Digital Photo Professional (DPP) software with .hif images generated by Canon cameras.  Sony provides a <a href="https://support.d-imaging.sony.co.jp/app/heif/en/">HEIF Converter</a> tool for its HEIF files; conversion to TIFF retains the full bit depth and BT.2100 HLG color profile indicator from the HEIF source; conversion to JPEG reduces the image to 8 bits.</p>
			<p>Image conversion tools that claim to support HEIC, primarily to convert to JPEG or PNG, include: <a href="https://imazing.com/heic">iMazing HEIC Converter</a>; <a href="https://www.copytrans.net/copytransheic/">CopyTrans HEIC
for Windows</a>; <a href="https://convertio.co/heic-converter/">Convertio</a>.  See also <a href="https://heic.imobie.com/review/top-free-heic-file-converter-for-windows-and-mac.htm">Top &amp; Free HEIC File Converters for Windows/Mac</a>.  A useful tool for looking at the structure of a HEIF file with HEVC encoding (or indeed for looking at any ISO_BMFF file) is <a href="https://imazing.com/isobmff">ISOBMFF Explorer</a>, available as source code on <a href="https://github.com/DigiDNA/ISOBMFF">github</a> or as a ready-to-use app for the Macintosh [<a href="https://apps.apple.com/in/app/isobmff-explorer/id1300778278?mt=12">at the App Store</a>].  The app reveals the nested box structure of the file and much of the structural metadata. </p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>The underlying HEVC encoding is heavily encumbered with patents.  According to <a href="https://apnews.com/press-release/pr-prnewswire/f49e22701a38b361a288563412fb7211">HEVC Advance Passes 10,000 Patent Milestone - announces Toshiba Corp. Joins as a Licensor</a>, a March 2020 press release, there are around 17,000.  Patents have proved a general problem for video coding schemes.  See, for example, <a href="https://www.eetimes.com/patents-standards-brew-licensing-woes/#">Patents, Standards Brew Licensing Woes (June 2019)</a> from EE Times.  Rather than there being a single patent pool, there are three, as shown in a <a href="https://blog.chiariglione.org/a-crisis-the-causes-and-a-solution/">blog post from January 2018</a> by Leonardo Chiariglione.</p>
			<p> In January 2019, a <a href="https://www.unifiedpatents.com/insights/2019/1/9/independent-economic-study-suggests-hevc-royalties-should-be-comparable-to-or-less-than-rates-for-avc">study of HEVC / H.265 standard-essential patent royalty rates</a> was released by Unified, an international membership organization that seeks to improve patent quality and deter unsubstantiated or invalid patent assertions in defined technology sectors (<a href="https://www.unifiedpatents.com/sep/">Zones</a>).  Video Codecs form one of the zones for Unified&apos;s activities.  The report, based on a methodology Unified describes as objective economic evaluation (OVAL), claims that it &quot;demonstrates that HEVC rates should be comparable to or less than the cost of licensing the main patent pool for AVC (MPEGLA), HEVC’s predecessor codec.&quot;  The report found that &quot;each of the three major licensors are asking for licensing rates that likely exceed what the total HEVC rate should be, both individually and when taken together.&quot;</p>
			<p>It is clear to the compilers of this resource that the patent situation has been an impediment to adoption.  In particular, the lack of built-in support for HEIF formats in browsers and in operating systems other than Apple&apos;s iOS and Mac OS seems likely to be related to the challenges and risks associated with the patent landscape.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.  Although related to the earlier AVC (H2.64) coding scheme,  the patent-related battle between Nokia and Lenovo in Germany in 2020 illustrates the risks.  See, for example, <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-nokia-patent-lenovo-group/setback-for-nokia-in-german-patent-battle-with-lenovo-idUSKBN27I25F">Setback for Nokia in German patent battle with Lenovo</a>, a November 2, 2020 post by Reuters.  Nokia has not joined any of the HEVC patent pools.</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon complex algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication to build tools.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>The format has excellent capabilities for incorporating metadata in various forms into the file.  Metadata can relate to the primary image or a collection of images as a whole, to individual items in a file comprising a collection or sequence of pictures, and to derived images, auxiliary images or thumbnails.  Commonly included is EXIF metadata, using a structure defined in clause A.2 in Annex A of the HEIF specification.  Annex A also defines how to include XMP metadata and also metadata as defined in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MPEG-7">MPEG-7</a> in XML form. Notice that the well-supported International Press Telecommunications Council (IPTC) metadata can be expressed in XMP using IPTC-developed XMP schemas.  See <a href="https://www.iptc.org/std/photometadata/specification/IPTC-PhotoMetadata">IPTC Photo Metadata Standard 2019.1</a>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>See <fddLink id="fdd000525">HEIF</fddLink>.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See <fddLink id="fdd000525">HEIF</fddLink>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>
				<p>Excellent support for online image functionality, panning, zooming, etc., especially when the tiling feature is employed.  Requires hardware coding support for real-time image coding at capture time; decoding/rendering benefits from hardware implementation.</p>
				<p>An overarching objective for this format was reduction in file size, while maintaining image quality and decoding performance; found superior to image formats JPEG, JPEG 2000, JPEG XR, and application of video codecs, AVC (H.264), VP8, and VP9 to single images.  See <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275836640_Objective_Performance_Evaluation_of_the_HEVC_Main_Still_Picture_Profile">Objective Performance Evaluation of the HEVC Main Still Picture Profile (2015)</a> by Tung Nguyen and Detlev Marpe.</p>
			</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>
				<p>Excellent support for images with large picture sizes and high spatial resolution.  See <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-511/?time=1457">Demo of zooming into a huge panorama</a> that has 2.9 gigapixels (91,000 pixels by about 32,000 pixels).  In comparison, JPEG is limited to 64,000 pixels in both directions.</p>
				<p>Bit depth depends on HEVC encoding profile used.  HEVC has profiles that support up to 16 bits per color channel, but as of 2020, implementation in cameras and mobile devices does not appear to exceed 10 bits.  Color spaces are indicated in the ColorInformationBox (with box type <i>colr </i>), which permits three different 4-character values for color type, allowing three mechanisms for specifying the color space.  The first mechanism is indicated by the colour type <i>nclx </i> as defined in Annex A.7.21 of the JPEG-XR specification for PTM_COLOR_INFO.  This provides a compact way to specify color primaries, transfer characteristics, and matrix coefficients via integer codes as listed and interpreted in tables A.8, A.9, and A.10 in the same annex.  Sample images from Canon and Sony showed use of this mechanism, with different choices for the coded values.  The compilers of this resource have not attempted to explore the differences or to discover whether the cameras use different values based on user choices or camera configuration. The second method, indicated by <i>prof</i>, declares an &quot;unrestricted&quot; ICC profile.  For example, the color space found in photos taken with an iPhone 7 is an Apple profile called <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/coregraphics/cgcolorspace/1408916-displayp3">Display P3</a>, which uses DCI P3 primaries, a D65 white point, and the sRGB transfer function. The compilers of this description have not identified any use of the third mechanism, indicated by <i>rICC</i> which appears to be for use in specialized workflows.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>See <fddLink id="fdd000525">HEIF</fddLink>.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:multispectral>See <fddLink id="fdd000525">HEIF</fddLink>.</fdd:multispectral>
			<fdd:beyondImage>The HEIF format allows storage of many HEVC coded images in one file; this capability supports a number of use cases.  See <a href="#identification">Description</a> above for information about uses for auxiliary images.  Image sequences (with or without associated timing information) can be used to support animation and image bursts, as used for Apple&apos;s &quot;Live Photo&quot; feature and equivalent features from other vendors, such as Samsung&apos;s &quot;Motion Photos.&quot;  It is also possible to store a collection of images with no order specified.  See examples of image collections, image sequences, image bursts, stereo pairs, etc., at <a href="https://nokiatech.github.io/heif/examples.html">HEIF example images</a> from Nokia.</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>heic</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>.heic is used for HEIF file containing one or more HEVC coded
image items.  Used by Apple starting in 2017 as default image storage format for mobile devices (iOS 11 and later).  .heics is specified for use for image sequences.  See below.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>image/heic</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration</a>. &quot;The MIME subtype name may be &apos;heic&apos; only if the file conforms to the requirements of the &apos;heic&apos;, &apos;heix&apos;, &apos;heim&apos;, or &apos;heis&apos; brand, and contains at least one of those brands as a compatible brand.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for the &apos;heim&apos; and &apos;heis&apos; brands. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Uniform Type Identifier (Mac OS)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>public.heic</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Used by Apple.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>File type brand (ISO Base Media File Format)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>heic</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Used for encoding single images or image collections in HEVC Main or Main Still Picture profile.  See <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">https://mp4ra.org/#/brands</a> and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration for image/heic</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>File type brand (ISO Base Media File Format)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>heix</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Used for encoding single images or image collections in HEVC Main 10 profile or format range extensions profile.  See <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">https://mp4ra.org/#/brands</a> and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration for image/heic</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>heics</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The compilers of this resource have not located examples of image sequence files with the .heics extension.  According to most sources, iPhone &quot;Live Photos&quot; are stored as .mov (Quicktime) files with HEVC encoding with an accompanying still photo with .heic extension.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>image/heic-sequence</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration</a>. &quot;The MIME subtype name may be &apos;heic-sequence&apos; only if the file conforms to the requirements of the &apos;hevc&apos;, &apos;hevx&apos;, &apos;hevm&apos;, or &apos;hevs&apos; brand, and contains that brand as a compatible brand. See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for the &apos;hevm&apos; and &apos;hevs&apos; brands.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>File type brand (ISO Base Media File Format)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>hevc</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Used for encoding image sequences in HEVC Main or Main Still Picture profile.  See <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">https://mp4ra.org/#/brands</a> and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration for image/heic-sequence</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>File type brand (ISO Base Media File Format)</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>hevx</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Used for encoding image sequences in HEVC Main 10 profile or format range extensions profile.  See <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">https://mp4ra.org/#/brands</a> and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration for image/heic-sequence</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>hif</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Used by Canon and Sony in cameras, apparently for single images, image collections, and for image sequences.  See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration for image/heic</a> and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration for image/heic-sequence</a>.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>Brands that identify variants of HEIF files with HEVC encoding</b>: Types for files complying with the <fddLink id="fdd000079">ISO_BMFF</fddLink> format are distinguished by means of <i>brands</i>.  Each file has a single major brand and may have a list of brands with which the file is declared to be compatible.  Brands are registered at <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">https://mp4ra.org/#/brands</a>.</p>
			<p>Brands associated with HEIF image files with HEVC encoding are listed below.  The file extension and MIME type (aka Internet media type) of a file in deriving from the ISO base media file format usually reflect the major brand in the filetype box.  See the IANA registrations at <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic</a> and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence</a> for the brands associated with the two MIME types registered for HEIF files with HEVC encoding.  HEVC-specific brands are defined in Annex B of the HEIF specification.  The brand depends on which of the many HEVC profiles defined in Annex A of the HEVC specification was used for encoding the primary image in the file.  The brands associated with HEVC encoding fall into three groups.  The first group of brands applies to variants intended for image capture, editing, and display:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>heic</b>: for HEIF files with individual <b>image items and image collections</b> where the image encoding of the items conforms to the <b>Main or Main Still Picture profile of HEVC</b>.  The Main profile is defined in clause A.3.2 of the HEVC specification. The Main Still Picture profile is defined in clause A.3.4 of the HEVC specification.  These profiles are <b>limited to 8 bits per color channel with chroma subsampling of 4:2:0</b>.  Associated primarily with .heic file extension (although .hif seems permissible according to the IANA registration) and MIME type image/heic.  See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>heix</b>: for HEIF files with individual <b>image items and image collections</b> where the image encoding of the items conforms to the Main 10 profiles or any of the &quot;format range extensions profiles&quot; of HEVC.  The <b>Main 10 and Main 10 Still Picture profiles</b> are defined in clause A.3.3 of the HEVC specification. The &quot;10&quot; in these profile names indicates the use of <b>10 bits per color channel</b>.  Format range extension profiles are explained in clause A.3.5 of the HEVC specification.  They are a collection of profiles that <b>extend either the bit-depth to 10 bits or more per color channel, or chroma subsampling to 4:2:2 or 4:4:4</b>, or both.  Also included are profiles for monochrome images. Associated with .heic or .hif file extension and MIME type image/heic.  See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>hevc</b>: for HEIF files with <b>image sequences</b> where the image encoding of the items conforms to the <b>Main or Main Still Picture profile</b> of HEVC.  Associated with .heics file extension and MIME type image/heic-sequence. See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>hevx</b>: for HEIF files with <b>image sequences</b> where the image encoding of the items conforms to the <b>Main 10 profiles or any of the format range extension profiles of HEVC</b>. Associated with .heics file extension and MIME type image/heic-sequence. See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The second group of brands applies to variants of ISO_BMFF that address requirements for streaming services, using an approach described as Layered HEVC (L-HEVC), which employs a concept known as Network Abstraction Layers (NAL).  This approach is specified in clauses 9 and 10 of <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/74429.html">ISO/IEC 14496-15:2019
Information technology — Coding of audio-visual objects — Part 15: Carriage of network abstraction layer (NAL) unit structured video in the ISO base media file format</a>.  The compilers of this resource have not encountered or investigated use of these L-HEVC variants beyond assembling the following list of associated brands. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>heim</b>: for HEIF files with individual <b>image items and image collections</b> where the image encoding of each layer of the item conforms to the Main profile or the Multiview Main profile of HEVC.  Associated with .heic file extension and MIME type image/heic.  See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>heis</b>: for HEIF files with individual <b>image items and image collections</b> where the image encoding of each layer conforms to Main profile, Main 10 profile, the Scalable Main profile, or the Scalable Main 10 profile of HEVC.  Associated with .heic file extension and MIME type image/heic.  See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic">IANA registration</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>hevm</b>: for HEIF files with <b>image sequences</b> where each layer in the reconstructed access units of the image sequence track conforms to the Main profile or the Multiview Main profile.  Associated with .heics file extension and MIME type image/heic-sequence. See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>hevs</b>: for HEIF files with <b>image sequences</b> where each layer in the reconstructed access units of the image sequence track conforms to the Main profile, Main 10 profile, Scalable Main profile, or the Scalable Main 10 profile. Associated with .heics file extension and MIME type image/heic-sequence. See <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/heic-sequence">IANA registration</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>The third group of brands are structural rather than codec-specific. These structural brands serve as a lowest common denominator for HEIF files, applicable to all codecs.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>mif1</b>: structural (not codec-specific) brand <b>applicable to all HEIF files for images and image collections</b>.  Defined in clause 10.2 of the HEIF specification.  Typically appears as the first compatible brand in all HEIF files for individual images or image collections with HEVC encoding.</li>
				<li>
					<b>msf1</b>: structural (not codec-specific) brand <b>applicable to all HEIF files for image sequences</b>.  Defined in clause 10.2 of the HEIF specification.  Typically appears as the first compatible brand.  Has been observed in use as the major brand for early demonstrations of image sequence files with the .heic extension.  However, <a href="https://www.ionos.com/digitalguide/websites/web-design/what-can-heif-high-efficiency-image-file-format-do/">HEIF: all you need to know about High Efficiency Image File Format</a>, a January 2020 post from IONOS, states that &quot;newer Apple devices (A9 processor required) automatically use the .heics extension when using the container format for image sequences.&quot; The compilers of this resource have not been able to confirm this statement. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Shown below are a few examples of the <i>ftyp</i> boxes and their major and compatible brands found in image files with .heic or .hif extensions.  In all these cases the <i>ftyp</i> box is the first box in the file and these strings show up in a text editor.  Since the ftyp box starts with its length (as a 32-bit unsigned binary integer, occupying 4 bytes), the &quot;ftyp&quot; string usually begins in the 5th byte of the file.  The four periods in the middle of these strings represent 4 bytes of binary zeroes; these bytes are reserved to support future versioning.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ftypheic....mif1miafMiHBheic<br/>taken with an Apple iPhone 7 using iOS 14, with extension .heic. Note: the <i>miaf</i> and <i>MiHB</i> brands are defined in <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/74417.html">ISO/IEC 23000-22:2019</a> and are described in the <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">MP4RA list of brands</a> as &quot;Multi-Image Application format brand for general MIAF requirements&quot; and &quot;Multi-Image Application format brand for MIAF HEVC Basic Profile.&quot;  See also <a href="https://nokiatech.github.io/heif/technical.html#miaf">Multi-Image Application Format (MIAF)</a> from Nokia.</li>
				<li>ftypmsf1....msf1hevcheicmif1iso8<br/>early example of an animated image sequence (&quot;Starburst), with extension .heic.  This example can be found at <a href="https://nokiatech.github.io/heif/examples.html">Examples</a> from Nokia under the heading &quot;Image sequences.&quot;  The <i>iso8</i> brand is defined in the underlying ISO_BMFF specification and identifies the version of that format.</li>
				<li>ftypmif1....mif1heichevc<br/>from an <a href="https://github.com/strukturag/libheif/blob/master/examples/example.heic">example</a> available from the github repository for the libheif software library</li>
				<li>ftypheix....mif1heix<br/>from a Canon camera, distributed with .hif extension.  The photo uses 10-bit color, and indicates this with a major brand of <i>heix</i>.  See <a href="https://github.com/lclevy/canon_cr3/blob/master/heif.md">Inside Canon High Efficiency Image File format</a> for more Canon examples.</li>
				<li>ftypheix....mif1heixmiafMiHAjpegSHIF<br/>from a Sony AS7 III camera, distributed from <a href="https://www.lightandmatter.org/2020/news-2/industry-news/new-from-sony-heif-to-tiff-converter-a7s-iii-atmos-ninja-support/">New From Sony: HEIF to TIFF Converter</a> with .hif extension.  Image has 10-bit color and declares itself compatible with the <i>miaf</i> and <i>MiHA</i> brands described in the <a href="https://mp4ra.org/#/brands">MP4RA list of brands</a> as &quot;Multi-Image Application format brand for general MIAF requirements&quot; and &quot;Multi-Image Application format brand for MIAF HEVC Advanced Profile.&quot;
	Additionally, it declares itself compatible with the use of JPEG encoding within the HEIF structure and the brand <i>SHIF</i>, which does not appear in the list of registered brands as of November 2020, but	may be a new brand in use by Sony. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				<b>Specifics for Apple-generated HEIC files </b>: The first Apple iPhones to support image capture in the HEIC format were the iPhone 7 and the iPhone 7 Plus, released in 2017 and incorporating the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_A10">A10 Fusion processor chip</a>, the first Apple chip to support hardware encoding of HEIF and HEVC.  The HEIC subtype of HEIF is used to capture images on supported mobile devices using Apple&apos;s iOS 11 or later, when the default &quot;High Efficiency&quot; is selected as the storage option for photographs in the Camera app.  See <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT207022">Using HEIF or HEVC media on Apple devices</a> for information on the iPad models able to capture images in the HEIC format.  Note: Apple typically uses a new processor chip with the release of each new family of products. See Wikipedia entry for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple-designed_processors">Apple-designed processors</a>. For example, in October 2020, Apple released the IPhone 12 family of phones with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_A10">A14 Bionic chip</a>.</p>
			<p>Apple provided detailed information about the characteristics of the HEIC images generated by its devices in some presentations at its WWDC 2017 conference for developers.  See, in particular:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-513/?time=1522">HEIF Configuration with Camera App</a>, the final content from a voice with slides presentation on the High Efficiency Image File Format.  This is a concise summary of the characteristics of the HEIC image files generated by Apple mobile devices.</li>
				<li>High Efficiency Image File Format, starting from the slide on file extensions from <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-513/?time=565">https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-513/?time=565</a>. This slide is followed by detailed sections on HEIF anatomy and the HEVC codec as applied by Apple to its images.  The sections on Tiles and HEVC are particularly helpful.  The section on HEVC compares this codec with JPEG compression.</li>
				<li>Presentation on Introducing HEIF and HEVC starting at <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-503/?time=1008">https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-503/?time=1008</a>, a link  to another summary of the characteristics of the Apple-generated HEIC images, followed by material aimed at application developers, including discussion of the software tools Apple provides for encoding and decoding and information on which Mac processors offer hardware support for encoding and decoding.</li>
				<li>Presentation on Working with HEIF and HEVC starting at the beginning of the section on HEIF at <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-511/?time=1208">https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017-511/?time=1208</a>.  This presentation covers, not only matters mainly of interest to developers, but also demonstrations of what the HEIF/HEIC combination format as implemented by Apple makes possible to enhance the experience for the ultimate end users of HEIC images in the Apple Photos application and features useful for developers of image editing applications.  [Aside: There is also a sprinkling of humor and poetry.]</li>
			</ul>
			<p>A brief summary of the technical characteristics of a still image captured by an Apple device, drawn from the video resources above, is:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>.heic extension.</li>
				<li>512 x 512 pixel tiles positioned in a grid.</li>
				<li>312 x 240 pixel thumbnail (larger than for JPEG, because of better compression using HEVC).</li>
				<li>use of HEVC Main Still Picture profile for encoding tiles.  Since the Main Still Picture profile is a subset of the Main Profile, this implies 8 bits per color channel.  In the experiment reported in <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275836640_Objective_Performance_Evaluation_of_the_HEVC_Main_Still_Picture_Profile">Objective Performance Evaluation of the HEVC Main Still Picture Profile</a>, the Main Still Picture profile outperformed JPEG by 44% based on PSNR and associated bit-rate savings.  Based on Apple&apos;s own experiments, the company claims twice the compression for the same visual quality.</li>
				<li>use of HEVC Monochrome profile for depth map.</li>
				<li>EXIF metadata (equivalent to that generated for JPEG by earlier iPhones).</li>
				<li>Technical metadata for depth map in XMP.</li>
				<li>After the <i>ftyp </i>box, the order of boxes/items in the file (not constrained by ISO_BMFF or HEIF specifications) is structural metadata (to allow decoders to prepare for processing the coded data), thumbnail, followed by coded data for the main image.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				<a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/avfoundation/avcapturephoto">AVCapturePhoto</a>Apple frameworks for developers to work with HEIF files with HEVC encoding include: <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/imageio">ImageIO</a>, the lowest level of Apple image framework access, which supports HEIF as a destination format, as well as a source for decode, incremental loading, metadata, and thumbnail abstraction.

Higher level access for editing or managing images in Mac OS is available using <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/photokit">Photokit</a> APIs.  On a suitable Apple iPhone or iPad, developers can employ the <a href="https://developer.apple.com/av-foundation/">AVFoundation</a> framework, using the new <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/avfoundation/avcapturephoto">AVCapturePhoto</a> and <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/avfoundation/avcapturephotooutput">AVCapturePhotoOutout</a> classes, to control capture and import HEIF content from the camera and write files in the HEIC format or in another format, such as JPEG.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>The HEVC (H.265) specification was first published in 2013, with an important update in 2014 to add profiles that are important for still images, to support greater bit depth per color channel and for wide color gamut.  The HEIF specification was first published in 2017.  The compilers of this description believe that HEIF/HEIC image files generated by Apple and other phone and camera manufacturers as of November 2020, are based on the 2014 HEVC specification and the 2017 HEIF specification.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>For format specifications for High Efficiency Image Format (HEIF), see format description for <fddLink id="fdd000525">HEIF</fddLink>.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Format specifications for High Efficiency Video Coding (HEVC), not yet described separately on this website.  Text for all editions is available via <a href="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/14107">http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/14107</a> or <a href="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.265">https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.265</a>. Initially published in 2013.  As of October 2020, the most recent edition is Edition 7, published November 2019.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.265</link>
							<tag>H.265 : High efficiency video coding</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/14107</link>
							<tag>Persistent identifier for H.265 Recommendation: http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/14107</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.265-201911-I</link>
							<tag>ITU Recommendation H.265 : High efficiency video coding, Version 7 (11/19)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/14107</link>
							<tag>Persistent identifier for ITU-T H.265 (V7) (11/2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/75484.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 23008-2:2020
Information technology — High efficiency coding and media delivery in heterogeneous environments — Part 2: High efficiency video coding</tag>
							<comment>ISO catalog record and preview.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Efficiency_Image_File_Format#HEIC:_HEVC_in_HEIF</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for High Efficiency Image File Format | HEIC: HEVC in HEIF</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to HEVC (High Efficiency Video Coding), also known as H.265 and MPEG-H Part 2.  Text for all editions is available via <a href="http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/14107">http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/14107</a> or <a href="https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.265">https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-H.265</a>. Initially published in 2013.  As of October 2020, the most recent edition is Edition 7, published November 2019.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Efficiency_Video_Coding</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for High Efficiency Video Coding</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://handle.itu.int/11.1002/1000/11885</link>
							<tag>Persistent identifier for ITU-T H.265 (04/2013)</tag>
							<comment>Record for first edition of ITU-T H.265.  Lists other editions.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://x265.org/</link>
							<tag>x265 HEVC Encoder / H.265 Video Codec</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-h/high-efficiency-video-coding</link>
							<tag>High Efficiency Video Coding | on MPEG website</tag>
							<comment>As of June 2020, this MPEG website is no longer actively maintained by its former editor</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources with descriptions and examples of High Efficiency Video Coding (HEVC) for still images in the High Efficiency Image File Format (HEIF).</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://nokiatech.github.io/heif/technical.html</link>
							<tag>HEIF Technical information | from Nokia</tag>
							<comment>Based on a 2015 white paper prepared for MPEG meeting in Geneva, in October 2015.  Includes information on MIAF (Multi-Image Application Format).</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://nokiatech.github.io/heif/examples.html</link>
							<tag>Examples of HEIF images</tag>
							<comment>Examples of single images, image collections, image bursts, image sequences, stereo pair, etc.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://openheicfile.com/</link>
							<tag>Open HEIC File | openheicfile.com</tag>
							<comment>This special-purpose website has good information, but appears unchanged since 2018.  The site does not reveal its origins.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://mpeg.chiariglione.org/standards/mpeg-h/image-file-format</link>
							<tag>MPEG-H Image File Format | on MPEG website</tag>
							<comment>As of June 2020, this MPEG website is no longer actively maintained by its former editor.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.fredmiranda.com/forum/topic/1655827/0</link>
							<tag>Q&amp;A thread &quot;Photoshop does not support Canon HEIF files&quot; (July 2020)</tag>
							<comment>Has link to single sample HEIF .hif image file from Canon camera</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.lightandmatter.org/wp-content/download/DSC09397.HIF.zip</link>
							<tag>Single sample HEIF .hif image file from Sony camera</tag>
							<comment>Aavailable from https://www.lightandmatter.org/2020/news-2/industry-news/new-from-sony-heif-to-tiff-converter-a7s-iii-atmos-ninja-support/</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Apple held several sessions on HEIF and HEVC at its 2017 developers conference, WWDC 2017.  The videos listed below are excellent resources on the special features of the HEIF file format and HEVC encoding as chosen by Apple and the reasons behind Apple&apos;s choice to adopt them for built-in image support across its iOS and Mac OS product line.  Note that each video is supported by a transcript with convenient built-in links to the corresponding spot in the video.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017/503/</link>
							<tag>Introducing HEIF and HEVC (June 2017) | Video (30 mins) from Apple Developers Conference WWDC 2017</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017/513</link>
							<tag>High Efficiency Image File Format (2017) | Video (30 mins) from Apple Developers Conference WWDC 2017</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2017/511</link>
							<tag>Working with HEIF and HEVC (2017) | Video (60 mins) from Apple Developers Conference WWDC 2017</tag>
							<comment>Details for developers on API modifications in existing toolkits.  HEIF section begins at 20 mins.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://developer.apple.com/documentation/coregraphics/cgcolorspace/1408916-displayp3</link>
					<tag>Apple colorspace profile | Display P3</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Reports of studies comparing compression performance and image quality for HEVC still images with other compression schemes.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/275836640_Objective_Performance_Evaluation_of_the_HEVC_Main_Still_Picture_Profile</link>
							<tag>Objective Performance Evaluation of the HEVC Main Still Picture Profile (2015 | by Tung Nguyen and Detlev Marpe</tag>
							<comment>Published in 
IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology 25(5):790-797</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7532321</link>
							<tag>HEVC still image coding and high efficiency image file format (2016) | by Jani Lainema, et al. </tag>
							<comment>Requires subscription or purchase.  From 2016 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP 2016) </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to JPEG compression encoding, which was standardized as ITU Recommendation T.81 in 1992 and ISO/IEC 10918-1 in 1994.  See also the description in this resource for the widely supported <fddLink id="fdd000017">JPEG Image Encoding Family</fddLink>.  HEIF with the HEIC and HEIX brands is often described as a potential replacement for JPEG.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://jpeg.org/jpeg/</link>
							<tag>Overview of JPEG | from jpeg.org</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/18902.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 10918-1:1994
Information technology — Digital compression and coding of continuous-tone still images: Requirements and guidelines</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-T.81-199209-I/en</link>
							<tag>ITU Recommendation T.81 : Information technology - Digital compression and coding of continuous-tone still images - Requirements and guidelines</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Other resources related to adoption of HEIF with HEVC encoding:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT207022</link>
							<tag>Using HEIF or HEVC media on Apple devices | from Apple support site</tag>
							<comment>Includes list of Apple mobile devices on which HEIF format images can be captured.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://tidbits.com/2017/06/30/hevc-and-heif-will-make-video-and-photos-more-efficient/</link>
							<tag>HEVC and HEIF Will Make Video and Photos More Efficient (June 2017) | from TidBITS</tag>
							<comment>States &quot;These two new formats will be used by iOS 11 and macOS 10.13 High Sierra when Apple releases them later this year.&quot;</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.howtogeek.com/345314/what-is-the-heif-or-heic-image-format/</link>
							<tag>What is the HEIF (or HEIC) Image Format? (March 2018) | from How-to Geek</tag>
							<comment>States that HEIF is used by Apple’s iPhone and is also coming to Google’s Android P.  Mentons .heic as often used as file extension </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.usa.canon.com/internet/portal/us/home/explore/product-showcases/cameras-and-lenses/1dx-mark-iii</link>
							<tag>Canon EOS-1D X Mark III</tag>
							<comment>This new Canon camera, introduced in January 2020 supports HEIF as an in-camera filetype.  Uses .hif as extension</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://downloads.canon.com/nw/camera/products/eos/1d-x-mark-iii/resources/Canon_EOS_1DX_Mark_III_Still_White_Paper.pdf</link>
							<tag>Canon EOS-1D X Mark III White Paper (January 2020)</tag>
							<comment>By staff of Canon U.S.A., Inc.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.cameralabs.com/jpeg-vs-heif-canon-hif-comparison/</link>
							<tag>JPEG vs HEIF: Canon commits to HIF (January 2020) | from Gordon Laing of Camera Labs</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://camerajabber.com/tutorials/how-to-shoot-in-heif-format-on-canon-cameras/</link>
							<tag>HOW TO... shoot in HEIF format on Canon cameras</tag>
							<comment>Implies that Canon EOS-1D X Mark III supports 10-bit color.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://support.usa.canon.com/kb/index?page=content&amp;id=ART176556&amp;cat=CAMCORDERS&amp;actp=LIST&amp;showDraft=false</link>
							<tag>Canon Support: Working with files saved in HEVC format.</tag>
							<comment>Canon provides its own HEVC codec for Windows to support its Digital Photo Professional (DPP) image processing application.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://shop.sg.canon/canon-insider/hdr-pq-heif-breaking-through-the-limits-of-jpeg/</link>
							<tag>HDR PQ HEIF: Breaking Through the Limits of JPEG | from Canon Insider </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://github.com/lclevy/canon_cr3/blob/master/heif.md</link>
							<tag>Inside Canon High Efficiency Image File format (2020) | by Laurent Clevy</tag>
							<comment>Analyzes examples of files from the three Canon cameras that create HEIF files (with .hif extension)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.sony.com/electronics/interchangeable-lens-cameras/ilce-7sm3/specifications</link>
							<tag>Sony A7S III with pro movie/still capability
ILCE-7SM3
</tag>
							<comment>Supports 8-bit and 10-bit color.  Uses .hif extension.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://camerajabber.com/reviews/sony-a7s-iii/</link>
							<tag>Sony A7S III first impressions (July 2020)</tag>
							<comment>Indicates, &quot;10-bit colour depth and 4:2:2 colour sampling available in all recording formats.&quot;</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://support.d-imaging.sony.co.jp/app/heif/en/</link>
							<tag>Sone | HEIF Converter</tag>
							<comment>Provides details of the conversions to JPEG and TIFF for the Sony-specific variant of HEIF image with .hif extension.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://developer.android.com/guide/topics/media/media-formats#image-formats</link>
							<tag>Android Studio | Supported media formats: Image support</tag>
							<comment>States that versions of Android since 8.0 can decode HEIF, giving .heif and .heic as extensions.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://source.android.com/devices/camera/heif</link>
							<tag>HEIF Imaging | from source.android.com (open source OS)</tag>
							<comment>Supports HEIF decoding since Android 8.0</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.cnet.com/news/qualcomm-snapdragon-855-chip-gives-android-phones-iphone-photo-packing-ability/</link>
							<tag>With Snapdragon 855 chip, Android phones get iPhone&apos;s photo-packing ability (December 5, 2018) | from CNet</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.qualcomm.com/media/documents/files/qualcomm-snapdragon-662-mobile-platform-product-brief.pdf</link>
							<tag>Qualcomm Snapdragon 662 Mobile Platform</tag>
							<comment>Chip used in some lower-end Android mobile devices.  Supports HEIF for camera capture.  Released in January 2020.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.facebook.com/business/help/523719398041952</link>
							<tag>Facebook | Supported Image Formats for Ads</tag>
							<comment>Includes HEIC</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://help.smugmug.com/accepted-file-types-for-uploading-Sy7llgPJ4Sf</link>
							<tag>SmugMug | Accepted file types for uploading</tag>
							<comment>HEIC images are converted to JPEG on upload.  The size limitations per photo are 500 mebibytes (a bit over 500 megabytes) and 4 gigapixels.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://support.shutterfly.com/s/article/upload-my-photos#accepted-files</link>
							<tag>Shutterfly | Accepted File Formats</tag>
							<comment>Users of Shutterfly&apos;s iOS app can upload HEIF/HEIC files.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://help.dropbox.com/installs-integrations/mobile/ios-formats</link>
							<tag>Dropbox | Support for HEIF (.heic) and HEVC photo and video files</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://gdal.org/drivers/raster/heif.html</link>
							<tag>GDAL | HEIF/HEIC – ISO/IEC 23008-12:2017 High Efficiency Image File Format</tag>
							<comment>Read-only support added in version 3.2 (October 2020), based on use of libheif.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.nokia.com/ozo/heif/</link>
							<tag>Nokia HEIF Solution</tag>
							<comment>Product description for read/write engine for HEIF images</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to JPEG compression encoding, which was standardized as ITU Recommendation T.81 in 1992 and ISO/IEC 10918-1 in 1994.  See also the description in this resource for the widely supported <fddLink id="fdd000017">JPEG Image Encoding Family</fddLink>.  HEIF with the HEIC and HEIX brands is often described as a potential replacement for JPEG.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://jpeg.org/jpeg/</link>
							<tag>Overview of JPEG | from jpeg.org</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/18902.html</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 10918-1:1994
Information technology — Digital compression and coding of continuous-tone still images: Requirements and guidelines</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-T.81-199209-I/en</link>
							<tag>ITU Recommendation T.81 : Information technology - Digital compression and coding of continuous-tone still images - Requirements and guidelines</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://mp4ra.org/</link>
					<tag>Official Registration Authority for the ISOBMFF family of standards</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
