<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000243" titleName="HD Photo, Version 1.0 (Windows Media Photo)" shortName="WMP_1_0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2020-09-25</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>HD Photo, Version 1.0 (formerly Windows Media Photo)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>raster image formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Format developed by Microsoft for continuous-tone still images that supports a wide range of features including:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Multiple color formats for display or print</li>
				<li>Fixed or floating point, high-dynamic-range image encoding</li>
				<li>Lossless or high-quality lossy compression</li>
				<li>Efficient decoding for multiple resolutions and sub-regions</li>
				<li>Minimal overhead for format conversion or transformations during decoding</li>
			</ul>
			<p>When HD Photo was released, Microsoft stated (<a href="https://news.softpedia.com/news/Microsoft-Unveils-Windows-Media-Photo-40482.shtml">as reported by Softpedia News on November 18, 2006</a>) that the format delivers &#34;a lightweight, high-performance algorithm with a small memory footprint that enables practical, in-device encoding and decoding.&#34; </p>
			<p>Support for HD Photo in Windows is provided by the Windows Imaging Component (<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/wic/-wic-about-windows-imaging-codec">WIC</a>), an installable codec architecture introduced for Windows Vista and built in to later Windows versions.  Microsoft stated that Vista represented the integration of imaging at the operating system level, reducing the level of activity required of specific applications. WIC is included with Windows Presentation Foundation (<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/desktop/wpf/">WPF</a>), a development environment provided by Microsoft for building user interfaces.</p>
			<p>In a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080113223843/http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2007/jul07/07-31JPEGXRPR.mspx">July 31, 2007, press release</a>, Microsoft Corp. announced the decision by the Joint Photographic Expert Group (JPEG) to introduce a new work item for the standardization of HD Photo which, if approved, would lead to a format tentatively titled &quot;JPEG XR."  JPEG XR was given final approval as ITU-T Recommendation T.832 in April 2009 and as ISO/IEC 29199-2 in June 2009.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Format developed by Microsoft for continuous-tone still images that supports a wide range of features including: multiple color formats for display or print, fixed or floating point, high-dynamic-range image encoding, lossless or high-quality lossy compression, efficient decoding for multiple resolutions and sub-regions, and minimal overhead for format conversion or transformations during decoding. Submitted to Joint Photographic Expert Group for standardization; published in 2009 as JPEG XR.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Used for content in middle and final states. Although designed for potential use by camera manufacturers, neither HD Photo nor its successor, JPEG XR, was adopted for that purpose.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>HD Photo was standardized as JPEG XR (not described on this website at this time).  See <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/billcrow/jpeg-xr-is-now-an-international-standard">JPEG XR is Now an International Standard</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000514</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MS-XPS</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Microsoft XML Paper Specification, (XPS)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>One of several image formats permitted in the XPS format. </fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress has a very small number of files with .hdp (3 files, 9KB) and .wdp (26 files, 6MB) file extensions in its digital collections. These have likely come from archived websites..</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>Neither HD Photo nor Windows Media Photo are included in the <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/index.html">Recommended Formats Statement</a> in relation to acquisition of digital images for LC collections.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Developed by the Microsoft Corporation and publicly documented.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>The container format and API were specified in the <i>HD Photo Feature Specification</i> (2006), made available from <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080119233135/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/wmphoto.mspx">http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/wmphoto.mspx</a> (link from January 2008 via Internet Archive) and later from <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121026085801/http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463400.aspx">http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463400.aspx</a> (link from October 2012 via Internet Archive).  Information about the HD Photo compressed bitstream format and how to implement an encoder and decoder were part of the HD Photo Device Porting Kit 1.0 (DPK).  This kit was available from <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080117122652/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/hdphotodpk.mspx">http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/hdphotodpk.mspx</a> (link from January 2008 via Internet Archive) and later from <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20121017071823/http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463381.aspx">http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/hardware/gg463381.aspx</a> (link from October 2012 via Internet Archive).</p>
			<p>The page titled <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/previous-versions/gg463400(v=msdn.10)">HD Photo Specification Download (last updated March 2010)</a> has been archived by Microsoft, but lacks an active link for the download.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Introduced in 2006, with initial dependency on the level of adoption of the  Windows Vista operating/application system, made available in a general release in 2007.  In December 2007, Microsoft announced the availability of plug-ins for Adobe PhotoShop. HD Photo is incorporated as a native codec into the Windows Imaging Component (WIC); see <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/wic/hdphoto-format-overview">HD Photo Format Overview</a>.  HD Photo is one of several image formats that could be incorporated into Microsoft&apos;s <fddLink id="fdd000514">XPS</fddLink> format.  The compilers of this resource have not encountered indications of significant adoption of HD Photo outside Windows.  For example, in <a href="https://fileinfo.com/extension/hdp">https://fileinfo.com/extension/hdp</a> (as of September 2020) the only Mac application listed is the plugin released by Microsoft for Adobe Photoshop.  However, in a response to the February 2020 question <a href="https://community.adobe.com/t5/photoshop/how-to-use-javascript-to-save-jpeg-xr-files/m-p/10912391?page=1">How to use javascript to save jpeg-xr files</a> on the Adobe Support Community, there was a response indicating that the plugin may not work in recent versions of Adobe Photoshop.  The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPEG_XR">Wikipedia entry for JPEG XR</a> indicates that the plugin works with Photoshop versions CS2, CS5-CS6 but is silent on later versions of Photoshop.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>The following graphics applications claim to read and write photos in the HD Photo format:  XnView Classic (for Windows); XnView MP (successor to XnView, available for Windows, MacOS, and Linux). The following graphics application claims to read but not write HD Photo images: <a href="https://www.irfanview.com/main_formats.htm">IrfanView</a> (for Windows only). Applications that claim to handle JPEG XR images may also handle images in Windows Media Photo and HD Photo formats. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>
			</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>Licensing applies to applications that create or display images, not to the images themselves. A Microsoft Web page consulted in August 2006 and no longer available in January 2007 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060718195423/http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/licensing/wmphoto.aspx">http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/licensing/wmphoto.aspx</a>) stated, "Under most conditions, Windows Media Photo technology is available free of charge; royalties are associated only with specific licensing conditions."</p>
			<p>According to the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090202180751/http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo">Wikipedia entry for HD Photo as of February 2, 2009</a>, &quot;A Microsoft representative stated in a January 2007 interview that in order to encourage the adoption and use of HD Photo, the specification is made available under the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/openspecs/dev_center/ms-devcentlp/1c24c7c8-28b0-4ce1-a47d-95fe1ff504bc">Microsoft Open Specification Promise</a>, which asserts that Microsoft offers the specification for free, and will not file suit on the patented technology, and that open-source software can therefore make use of the format. However, as of Microsoft&apos;s December 4, 2007 update, HD Photo is still not among the technologies that Microsoft has listed as being covered by the Open Specification Promise.&quot;</p>
			<p>Note: Rather than covering HD Photo&apos;s successor JPEG XR by the Open Specification Promise (OSP), Microsoft chose to use its <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/openspecs/dev_center/ms-devcentlp/8b8d1b7a-a10a-4667-9558-6d9c43adf60d">Microsoft Community Promise</a>.  See <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100818181609/http://www.microsoft.com:80/interop/CP/default.mspx">Microsoft Community Promise (as of August 18, 2010, via Internet Archive)</a>. The Community Promise model was introduced in 2007 to support interoperability. See, for example, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20070306185119/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/xpscommunitypromisefaq.mspx">Community Promise for XPS - FAQ (as of March 6, 2007, via Internet Archive)</a>.</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication to build tools.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>WMP_1_0 uses a &#34;TIFF-like&#34; file container to store image data in a table of Image File Directory (IFD) tags, using tag numbers from  TIFF's baseline, extended, and &#34;private&#34; sets. Examples of tags drawn from extended and private TIFF sets: ICCProfile (34675), XMPMetadata (700), and EXIFMetadata (34665). For an overview of tags, including a listing of WMP_1_0 tags, see <a href="../content/tiff_tags.shtml">Tags for TIFF and Related Specifications</a>.</p>
			<p>The large number of possible image encodings are identified by means of GUIDs specified by Microsoft. (This contrasts with an approach based upon the placement of data in a set of tags for such features as bits per pixel, photometric interpretation, and so on.)</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>No DRM technology; see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>Supported.</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>Very high levels of image quality are supported. The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090202180751/http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo">Wikipedia entry for HD Photo as of February 2, 2009</a> reports, &#34;HD Photo is an image codec that gives a high-dynamic-range image encoding while requiring only integer operations (with no divides) for both compression and decompression. It supports monochrome, RGB, CMYK and even n-channel color representation, using up to 16-bit unsigned integer representation, or up to 32-bit fixed point or floating point representation, and also supports RGBE (Radiance) . . . .  All color representations are transformed to an internal color representation. The transformation is entirely reversible, so, by using appropriate quantizers, both lossy and lossless compression can be achieved.&#34;</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>Excellent support; files can include ICC profiles; extended color gamuts are supported.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>HD Photo is a raster format, without support for vector graphics</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:beyondImage>Paraphrasing the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090202180751/http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo">Wikipedia entry for HD Photo as of February 2, 2009</a>: An alpha channel may be present for transparency. The format allows decoding part of an image, without decoding the entire image. Full decoding is also unnecessary for certain operations such as cropping, downsampling, horizontal or vertical flips, or cardinal rotations.</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>hdp</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>wdp</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Both extensions are listed in Microsoft&apos;s document describing the features of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080119233135/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/wmphoto.mspx">HD Photo</a> (November 16, 2006).  In the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090202180751/http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo">Wikipedia entry for HD Photo as of February 2, 2009</a> the extension &quot;wdp&quot; is labeled &quot;formerly.&quot;  PRONOM&apos;s entry for JPEG XR [<a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/590">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/590</a>] includes the extension .wdp but not .hdp.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>image/vnd.ms-photo</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090202180751/http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo">Wikipedia entry for HD Photo as of February 2, 2009</a>. Also in Microsoft&apos;s documents describing the features of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060630062104/http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/forpros/wmphoto/">Windows Media Photo</a> (June 25, 2006) and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080119233135/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/wmphoto.mspx">HD Photo</a> (November 16, 2006).</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 49 49 BC</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: II.</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From the <a href="https://filext.com/file-extension/WDP">The File Extension Source</a> for WDP.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/590</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM includes the .wdp file extension in its entry for JPEG XR.  See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/590">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/590</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q11222362</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11222362">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11222362</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>Regarding compression:</b> The summation for compression from the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060913000000/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Media_Photo">Wikipedia entry for Windows Media Photo on September 13, 2006</a> was as follows.  &#34;uses a reversible color space conversion, a reversible lapped biorthogonal transform and a non-arithmetic entropy encoding scheme, which is very efficient in preserving high frequency image data. This makes the algorithm retain a higher image quality at high compression ratios. The transform operation needs 3 multiply and add operations and 7 add or shift operations at the highest quality level and in the highest performance mode, 1 multiply and add operation and 4 add or shifts are required per pixel, giving the codec a high performance. Windows Media Photo processes images in 16x16 macroblocks.&#34; The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090202180751/http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo">Wikipedia entry for HD Photo as of February 2, 2009</a> offers more detail. </p>
			<p>
				<b>Regarding digital rights management</b>: In a comment on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060813190610/http://blogs.msdn.com/andy_simonds/archive/2005/10/06/477954.aspx">blog post</a> consulted in August 2006, HD Photo Program Manager Bill Crow commented:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Windows Media DRM is ideal for publishing audio and video, but is really not that useful for still photography. Most commercial scenarios for digital photos require that the customer receive direct access to the image, which basically  defeats the approach used by Windows Media DRM (where the goal is to protect the content all the way to the glass or speakers). Also, Windows Media DRM is designed for a &#34;few to many&#34; publishing model; the DRM license generation technology does not easily allow anyone to generate their own DRM licenses.</li>
				<li>While we are looking at DRM for photos for possible support in the future, the initial implementation was deliberately been designed to be simple, lightweight and easy for partners to implement directly in devices. That said, you can currently use Windows Document Rights Management for very effective management of rights access to digital photos.</li>
				<li>We're investigating more comprehensive solutions to manage digital photo access rights, copyright protection and provenance guarantees as features for future versions of Windows Media Photo.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				<b>Other notes: </b>
				<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20090120174809/http://blogs.msdn.com/billcrow/">Bill Crow's own blog</a> is informative; here are some excerpts from 2006:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>From <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/billcrow/encoding-windows-media-photo-files-part-1-dpk-tools">July 5, 2006</a>: Our current encoder tools include a choice between the sample applications that are part of the Windows Media Photo Device Porting Kit (DPK) or an encoder utility based on the Windows Imaging Components (WIC) interfaces that we developed internally for our own testing purposes.  Both tools are command line utilities, and each has its own specific strengths.</li>
				<li>From <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/billcrow/pixel-formats-part-2-fixed-point-and-floating-point">June 21, 2006</a>: The fundamental goal with a high dynamic range, wide gamut pixel format is to never discard image information that falls outside the visible range.  The entire tonal spectrum is always retained, regardless of the current exposure or color adjustments. Using fixed point or floating point values, pixel information is encoded using an extended numerical range.  The visible portion of the numerical range is a subset of the total numerical range that can be encoded with fixed point or floating point values.  . . . If color or exposure adjustment pushes a pixel value outside the visible range, rather than losing this value (as is the case with unsigned integer representations), the numerical value is still retained.  If a subsequent adjustment brings that pixel value back into the visible range, the correct numerical value is fully recovered.  This dramatically eliminates the issues and concerns with &#34;flattening&#34; a file.  Most color or exposure adjustments are completely reversible, eliminating the need to restart with the original RAW file or an intermediate layered editing file.</li>
				<li>From <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/billcrow/introducing-hd-photo">November 17, 2006</a>: For the immediate future, we will still use the Windows Media Photo name to refer to the implementation of HD Photo in Microsoft products that are already shipping.  This includes the initial release of Windows Vista, the XML Paper Specification (XPS), .NET Framework 3.0, and Windows Imaging Component (WIC). With the new name, the spec now adds support for a new file extension - .hdp.  However, the various Windows implementations won&apos;t recognize this new extension until some updates have been released at some point in the future.  (No, I don&apos;t know exactly when that will be.) So we&apos;re recommending implementers stick with the current .wdp extension.  You can &quot;future-proof&quot; your application by also adding support for the new .hdp extension.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The image-coding technology used in WMP_1_0 was incubated in Microsoft Research and developed by Microsoft’s Core Media Processing team.   Windows Media Photo was announced at the Windows Hardware Engineering Conference (WinHEC) in May 2006; see <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20060920090419/http://news.com.com/Microsoft+shows+off+JPEG+rival/2100-1025_3-6076650.html">Microsoft shows off JPEG rival</a>, a May 24, 2006 article from c|net.  See <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/billcrow/welcome">Welcome!</a> post for a new blog devoted to the format.  The name was changed to HD Photo later in 2006.  See <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/billcrow/introducing-hd-photo">Introducing HD Photo</a>, a blog post from November 17, 2006.  In July 2007, Microsoft Corp issued a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20071213055354/http://www.microsoft.com:80/presspass/press/2007/jul07/07-31JPEGXRPR.mspx">press release</a> announcing that its HD Photo file format would be considered for standardization by the Joint Photographic Expert Group (JPEG), tentatively to be titled JPEG XR.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080119233135/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/wmphoto.mspx</link>
					<tag>HD Photo Specification 1.0 (2006)</tag>
					<comment>Link via Internet Archive</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20080117122652/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/hdphotodpk.mspx</link>
					<tag>HD Photo Device Porting Kit 1.0 (DPK)</tag>
					<comment>Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20090202180751/http:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for HD Photo as of February 2, 2009 | link via Internet Archive</tag>
					<comment>By early 2011 https:/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HD_Photo redirected to the Wikipedia entry for JPEG XR.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060913000000/http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_Media_Photo</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for Windows Media Photo as of September 13, 2006 | link via Internet Archive</tag>
					<comment>This is a poor capture of the page, missing the layout.  However, it appears to be the only capture of the entry before it was redirected to the entry for HD Photo.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Bill Crow was Microsoft&apos;s Program Manager for Windows Media Photo and HD Photo.  He maintained a blog from the public announcement of Windows Media Photo in 2006 through the adoption of the image-coding system as the international standard known as JPEG XR in 2009.  </fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/archive/blogs/billcrow/</link>
							<tag>Bill Crow blog (active 2006-2009) | as archived by Microsoft</tag>
							<comment>Crow was the Windows Media Photo Program Manager.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20090120174809/http://blogs.msdn.com/billcrow/</link>
							<tag>Bill Crow blog (active 2006-2007 at this URL) | link via Internet Archive</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060716141308/http://www.billcrow.com/wmphoto/An%20Introduction%20to%20Windows%20Media%20Photo.ppt</link>
							<tag>Windows Media Photo | a new format for end-to-end digital photography (2006)</tag>
							<comment>Presentation given at Pro Photo 2006, based on earlier presentation at WinHEC 2006.  Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20090120174809/http://download.microsoft.com/download/a/f/d/afdfd50d-6eb9-425e-84e1-b4085a80e34e/CLN-T374_WH07.pptx</link>
							<tag>HD Photo Implementation Guidelines | presented at WinHEC 2007</tag>
							<comment>Link via Internet Archive</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060813190610/http://blogs.msdn.com/andy_simonds/archive/2005/10/06/477954.aspx</link>
					<tag>Andy Simonds blog post (10/6/2005) | with comments</tag>
					<comment>Comments mention licensing and DRM.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to Windows Media Photo, prior to its renaming as HD Photo.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060630062104/http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/forpros/wmphoto/</link>
							<tag>For Professionals: Windows Media Photo | link via Internet Archive as of June 30, 2006</tag>
							<comment>Includes functioning link to download specification for Windows Media Photo (dated June 25, 2006)..</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060926230042/http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/xps/wmphotodwn.mspx</link>
							<tag>Windows Hardware Developer Central (WHDC): Windows Media Photo Specification (May 25, 2006)</tag>
							<comment>Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20060920090419/http://news.com.com/Microsoft+shows+off+JPEG+rival/2100-1025_3-6076650.html</link>
							<tag>C|net: Microsoft shows off JPEG rival (May 24, 2006) </tag>
							<comment>Reports on presentation by Bill Crow at Windows Hardware Engineering Conference (WinHec 2006)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/590</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/590</tag>
					<comment>PRONOM information for JPEG/XR includes .wdp as possible file extension. PUID: fmt/590</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11222362</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q11222362</tag>
					<comment>Information in WikiData about HD Photo. WikiData Title ID: Q11222362</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
