<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><fdd:FDD id="fdd000577" titleName="WebP" shortName="WebP" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">	<fdd:properties>		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>			<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>		<fdd:formatCategories>			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>		</fdd:formatCategories>		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>		<fdd:updates>			<fdd:date>2023-04-13</fdd:date>		</fdd:updates>		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>	</fdd:properties>	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>		<fdd:fullName>WebP</fdd:fullName>		<fdd:keywords>			<fdd:keyword>image formats</fdd:keyword>			<fdd:keyword>compression formats</fdd:keyword>		</fdd:keywords>		<fdd:description>			<p>WebP, pronounced "weppy," is a raster image file format for providing lossless and lossy compression for images on the web. Matt Ellis in <a href="https://99designs.com/blog/tips/webp-image-format/">What is WebP? Pros and Cons of this Next-gen Image Format</a>, 2021, defines lossless compression as when the image quality stays the same as the data size goes down and lossy compression as when the image quality goes down slightly as the data size goes down significantly.  To quote Ellis, “WebP images are usually smaller than their counterparts, but with the same quality, thanks to their superior compression.” WebP is developed by Google, first released in 2018, and is defined through the <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp">WebP Open-Source Project Page</a> (referenced throughout this document), where users can find WebP support, guides, reference, and samples.</p>			<p>				<b>Advantages of WebP:</b>			</p>			<ul>				<li>					<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp ">Google reports</a> that WebP lossless images are 26% smaller in size compared to PNGs and lossy images are 25-34% smaller in size compared to JPEGs.</li>				<li>Compatible with various browsers including native support for WebP lossy in Google Chrome (desktop) 17+,Google Chrome for Android version 25+,Microsoft Edge 18+,Firefox 65+,Opera 11.10+,Native web browser, Android 4.0+ (ICS), and Safari 14+ (iOS 14+, macOS Big Sur+). See <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq#which_web_browsers_natively_support_webp">Which web browsers natively support WebP?</a> for full list</li>				<li>According to <a href="https://99designs.com/blog/tips/webp-image-format/">What is WebP? Pros and cons of this next-gen image format</a>, websites load faster and use less bandwidth thanks to the smaller file size.</li>				<li>Higher levels of annimation support with the transparent backgrounds of PNG and the animation capabilities of GIF</li>			</ul>			<p>				<b>Disadvantages of WebP:</b>			</p>			<ul>				<li>					<a href="https://99designs.com/blog/tips/webp-image-format/">What is WebP? Pros and cons of this next-gen image format</a> details some drawbacks of WebP including that since it is designed mainly for the web, images may not suitable for printing</li>				<li>Older browsers may not support WebP.</li>				<li>Loss of some details, compressing files reduces quality.</li>				<li>In addition, 					<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq#why_should_i_use_animated_webp">Google</a> notes that WebP is more CPU-intensive than animated GIF.				</li>			</ul>			<p>Reference implementation library [libwebp] is available from <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/code/">Google Git Repository</a> or as a <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/download">tarball</a> (set of <a href="https://www.cs.cornell.edu/courses/cs5220/2017fa/tar-info.html">packaged files</a> in a single file that is compressed using gzip).</p>			<p>				<b>WebP Container Specification:</b>			</p>			<p>Per the <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">WebP Project Page</a>, WebP files include <fddLink id="fdd000578">VP8</fddLink> lossy encoding or VP8L lossless encoding image data in a container package based on <fddLink id="fdd000025">Resource Interchange File Format (RIFF)</fddLink>. The WebP container supports:</p>			<ul>				<li>Lossless compression.</li>				<li>Animation, multiple frames.</li>				<li>Metadata, stored in Exif or XMP formats (optional).</li>				<li>Transparency, i.e., alpha channel (optional).</li>				<li>Color Profile, may have embedded ICC profile (optional).</li>			</ul>			<p>WebP files contain either a still image or animation, and the file format is based on RIFF, which has the basic file element chunk, containing a RIFF header with the FourCC ‘WEBP,’ followed by the VP8 or VP8L chunk, containing a header followed by the VP8 or VP8L data.</p>			<p>See <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">WebP Project Page</a> for more detailed information on WebP file format.</p>			<p>				<b>Uses of WebP:</b>			</p>			<p>WebP was developed to reduce the size of images to make the web faster with smaller and richer photos, “The <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq">WebP format</a> essentially aims at creating smaller, better looking images that can help make the web faster.” WebP images are intended to replace <fddLink id="fdd000017">JPEG</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000133">GIF</fddLink> on the internet. According to <a href="https://www.adobe.com/">Adobe.com’s</a>				<a href="https://www.adobe.com/creativecloud/file-types/image/raster/webp-file.html">WebP Files</a> page, “Google created the WebP file format to make online image less bulky. With significantly reduced photo and graphic sizes, website load faster and give users a better experience.”</p>		</fdd:description>		<fdd:shortDescription>WebP is a raster image file format for providing lossless and lossy compression for images on the web.</fdd:shortDescription>		<fdd:productionPhase/>		<fdd:relationships>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:id>fdd000025</fdd:id>					<fdd:shortName>RIFF</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>Resource Interchange File Format (RIFF)</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP file consists of VP8 or VP8L image data, and a container based on RIFF.”</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:id>fdd000578</fdd:id>					<fdd:shortName>VP8</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>VP8</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP file consists of VP8 or VP8L image data, and a container based on RIFF.”</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:shortName>VP8L</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>VP8L</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>					<br/>Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP file consists of VP8 or VP8L image data, and a container based on RIFF.” Not described separately at this time. See <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/webp_lossless_bitstream_specification">Specification for WebP Lossless Bitstream</a> for more information.</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:shortName>WebP 2</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>WebP 2</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>Not described separately at this time. See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> for more information.</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>		</fdd:relationships>	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>	<fdd:localUse>		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress has a small amount of WebP files in its collections. </fdd:experience>		<fdd:preference>See the Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement for format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/stillimg.html">still images works</a>.</fdd:preference>	</fdd:localUse>	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>		<fdd:disclosure>			<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq#why_did_google_release_webp_as_open_source">Open source</a>, anyone can work with the WebP format and suggest improvements.</fdd:disclosure>		<fdd:documentation>			<p>				<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp">Google Developers - WebP Open-Source Project Page</a> provides useful information, guides, references, and support.</p>			<p>				<b>Source Code:</b>			</p>			<p>WebP Container Specification, see <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">(https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container)</a>.</p>			<p>WebP Utilities and Library, see<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/download">(https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/download)</a>.</p>			<p>VP8 Specification, lightweight decoder code. See <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/">(https://www.webmproject.org/docs/)</a>.</p>			<p>RIFF Container Page for WebP Container Specification. See <fddLink id="fdd000025">RIFF</fddLink>. See <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/xaudio2/resource-interchange-file-format--riff-">Microsoft Build Resource Interchange File Format (RIFF)</a>.</p>		</fdd:documentation>		<fdd:adoption>			<p>According to the <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP is natively supported by Google Chrome, Safari, Firefox, Edge, the Opera browser, and many other tools and software libraries. Developers have also added support to a variety of image editing tools.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/download">WebP Project Page WebP Converter Download</a> - encoding tool for PNG, JPEG, or TIFF to WebP and decoding tool for WebP to PNG for Linus, Windows or macOS.</p>			<p>According to <a href="https://caniuse.com/webp">CanIUse.com</a>, the WebP format has over a 97% adoption rate. Up-to-date browser support for WebP on CanIUse.com.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:adoption>		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>			<p>Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp">WebP Project Page</a>, “Except as otherwise noted, the content of this page is licensed under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License</a>, and code samples are licensed under the <a href="https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">Apache 2.0 License</a>. For details, see the <a href="https://developers.google.com/terms/site-policies">Google Developers Site Policies</a>. Java is a registered trademark of <a href="https://www.oracle.com/legal/trademarks.html">Oracle</a> and/or its affiliates.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>		<fdd:transparency>			<p>WebP is a compressed raster image format. Depends upon algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication to build tools.</p>			<p>Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/compression">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP’s lossy compression uses the same methodology as <fddLink id="fdd000578">VP8</fddLink> for predicting (video) frames...The WebP-lossless encoding is based on transforming the image using several different techniques.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:transparency>		<fdd:selfDocumentation>			<p>Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">WebP Project Page</a>, WebP images can have metadata that is stored in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exif">Exif</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extensible_Metadata_Platform">XMP</a> formats.</p>			<ul>				<li>Exif: photo metadata, standard for recorded image and sound files specifying formatting tags.</li>				<li>XMP: digital document metadata, ISO standard for creation, processing, and interchange of metadata for digital documents.</li>			</ul>			<p>Additional metadata guidance: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metadata_Working_Group">Metadata Working Group’s</a>				<a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/software.tagthatphoto.com/docs/mwg_guidance.pdf">Guidelines for Handling Metadata</a>.</p>			<p>According to <a href="https://webflow.com/">WebFlow.com’s</a> blog, <a href="https://webflow.com/blog/webp-images">WebP Images: What They Are and How They Are Helpful in Building for the Web</a>, August 2022, “Metadata is useful for giving digital context to images — for example, time and location data attached to an image from a digital camera. Users can add tags and short descriptions to images with metadata that help search engines identify images, boosting SEO.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:selfDocumentation>		<fdd:externalDependencies>			<p>None beyond availability of supporting software/hardware.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:externalDependencies>		<fdd:techProtection>			<p>None.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:techProtection>	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>		<fdd:stillImageQF>			<fdd:normalImage>				<p>Good support. Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP typically achieves an average of 30% more compression than JPEG and JPEG 2000, without loss of image quality.”</p>				<p>					<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/c_study">WebP Project Comparative Study</a> of WebP, <fddLink id="fdd000017">JPEG</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000143">JPEG 2000</fddLink>.</p>				<p>According to Emil Nova in <a href="https://blog.scaleflex.com/best-web-image-formats/">Most Popular Web Image Formats: Full Overview &amp; Comparison</a>, February 2022, “WebP was conceived as a replacement for some of the best image formats on the web...It uses lossy compression and can produce images that are smaller that JPEGs with sacrificing any quality.”</p>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:normalImage>			<fdd:clarity>				<p>Some support. Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP is bitstream-compatible with VP8 (fdd000578) and uses 14 bits for width and height. The maximum pixel dimensions of a WebP image s 16383 x 16383.”</p>				<p>Lossy compression is adjustable, users can choose higher image quality/file size or lower image quality/file size.</p>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:clarity>			<fdd:colorMaint>				<p>WebP supports 24-bit RBG Color. Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq">WebP Project Page</a>, “Consistent with the VP8 bitstream, lossy WebP works exclusively with an 8-bit <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YCbCr">Y’CbCR</a>					<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chroma_subsampling#4:2:0">4:2:0 (YUV420)</a> image format...Lossless WebP works exclusively with RGB format.”</p>				<p>See <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc6386/">RFC 6386 VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide</a>, Section 2, Format Overview for more detailed information.</p>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:colorMaint>			<fdd:graphics>				<p>Some support. WebP files are raster images, built from pixels.</p>				<p>According to <a href="https://www.fileformat.com/">FileFormat.com</a>, <a href="https://docs.fileformat.com/image/webp/">What is a WebP File?</a>, WebP images provide support for transparency with a “8-bit alpha channel useful for graphical images.”</p>				<p>Chromium Blog, <a href="https://blog.chromium.org/2011/11/lossless-and-transparency-encoding-in.html">Lossless and Transparency Encoding in WebP</a>, 2011, states “Photographic images typically encoded as JPEG can be encoded in WebP lossy mode to achieve smaller file size. Icons and graphics can be encoded better in WebP lossless mode than in PNG. WebP lossy with alpha can be used to create transparent images that have minimal visual degradation yet are much smaller in file size.”</p>				<ul>					<li>Alpha channel has 256 color levels of gray, black (0) to white (255), white is visible, black is transparent, level of gray equals level of visible background. See <a href="https://www.axialis.com/">Axialis.com’s</a>						<a href="https://www.axialis.com/tutorials/create-transparent-image-with-photoshop.html">Tutorial: Create a Transparent Image with Adobe Photoshop</a> for more detailed information about Alpha channels.</li>				</ul>				<p>WebP images do support transparency. Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp">WebP Project Page</a>, “Lossless WebP supports transparency (also known as alpha channel) at a cost of just 22% additional bytes...Lossy WebP also supports transparency, typically providing 3x smaller file sizes compared to PNG.”</p>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:graphics>			<fdd:multispectral>				<p>No support. Little to no information found on support for multispectral bands.</p>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:multispectral>			<fdd:beyondImage>				<p>Some support. WebP images have animation support on the following browsers, Google Chrome 32+, Microsoft Edge 18+, Firefox 65+, Opera 19+, and Safari 14+</p>				<p>Per <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container">WebP Project Page</a>, <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container#animation">WebP supports Animation</a>, image data consists of multiple frames, controlled by ANIM and ANMF chunks.</p>				<ul>					<li>ANIM: contains global parameters of animation, ie., background color, loop count.</li>					<li>ANMF: contains information about a single frame, ie., frame x, frame y, width, height, duration, reserved, blending method, disposal method, frame data.</li>				</ul>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:beyondImage>		</fdd:stillImageQF>	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>		<fdd:signifiersGroup>			<fdd:filenameExtension>				<fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:sigValue>webp</fdd:sigValue>				</fdd:sigValues>				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container#naming">https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container#naming</a>.</fdd:note>			</fdd:filenameExtension>			<fdd:internetMediaType>				<fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:sigValue>image/webp</fdd:sigValue>				</fdd:sigValues>				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container#naming">https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container#naming</a>.</fdd:note>			</fdd:internetMediaType>			<fdd:magicNumbers>				<fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 52 49 46 46 xx xx xx xx 57 45 42 50 56 50 38</fdd:sigValue>					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: RIFF xx xx xx xx WEBPVP8</fdd:sigValue>				</fdd:sigValues>				<fdd:note>The first 4 bytes are 0x52, 0x49, 0x46, 0x46 ('RIFF'), followed by 4 bytes for the RIFF chunk size. The next 7 bytes are 0x57, 0x45, 0x42, 0x50, 0x56, 0x50, 0x38 ('WEBPVP8'). See <a href=" https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/webp"> https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/webp </a>				</fdd:note>			</fdd:magicNumbers>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>FOURCC</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>WEBP</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container#webp_file_header">https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container#webp_file_header</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/566</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Lossy. See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/566">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/566</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/567</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Lossless. See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/567">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/567</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/568</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Extended. See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/568">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/568</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q62617958</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP, type of image file format. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62617958">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62617958</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q683370 </fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Lossless, version of the WebP image file format. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q683370">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q683370</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q4598100</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Lossy, version of the WebP image file format. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q4598100">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q4598100</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q62617999</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Container Specification, technical specification. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62617999">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62617999</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q62618616</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Extended Lossless, version of the WebP image file format. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62618616">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62618616</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q62618601</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Extended Lossy. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62618601">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62618601</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q45989477</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP Extended, version of the WebP image file format. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q45989477">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q45989477</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q103815271</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>WebP 2, successor of the WebP image format. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q103815271 ">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q103815271</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>		</fdd:signifiersGroup>	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>	<fdd:notes>		<fdd:general>Per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebP#WebP_2">WebP Wikipedia page</a>, Google started developing a second version of WebP, reference implementation is libwebp2, with a goal of reaching similar compression ratios as AVIF, but October 2022 <a href="https://chromium.googlesource.com/codecs/libwebp2/">WebP 2’s development repository</a> stated “WebP 2 will not be released as an image format.”</fdd:general>		<fdd:history>			<p>WebP was originally created by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On2_Technologies">On2 Technologies</a> as a proprietary format, but shortly after acquiring On2 Technologies in 2010, Google announced the open format for lossy compressing graphics for the web, WebP.</p>		</fdd:history>	</fdd:notes>	<fdd:usefulReferences>		<fdd:urls>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Google Developers</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://developers.google.com/speed/webp</link>							<tag>An Image Format for the Web</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/riff_container</link>							<tag>WebP Container Specification</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/compression</link>							<tag>Compression Techniques</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/faq</link>							<tag>Frequently Asked Questions</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/docs/c_study</link>							<tag>Comparative Study</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://developers.google.com/speed/webp/download</link>							<tag>Downloading and Installing WebP</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://developers.google.com/terms/site-policies</link>							<tag>Site Policies</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>WebM Project</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/</link>							<tag>WebM: An Open Web Media Project</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/code/#libwebp-webp-image-library</link>							<tag>Developer Overview</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/docs/</link>							<tag>Documentation</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>IETF Datatracker</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc6386/</link>							<tag>RFC 6386 - VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-zern-webp/</link>							<tag>WebP Image Format</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-zern-webp/03/</link>							<tag>WebP Image Format Media Type Registration</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/image/webp</link>					<tag>Iana.org - WebP</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>The National Archives</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/Format/proFormatSearch.aspx?status=detailReport&amp;id=1354</link>							<tag>WebP Lossy</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/Format/proFormatSearch.aspx?status=detailReport&amp;id=1355</link>							<tag>WebP Lossless</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/Format/proFormatSearch.aspx?status=detailReport&amp;id=1356</link>							<tag>WebP Extended</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/xaudio2/resource-interchange-file-format--riff-</link>					<tag>Learn.Microsoft.com - Resource Interchange Filr Format (RIFF)</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://99designs.com/blog/tips/webp-image-format/</link>					<tag>99Designs.com - What is WebP? Pros and Cons of this Next-Gen Image Format</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.adobe.com/creativecloud/file-types/image/raster/webp-file.html</link>					<tag>Adobe.com - WebP Files</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Wikipedia.org</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebP</link>							<tag>WebP</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exif</link>							<tag>Exif</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extensible_Metadata_Platform</link>							<tag>Extensible Metadata Platform</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metadata_Working_Group</link>							<tag>Metadata Working Group</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Wikidata.org</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62617958</link>							<tag>WebP</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q683670</link>							<tag>WebP Lossless</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q45989100</link>							<tag>WebP Lossy</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62618616</link>							<tag>WebP Extended Lossless</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q62618601</link>							<tag>WebP Extended Lossy</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q63437758</link>							<tag>libwebp</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q103815271</link>							<tag>WebP 2</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://webflow.com/blog/webp-images</link>					<tag>WebFlow.com - WebP Images: What They Are and How They Are Helpful in Building for the Web</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://s3.amazonaws.com/software.tagthatphoto.com/docs/mwg_guidance.pdf</link>					<tag>Guidelines for Handing Image Metadata PDF</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.axialis.com/tutorials/create-transparent-image-with-photoshop.html</link>					<tag>Axialis.com - Create a Transparent Image with Alpha Channel</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://docs.fileformat.com/image/webp/</link>					<tag>FileFormat.com - What is a WebP File?</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://blog.chromium.org/2011/11/lossless-and-transparency-encoding-in.html</link>					<tag>Blog.Chromium.org - Lossless and Transparency Encoding in WebP</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.cs.cornell.edu/courses/cs5220/2017fa/tar-info.html</link>					<tag>CS.Cornell.edu - Working with Tarballs</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</link>					<tag>CreativeCommons.org - Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</link>					<tag>Apache.org - Apache License, Version 2.0</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.oracle.com/legal/trademarks.html</link>					<tag>Oracle.com - Legal Noties</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://caniuse.com/webp</link>					<tag>CanIUse.com - WebP</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>		</fdd:urls>	</fdd:usefulReferences></fdd:FDD>