<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000500" titleName="glTF (GL Transmission Format) 2.0" shortName="glTF_2_0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>model</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-group</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>container-bundle</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2019-06-16</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>GL Transmission Format (glTF) 2.0</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>3D model formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The glTF 2.0 format is the most widely used chronological version of the glTF family of formats, published by the <a href="https://www.khronos.org/">Khronos Group</a> in June 2017.  glTF is intended as a vendor-neutral distribution format for 3D content, bridging the gap between 3D content creation tools and applications and applications displaying 3D graphics.  Its originators described it as the &quot;JPEG of 3D&quot; or as a 3D content format for &quot;the last mile.&quot;  See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink> for a general description.</p>
			<p>glTF2.0 was a major upgrade in relation to glTF1.0, and is not backwards compatible.  glTF 1.0 is widely considered obsolete. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>The <a href="https://www.khronos.org/news/press/khronos-releases-gltf-2.0-specification">Khronos press release for glTF 2.0</a> stated, &quot;The release of glTF 2.0 delivers a significant upgrade to glTF 1.0, an extensible, runtime neutral, open standard format for real-time delivery of 3D assets, which describes full scenes with compact transmission and fast load time. In response to major functionality requests from the developer community using glTF 1.0, the release of glTF 2.0 adds Physically Based Rendering (PBR) for portable, consistent description of materials. In glTF 1.0, a material was defined with a GLSL shader, which suited WebGL, but was problematic when importing a glTF model into a Direct3D or Metal application. Through using PBR, visually arresting glTF 2.0 models are now consistently portable to any rendering API. A PBR material is defined by a few concise parameters that can be used to generate shaders for any rendering API. glTF 2.0 defines a simple to implement, but powerful, PBR model that provides high-quality materials, and yet, is scalable to suit the capabilities of different classes of platform and device.&quot; &quot;Including the addition of PBR-based materials, glTF 2.0 is a stable base for the future and will support practical runtime implementations for many graphics APIs. It includes updates to improve consistency, API-neutrality, and performance and will enable the industry to move to PBR material models.&quot;</p>
			<p>For the general structure of glTF as a cluster of files, see description in <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink> and the <a href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF/blob/master/specification/2.0/figures/files.png">figure showing component files</a> from the <a href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF/tree/master/specification/2.0/">glTF 2.0 specification</a>. The <a href="https://www.khronos.org/files/gltf20-reference-guide.pdf">glTF 2.0 Quick Reference Guide</a> provides a compact summary of glTF features.  The PBR model included in the core specification of glTF 2.0 is known as the &quot;metallic-roughness material model.&quot;  This model uses three parameters: baseColorFactor (base color of the material); metallicFactor (metalness of the material); and roughnessFactor (roughness of the material).</p>
			<p>glTF defines an extensibility mechanism, which is proving a widely used feature.  See <a href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF/blob/master/extensions/README.md">glTF Extension Registry</a>.  As of June 2019, glTF 2.0 has five extensions ratified by Khronos.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>KHR_draco_mesh_compression</b>: Allows glTF to support streaming compressed geometry data instead of the raw data.  This extension appears likely to be widely used. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>. See, for example, <a href="https://cesium.com/blog/2018/04/09/draco-compression/">Draco Compressed Meshes with glTF and 3D Tiles</a>, (April 2018) and <a href="https://cesium.com/blog/2019/02/05/3d-tiles-ogc-community-standard/">3D Tiles Now an OGC Community Standard for Streaming Massive 3D Geospatial Content</a> (February 2019), both blog posts from Cesium.</li>
				<li>
					<b>KHR_lights_punctual</b>: Supports definition of a set of light sources within a scene.</li>
				<li>
					<b>KHR_materials_pbrSpecularGlossiness</b>: Allows use of the PBR specular-glossiness material model.  For a comparison between the metallic-roughness and specular-glossiness models for materials, see clause 4.5 of <a href="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/4146/b2ce58b95cfc1641fd78d352fd2ce640de3a.pdf">Automatic Optimization of 3D Mesh Data for Real-Time Online Presentation</a>, a dissertation by Max Alfons Limper.  The metallic-roughness material model can be used to represent a wide range of real-world materials and is more widely used. The specular-glossiness model offers more options; it can represent some real-world materials more faithfully, but can also model materials that cannot exist in the real world.</li>
				<li>
					<b>KHR_materials_unlit</b>: Allows an unlit shading model.  Three motivating uses cases for unlit materials include: mobile devices with limited resources; photogrammetry, in which lighting information is already present; and stylized materials, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anime">anime</a>.</li>
				<li>
					<b>KHR_texture_transform</b>:  To reduce load times for a model with many texture images, some rendering engines encourage packing many low-resolution textures into a single large texture atlas.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Some extensions are vendor-specific.  According to <a href="https://www.engineering.com/Hardware/ArticleID/17765/3D-Scanning-the-Past-at-the-Smithsonian.aspx">3D Scanning the Past at the Smithsonian</a>, an article from October 2018, the Smithsonian&apos;s Digitization Program Office team is working on an extension to the glTF file format to add support for annotations.  All extensions used in a model must be listed in the top-level <i>extensionsUsed</i> array; required extensions are listed in the <i>extensionsRequired</i> array.  A best practice for extensions is to allow safe fallback consumption in tools that do not recognize an extension in the <i>extensionsUsed</i> array.  All KHR extensions are designed this way.</p>
			<p>The compilers of this resource have not attempted to determine the degree to which the individual extensions are used or supported in tools.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>version 2.0 of royalty-free specification designed as efficient, extensible, interoperable asset delivery format for the transmission and loading of 3D content.  Developed as an open project by the Khronos Group.  Version 2.0 is widely supported.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>A final-state format used for delivery to a web browser or other viewing software or device.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000498</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>glTF_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>GL Transmission Format (glTF) Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Contains</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000381</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>JSON</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>JavaScript Object Notation</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Equivalent to</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Binary glTF, with extension .glb, not described separately on this website.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>Khronos is an industry consortium focused on cooperatively creating open API standards for graphics, compute, and vision acceleration that are available for royalty-free use.  See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink> for more information about the Khronos Group.</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>The <a href="https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF/blob/master/specification/2.0/README.md">glTF v 2.0 specification</a> is available on github.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>glTF 2.0 has been rapidly adopted by a large number of applications related to 3D content.  Several sections of the <a href="https://www.khronos.org/gltf/">glTF Overview</a> from Khronos illustrate adoption: a graphic illustrating the position of glTF in an ecosystem of applications; a collection of logos for major adopters, and an extensive list of tools and applications that can import or export the format</p>
			<p>According to <a href="https://sketchfab.com/blogs/community/sketchfab-now-largest-online-repository-gltf-files/">Sketchfab is now the largest online repository of glTF files</a> from August 2017, &quot;glTF is quickly becoming the standard file transfer format for 3D, AR and VR assets.&quot;  Sketchfab introduced support for glTF in December 2016.  WorldViz added support for glTF to some of its products in August 2018 and posted an announcement titled <a href="https://www.worldviz.com/post/gltf-is-a-huge-deal-for-vr-ar-heres-why-were-embracing-it">glTF is a Huge Deal for VR + AR. Here&apos;s Why We&apos;re Embracing It</a>.  IKEA describes its use of glTF in its catalog in <a href="https://www.khronos.org/assets/uploads/developers/library/2018-gltf-ecosystem-forum/glTF-Forum-IKEA-and-Visual-Consistency-SIGGRAPH_Aug18.pdf">IKEA &amp; 3D</a>.  Another repository of 3D content is TurboSquid, which announced <a href="https://www.khronos.org/blog/turbosquid-adds-gltf-to-supported-formats-for-its-stemcell-initiative">TurboSquid adds glTF to supported formats for its StemCell initiative</a> in July 2018.</p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://medium.com/@akashkuttappa/updates-on-gltf-from-mozilla-adobe-facebook-google-microsoft-at-gdc-2019-a0be5c1afa79">Updates on glTF from Mozilla, Adobe, Facebook, Google &amp; Microsoft at GDC 2019</a> describes contributions to and use of glTF from major software developers.  In 2016, Microsoft introduced <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2016/10/26/introducing-3d-for-everyone/">&quot;3D for everyone&quot;</a> and the Paint 3D product.  By 2019, 3D models could be inserted into documents created in Word, Powerpoint, and Excel from Microsoft.  Mozilla has introduced Hubs, where you can &quot;share a virtual room with friends.&quot;  Facebook now supports 3D posts and 3D photos. Another major software vendor using glTF is Esri, whose <a href="https://doc.arcgis.com/en/cityengine/latest/whats-new/cityengine-release-notes.htm#ESRI_SECTION1_97F26EA1BD2748B8985FF0DB85E08A5C">CityEngine 2019.0</a> supports glTF for import and export, including glTF 2.0 and Binary glTF.</p>
			<p>In October 2018, Khronos and the Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) <a href="https://www.khronos.org/news/press/ogc-and-khronos-form-a-liaison-to-improve-interoperability-within-the-geospatial-and-3d-graphics-communities">announced</a> a collaboration. The two organizations will work jointly to develop use cases and requirements for open geospatial standards concerning 3D, VR and AR APIs, and related graphical representations.  For example, the OGC specification for 3D Tiles incorporates glTF 2.0 as a normative reference.  See <a href="http://docs.opengeospatial.org/cs/18-053r2/18-053r2.html">3D Tiles Specification 1.0 (November 2018)</a>.</p>
			<p>The Smithsonian is using glTF, as indicated in <a href="https://www.engineering.com/Hardware/ArticleID/17765/3D-Scanning-the-Past-at-the-Smithsonian.aspx">3D Scanning the Past at the Smithsonian</a>. In <a href="https://github.com/Smithsonian/dpo-cook/blob/master/doc/pages/tasks/convertMesh.md">Task: ConvertMesh</a>, the Smithsonian indicates that it uses FBX2glTF to create glTFfiles in its workflow for 3D digitization, with optional use of Draco compression.  Also using glTF to illustrate its efforts is NASA, for example, with this <a href="https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/2383/hubble-space-telescope-3d-model/">Hubble Space Telescope 3D Model</a>
			</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:otherQF>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Geometry</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Appearance</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.  glTF 2.0 introduced support for Physically Based Rendering (PBR) as an option for defining surface characteristics. The PBR model included in the core specification is the &quot;metallic-roughness material model.&quot;</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Scene</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Animation</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.  glTF 2.0 introduced support for animation using instantiated <i>Morph Targets</i>.  Starting with version 2.0, glTF supports the definition of morph targets for meshes. A morph target stores displacements or differences for certain mesh attributes. At runtime, these differences may be added to the original mesh, with different weights, in order to animate parts of the mesh. This is often used in character animations, for example, to encode different facial expressions of a virtual character.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
		</fdd:otherQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>gltf</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For the JSON-formatted file with the full scene description.   See specification and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/model/gltf+json">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>model/gltf+json</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For the JSON-formatted file with the full scene description.  See specification and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/model/gltf+json">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>Not found.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>As of June 2019, there is no PRONOM entry for glTF 2.0.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>Not found.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>As of June 2019, there is no Wikidata entry specifically for glTF 2.0.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>glb</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For Binary glTF.  See specification and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/model/gltf-binary">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>model/gltf-binary</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For Binary glTF.  See specification and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/model/gltf-binary">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: glTF</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>HEX: 0x46546C67</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For Binary glTF.  See specification and <a href="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/model/gltf-binary">IANA registration</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000498">glTF_family</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>Version 2.0 of glTF was officially released in June 2017, after a period of beta testing.</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF/blob/master/specification/2.0/README.md</link>
					<tag>glTF version 2.0 specification</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.khronos.org/gltf/</link>
					<tag>Khronos | glTF Overview </tag>
					<comment>Describes glTF as the &quot;JPEG of 3D.&quot;  Has graphics describing glTF &quot;ecosystem&quot; and showing industry support.  Lists tools.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF/blob/master/specification/2.0/figures/gltfOverview-2.0.0b.png</link>
					<tag>Infographic on the basics of glTF 2.0</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/KhronosGroup/glTF-Sample-Viewer</link>
					<tag>glTF 2.0 Sample Viewer</tag>
					<comment>Viewer (based on WebGL) has built-in menu of sample images demonstrating features of glTF 2.0.  Can render local glTF files (including .glb) by means of drag-and-drop.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khronos_Group</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for Khronos Group</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to physically based rendering (PBR), an approach in computer graphics for rendering graphics in a way that models the flow of light in the real world. glTF 2.0 includes an implementation of PBR for portable, consistent description of materials.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physically_based_rendering</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for Physically Based Rendering (PBR)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.pbr-book.org/</link>
							<tag>Physically Based Rendering:
From Theory To Implementation | book by Matt Pharr, Wenzel Jakob, and Greg Humphreys (2004-2018)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/4146/b2ce58b95cfc1641fd78d352fd2ce640de3a.pdf</link>
							<tag>Automatic Optimization of 3D Mesh Data for Real-Time Online Presentation | dissertation by Max Alfons Limper</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.substance3d.com/pbr-guide</link>
							<tag>Substance Academy: PBR Guide | by Wes McDermott</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to DRACO, an open-source library for compressing and decompressing 3D geometric meshes and point clouds.  Available as an extension to glTF.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://google.github.io/draco/</link>
							<tag>DRACO website</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://github.com/google/draco</link>
							<tag>DRACO github repository</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.khronos.org/news/press/khronos-announces-gltf-geometry-compression-extension-google-draco</link>
							<tag>Khronos press release for glTF extension using Google DRACO technology (February 15, 2018)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://cesium.com/blog/2018/04/09/draco-compression/</link>
							<tag>Draco Compressed Meshes with glTF and 3D Tiles | blog post April 9, 2018</tag>
							<comment>Announces support for glTF in Cesium 3D Tiles.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Selected Wikipedia entries for techniques associated with 3D modeling and computer graphics.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physically_based_rendering</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for Physically based rendering (PBR), a computer graphic technique for visual representation of materials</tag>
							<comment>glTF 2.0 introduced the use of PBR for metallic materials.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morph_target_animation</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for Morph Target animation</tag>
							<comment>Supported in glTF 2.0.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Selected resources illustrating support for glTF</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.khronos.org/assets/uploads/developers/library/2019-open-ar-cloud/Khronos-Update-Open-AR-Cloud-Symposium_May19.pdf</link>
							<tag>Khronos Update: Open standards in Augmented Reality | Presentation in April 2019</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.worldviz.com/post/gltf-is-a-huge-deal-for-vr-ar-heres-why-were-embracing-it</link>
							<tag>glTF is a Huge Deal for VR + AR. Here&apos;s Why We&apos;re Embracing It | blog post from WorldViz</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://blog.turbosquid.com/2018/07/20/support-for-gltf-coming-to-stemcell/</link>
							<tag>Support for glTF Coming to StemCell | blog post from TurboSquid (July 2018)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.khronos.org/blog/turbosquid-adds-gltf-to-supported-formats-for-its-stemcell-initiative</link>
							<tag>TurboSquid adds glTF to supported formats for its StemCell initiative | blog post at Khronos (July 2018)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.khronos.org/blog/google-and-binomial-contribute-basis-universal-texture-format-to-khronos-gltf-3d-transmission-open-standard</link>
							<tag>Google and Binomial Contribute Basis Universal Texture Format to Khronos’ glTF 3D Transmission Open Standard</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.worldviz.com/post/gltf-is-a-huge-deal-for-vr-ar-heres-why-were-embracing-it</link>
							<tag>glTF is a Huge Deal for VR + AR. Here&apos;s Why We&apos;re Embracing It</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.khronos.org/assets/uploads/developers/library/2018-gltf-ecosystem-forum/glTF-Forum-IKEA-and-Visual-Consistency-SIGGRAPH_Aug18.pdf</link>
							<tag>IKEA &amp; 3D (last 12 years) | from IKEA (2018)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://medium.com/@akashkuttappa/updates-on-gltf-from-mozilla-adobe-facebook-google-microsoft-at-gdc-2019-a0be5c1afa79</link>
							<tag>Updates on glTF from Mozilla, Adobe, Facebook, Google &amp; Microsoft at GDC 2019 | blog post (March 2019)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.engineering.com/Hardware/ArticleID/17765/3D-Scanning-the-Past-at-the-Smithsonian.aspx</link>
							<tag>3D Scanning the Past at the Smithsonian</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/resources/2383/hubble-space-telescope-3d-model/</link>
							<tag>Hubble Space Telescope 3D Model | From NASA</tag>
							<comment>Published on April 22, 2019</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
