<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000491" titleName="Universal 3D (U3D) format family. ECMA-363, Editions 1-4" shortName="U3D_family" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>model</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>family</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2018-10-04</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Universal 3D (U3D) format family. ECMA-363, Editions 1-4.</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>3D model formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The Universal 3D File Format (U3D) is a binary format based on technology developed by Intel Corporation in the late 1990s and first published as the standard <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-363.htm">ECMA-363</a> in December 2004 after consideration by ECMA International&apos;s Technical Committee 43 (TC43).  The stated intention for the format specification was &quot;for downstream 3D CAD [computer-aided design] repurposing and visualization purposes.&quot;  Four editions of ECMA-363 were published between December 2004 and June 2007.  The 3rd Edition of U3D (June 2006) is the most widely used, frequently as an encoding wrapped in a PDF rather than as a free-standing file.  See <a href="#notes">History Notes</a> below for more details on the early background for U3D.  Since the publication of the <fddLink id="fdd000276">PDF 1.6</fddLink> format by Adobe in November 2004, PDF documents have been able to include 3D art in the U3D encoding, but the latest edition cited as a normative reference in PDF specifications has been the 3rd Edition.   Important features introduced in the 4th Edition also do not appear to have been implemented in the software library released by Intel.  Although this description covers the four editions, it focuses on the 3rd Edition.  See <a href="#notes">History Notes</a> below for more about the 4th Edition.</p>
			<p>The 3rd Edition of the U3D specification states that the purpose &quot;is to provide a reliable, easy to use, easy to implement file format that supports the streaming, progressive transmission, of 3D mesh and level of detail information in a standard way. ... The motivation for this file format is to address the growing need to reuse existing 3D data for applications and usage models downstream from the engineering or design uses for which the data was originally created.&quot;  Elsewhere, the specification describes U3D as &quot;an extensible format for
downstream 3D CAD repurposing and visualization, useful for many mainstream
business applications.&quot; An <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/activities/Communications/U3D-presentation-public.pdf">informal description of the format</a> was provided by TC43 in April 2007 as a slideshow. Features emphasized in the specification and slideshow include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Execution architecture that facilitates run-time modification of geometry and progressive data streaming and playback</li>
				<li>Pre-computed continuous level of detail (CLOD).  Enables applications to increase or decrease model complexity based
on needed quality or performance.  Facilitates zooming and scaling.</li>
				<li>Key-frame and bones-based animation.  See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeletal_animation">Wikipedia entry on skeletal animation</a>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>U3D has been and is widely used for embedding artwork in PDF files.  Its past use as a neutral transfer format between applications has decreased because U3D lacks support for features considered essential in some domains and is no longer actively maintained as a standard. For more indications that use of and support for U3D is more likely to decline over time than to increase, see <a href="#sustainability">Adoption</a> under Sustainability Factors; <a href="#factors">Quality and Functionality Factors</a>; and Characteristics for the Market for 3D Technology under <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
			<p>
				<b>File Structure</b>:  The U3D format is a complex little-endian binary format.  The structure of a U3D file and the semantic architecture of the underlying model reflect a desire for computationally efficient rendering and manipulation of an object and small files for transmission and loading into memory. The semantics of the U3D model architecture involve several key elements: nodes, the scene graph, resources, and palettes. Nodes have spatial information and hierarchical relationships that build the scene graph. Together, a node and a resource compose a 3D object, that is, an independent part of the overall 3D scene.  In U3D, palettes support an index mechanism to provide efficient access to the nodes and resources and to permit re-use of resources that represent elements such as the geometry of a shape, lighting, shading, and textures, etc.  For example, a 3D shape is one resource, while separate palettes can indicate different instances of that shape with different colors or textures applied. Or the same texture can be applied to different shapes.</p>
			<p>A U3D file is structured as a sequence of blocks. The first block is the File Header Block, the only required block for a U3D file.  The header includes a &quot;profile indicator&quot; that will indicate if the file uses extensibility features of the format and whether or not the default compression specific to U3D is applied.  Each block begins with a <i>blocktype</i> value, with valid 32-bit values defined in the specification in hexadecimal (Hex).   For example, the blocktype for the File Header Block is Hex 00443355 (U3D in ASCII, which acts as a magic number for the file format).  Other examples include FFFFFF22 for a Model Node and FFFFFF51 for a Light Resource.  All blocks have the same basic structure. The blocktype value and values for the size of the block&apos;s data and metadata determine how the remainder of the block is interpreted by the loader. Padding fields are used to keep 32-bit alignment relative to the start of the File Header Block.</p>
			<p>Each architecture element is represented by a declaration block and zero or more continuation blocks; apart from the elements specifying 3D geometry for shapes, most elements are represented fully in the declaration block.  The declaration blocks, which come first in the file, contain enough information to create a shape or other resource and locate it appropriately in an in-memory data structure.  Each block has a data section and a metadata section. The format of the data section will vary based on the blocktype.  The format of all metadata sections is a sequence of key/value pairs.</p>
			<p>The specification defines a bit-encoding algorithm which serves as a specialized lossless compression scheme. Rather than compressing the file content as a whole, values within a block&apos;s data section are compressed.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Intended as a neutral format for downstream 3D CAD repurposing and visualization purposes.  Published as ECMA-363 Universal 3D File Format in 4 editions, between December 2004 and June 2007.  The 3rd Edition of U3D is the most widely used, particularly as an encoding wrapped in a PDF.
</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>
			<p>Intended as a middle-state format to enable a variety of end user applications with 3D data created in design applications.  As of late 2018, the primary use of U3D by end users is as the encoding for a stream wrapped in the PDF file format.</p>
		</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000030</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF (Portable Document Format) Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>3D artwork in the U3D encoding may be contained in various subtypes of the PDF format family, including <fddLink id="fdd000276">PDF_1_6</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000277">PDF_1_7</fddLink> (ISO 32000-1:2008) and PDF/E.  The last is not described separately on this website at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>No direct experience.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress has not yet expressed any format preference for digital models used as designs or surrogates for 3-dimensional objects.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard, published in four editions by Ecma International as ECMA-363, under the auspices of <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/memento/tc43.htm">Technical Committee 43</a>.  As of 2018, TC43 has been inactive for many years.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>Four editions of the ECMA-363 Universal 3D File Format are accessible from <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-363.htm">http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-363.htm</a>.  The most widely used version is <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/ECMA-363%203rd%20edition.pdf">ECMA-363 3rd Edition</a>.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The U. S. National Archives lists U3D as acceptable for the <a href="https://www.archives.gov/records-mgmt/policy/transfer-guidance-tables.html">transfer of Computer Aided Design (CAD)</a> files.</p>
			<p>As of 2018, the most frequent use of the U3D format is widely reported as an encoding embedded in PDF documents.  See, for example, <a href="https://www.pdf3d.com/u3d/">About U3D</a> from PDF3D.com.  A number of articles and other resources related to this use of U3D are listed in <a href="#references">Useful References</a> below.  Examples are <a href="https://www.elsevier.com/authors/author-services/data-visualization/interactive-u3d-models">Interactive U3D models</a>, from Elsevier instructions for authors and <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/794/">Towards an easier creation of three-dimensional data for embedding into scholarly 3D PDF (Portable Document Format) files</a>, an article published in PeerJ by Axel Newe.  However, support in the PDF standard and in Adobe products is only for Editions 1 through 3 of ECMA-363</p>
			<p>Given the lack of implementations that support features added in Edition 4 of ECMA-363 and the fact that there is no ongoing support for the <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/u3d/">Universal 3D Sample Software</a>, some software products have dropped support for U3D (see <a href="https://forum.solidworks.com/thread/88561">Why has the u3d export format been removed in SolidWorks 2015?</a>) and documentation for other tools lists limitations (e.g., <a href="https://www.okino.com/conv/exp_u3d.htm#limitations">Okino</a>).</p>
			<p>U3D and PRC are the two formats supported by PDF standards for embedding 3D artwork in documents.  <a href="https://www.pdf3d.com/understanding-how-pdfe-u3d-and-prc-are-related-to-3d-pdf/">PDF3D.com</a> states that PRC is generally preferable because it is &quot;significantly more feature rich than U3D, allows highly compressed geometric and visual representations to be added to 3D models and allows detailed structure, geometry and product manufacturing information (PMI) to be included.&quot;  However, the same site provides reasons to select U3D:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>More legacy viewing applications support U3D, including Adobe Acrobat back to version 7.x</li>
				<li>Need to use advanced features such as mesh representations with continuous level of detail and animation displacement channels</li>
				<li>Less complex data structures than PRC</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Open source software tools that support the reading and writing of U3D files include: the <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/u3d/">Universal 3D Sample Software</a>; and <a href="http://www.meshlab.net/">Meshlab</a>.  Commercial software includes: <a href="https://www.mevislab.de/mevislab/versions-and-licensing/">MeVisLab</a>; <a href="https://www.pdf3d.com/products/pdf3d-sdk/">PDF3D SDK PRO</a> and several products from the same company.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/activities/Communications/U3D-presentation-public.pdf">A 2007 public presentation by TC43 on the Universal 3D File Format</a> states that no licensing is required for use of the format and that the sample reference code was available under the Apache open source license.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>The U3D format is a complex binary format in which individual values can be compressed using a complex bit-encoding algorithm to enhance performance.  The format requires sophistication to build tools to visualize, render, or animate 3D models. </fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>The format supports the association of individual metadata values with any substructure (e.g., resource or block) within the U3D format, using a key-value representation.  There is no support for embedding XML-based metadata in a recognized schema.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None beyond software capable of reading and writing U3D encoding and files.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>No internal support for encryption.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:otherQF>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Geometry</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>
					<p>The U3D format supports geometry definition using several approaches, including: point clouds, line sets, and triangular meshes with &quot;continuous level of detail&quot; (CLOD).  The 4th Edition introduced an extension to support free-form curves and surfaces defined using uniform and non-uniform, rational and non-rational representations.  However, there appears to be no implementation of the functionality in this extension, which included support for the commonly used NURBS approach for defining surfaces.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.  According to a 2008 report from NCSA (<a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/applied-research/ncsa/8-an-overview-of-3d-data-content-file-formats-and-viewers.pdf">An Overview of 3D Data Content, File Formats and Viewers</a>), U3D does not support constructive solid geometry (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constructive_solid_geometry">CSG</a>) directly.</p>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Appearance</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>Resources related to model appearance that can be represented in U3D include material attributes, texture mapping, and shaders that can specify combinations of material attributes, textures, and lighting.  Texture maps can use images in <fddLink id="fdd000017">JPEG</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000022">TIFF</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000153">PNG</fddLink> formats. Material attributes available are ambient color, diffuse color, specular color, emissive color, opacity,
and reflectivity.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Scene</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>U3D can include a &quot;scene graph&quot; recording the hierarchical and spatial relationships between nodes.  A specialized hierarchical structure supported is known as a &quot;skeleton,&quot; used particularly for animation (see factor for 3D Model Animation below).  Other aspects of scene visualization can be represented in U3D through &quot;light resources&quot; and &quot;view&quot; instances.  Light resource attributes include type (ambient, directional, point, spot), color, and attenuation.  View instances (aka view nodes) provide spatial position and orientation and hierarchical information as well as defining clipping, projections (e.g. one, two or three point perspective or orthogonal), the view port, backdrops and overlays.  Fog can be applied to a scene through another type of view resource.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Animation</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>U3D supports animation using key-frames and skeleton structures (assemblies of bones and joints).  Note: These structures do not have to represent actual bones and skeletons.  See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeletal_animation">Wikipedia entry on skeletal animation</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
		</fdd:otherQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>u3d</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Used for standalone U3D files. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>model/u3d</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>There is no media type registered with IANA for the U3D format.  This value appears in an appendix table in <a href="https://mirror.hmc.edu/ctan/macros/latex/contrib/movie15/doc/movie15.pdf">a description of the
Movie15
package for LaTeX</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 55 33 44 00</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: U3D</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>
					<p>From <a href="http://filext.com/file-extension/U3D">filext.com</a> and other sources.</p>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/702</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/702">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/702</a>. Applies to all format editions.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q974182</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q974182">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q974182</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>3D Model Characteristics</b>:  The quality and functionality factors used above are based on an analysis from 2008 in <a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/applied-research/ncsa/8-an-overview-of-3d-data-content-file-formats-and-viewers.pdf">An Overview of 3D Data Content, File Formats and Viewers</a>, a technical report (ISDA08-002) from the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA).  According to this analysis, the key aspects of a 3D model are: geometry, appearance, scene, and animation. For brief descriptions of these factors, see the table for 3D model formats under <a href="./fdd_explanation.shtml#factors">Quality and functionality factors</a>.  The descriptions there are drawn from the 2008 report and from <a href="https://all3dp.com/3d-file-format-3d-files-3d-printer-3d-cad-vrml-stl-obj/">8 Most Common 3D File Formats of 2018</a> (an article from C|net), which uses the same factors to distinguish formats.</p>
			<p>All 3D formats support some method for representing the geometry (the shape) of an object; support for other aspects is optional depending on the primary use of the format.  Table 3 in the 2008 report, <a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/applied-research/ncsa/8-an-overview-of-3d-data-content-file-formats-and-viewers.pdf">An Overview of 3D Data Content, File Formats and Viewers</a>, compares nine popular 3D formats in use in 2008 based on these four aspects of 3D models.  See also <a href="https://all3dp.com/3d-file-format-3d-files-3d-printer-3d-cad-vrml-stl-obj/">8 Most Common 3D File Formats of 2018</a> for discussion of an overlapping set of formats.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Characteristics for the Market for 3D Technology</b>: As described in <a href="https://www.computer.org/csdl/mags/co/2005/08/r8023.pdf">Making 3D Technology Universal</a>, a 2005 article in Computer Magazine by David Geer, most computer-aided design (CAD) applications tended to use proprietary formats.  Several attempts to develop general-purpose 3D applications and formats for use on the web had failed in the marketplace.  These included Adobe&apos;s Atmosphere, Microsoft&apos;s Chromeffects, and Shockwave&apos;s .w3d formats.   Neil Trevett,
vice president for embedded content at
graphics-chip maker Nvidia, offered reasons beyond technical shortcomings, &quot;because 3D is a
market with so many niches that it is
difficult for a single approach to appeal
to enough  users to succeed;  and
because the technologies weren’t controlled by an open standards body.&quot;</p>
			<p>Both the  <a href="https://www.archives.gov/files/applied-research/ncsa/8-an-overview-of-3d-data-content-file-formats-and-viewers.pdf">NCSA technical report from 2008</a> and the <a href="https://all3dp.com/3d-file-format-3d-files-3d-printer-3d-cad-vrml-stl-obj/">C|net article from 2018</a> cited above mention the large number of 3D formats, well over 100.  See also the lists of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_file_formats#3D_graphics">3D graphics formats</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_file_formats#Computer-aided_design_(CAD)">Computer-aided design formats</a> from Wikipedia.  Many of these are proprietary.  Among &quot;neutral&quot; formats, some are specialized for particular tasks. For example, STL (Stereo Lithography format) is a lightweight format with no support for appearance, scene, or animation, but is the most widely used format for 3D printing.  Others, such as <fddLink id="fdd000448">STEP</fddLink>, are intended to capture all details essential for interchange and archiving of architectural and engineering designs, including parts specifications and tolerances.  In the context of video-games, such details are irrelevant.  A truly universal 3D format appears unlikely to emerge.  A niche for the U3D format seems to be for presentation of 3D models to users without specialized software, usually for purposes of explanation, demonstration, or promotion.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Embedding U3D into PDF</b>: A major use of 3D models is to present them in interactive form to end users without the need for special software; hence a primary use of U3D has become embedding U3D streams in PDF documents.  Beginning with <fddLink id="fdd000276">PDF_1_6</fddLink>, introduced in 2004 in association with Acrobat and Adobe Reader 7, a U3D model can be included in PDF documents using a 3D Stream.  A 3D Annotation specifies how the 3D artwork is to be presented and activated in the document.  The specifications for <fddLink id="fdd000276">PDF_1_6</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000277">PDF_1_7</fddLink> use Edition 1 of the U3D format as a normative reference.  The specification for PDF 2.0 uses Edition 3 of the U3D format as a normative reference.  There is no support in PDF or by Adobe in its products for Edition 4, which was published in 2007.  The lack of support in PDF documents for U3D streams using important features introduced in Edition 4 has resulted in some application software abandoning the use of U3D.</p>
			<p>As stated in <a href="https://www.pdf3d.com/u3d/">https://www.pdf3d.com/u3d/</a>, &quot;U3D is a 3D data structure and file format, one of two systems used in 3D PDF documents. Along side PRC, U3D is the historical foundation used to embed 3D interactive data and models into a PDF file. A PDF file containing U3D based 3D model can be viewed using the Adobe Reader as well as other tools. As the U3D format has been available since 2006, many software systems support U3D export. U3D is also referenced in the ISO PDF/E standard.&quot;  The following statements are based on information from the same site: U3D can be used as a 3D file type for storage and interchange with other U3D-compatible applications; U3D files may be &apos;wrapped&apos; into a PDF file using tools such as <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/acrobat/using/adding-3d-models-pdfs-acrobat.html">Acrobat Pro</a> and the <a href="https://mirror.hmc.edu/ctan/macros/latex/contrib/media9/doc/media9.pdf">media9</a> package for LaTeX; today, U3D is primarily used for 3D PDF internal encoding, rather than as an interchange format.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The origin of the U3D format was in technology from Intel, which had a 3D Architecture Lab in the late 1990s.  This lab developed software originally aimed at game developers, the IFX toolkit, with an associated file format.  A particular feature in the software supported modeling and animating &quot;skeletons,&quot; assemblies of bones and joints; this feature is present in the U3D specification.  A partnership with Macromedia, based on that technology, developed the Shockwave 3D format using .wrd as extension.  See <a href="https://www.okino.com/conv/exp_sw3d.htm">A Short and Current History of the Shockwave-3D File Format</a> from Okino.  Later, Intel formed the 3D Industry Forum (3DIF) to develop the format into a standard and promote its implementation.  This cross-industry group included Adobe, NVidia, ATI, and Fraunhofer among its roughly 40 member organizations; some were developers of 3D technology, others were corporate users.    3DIF proposed the Universal 3D Format for standardization through <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/">Ecma International</a>.  Intel provided the source code for the IFX toolkit as an open source software library for reading and writing U3D files. For more detail on the early background, see <a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/intels-3d-divorce-rate/">Intel&apos;s 3D Divorce Rate</a>, a June 18, 2004 news item from C|Net and the <a href="https://www.pdf3d.com/u3d/">section on History of the U3D File Format</a> (reproduced courtesy of Robert Lansdale of Okino Computer Graphics) in the summary of U3D from <a href="https://www.pdf3d.com/">PDF3D</a> (a provider of tools for embedding 3D artwork in PDF documents).</p>
			<p>Edition 1 of Ecma&apos;s U3D standard, <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-363.htm">ECMA-363</a>, was finalized in December 2004 under the auspices of <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/memento/tc43.htm">Ecma TC43</a>.   Edition 2 was published in August 2004, adding a mechanism for extensibility to the U3D format.  Edition 2 was submitted to ISO/IEC for fast-track processing, a process that was never completed.  Edition 3, published in June 2006, states that changes were made as a result of comments received during the ISO/IEC DIS ballot process. A brief comparison of Editions 2 and 3 of ECMA-363 by the compilers of this resource suggests that the changes were limited to a small number of clarifications.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>Enhancement of the specification continued in TC43, which resulted in the 4th Edition of ECMA-363 in June 2007.  In particular, Edition 4 introduced an extension to support free-form curves and surfaces using the non-uniform rational basis spline (NURBS).  NURBS offers great flexibility and precision for handling both surfaces defined by common mathematical formulae and modeled shapes and is very widely used.   <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0069446.s001">Appendix 1: A Brief History of 3-D PDF (2013)</a> states, &quot;Unfortunately, the development of U3D ceased in 2006:  the forum was disbanded, essential agreed-upon changes to U3D format (like non-uniform rational b-splines) were not implemented, plans to make
U3D an ISO standard were dropped,  and the U3D SDK was frozen.&quot;  This appendix, which also provides more detail on U3D history, is a supplement to <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0069446">&quot;Embedding and Publishing Interactive, 3-dimensional, Scientific
Figures in Portable Document Format (PDF) files&quot;</a> by David G. Barnes et al.</p>
			<p>The code that originated with Intel is still available as <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/u3d/">Universal 3D Sample Software</a>.  <a href="https://sourceforge.net/p/u3d/code/HEAD/tree/releases/Gold12Update/Docs/ReleaseNotes.htm">Release notes for the latest version of the SDK (dated Dec 2006)</a> indicate that it corresponds to Edition 3 of the U3D specification.  The compilers of this resource are not aware of any full implementations of Edition 4 of the U3D specification.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/ECMA-363%203rd%20edition.pdf</link>
					<tag>ECMA-363 Universal 3D File 
Format (3rd Edition, June 2006)</tag>
					<comment>The specification for the most widely used version of the U3D format.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-363.htm</link>
					<tag>ECMA-363: Universal 3D File Format</tag>
					<comment>Provides access to the four editions of the specification.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_3D</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for Universal 3D (U3D)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.adobe.com/content/dam/acom/en/devnet/acrobat/pdfs/U3DElements.pdf</link>
					<tag>U3D Supported Elements | in Adobe Acrobat SDK (April 2007)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/activities/Communications/U3D-presentation-public.pdf</link>
					<tag>TC 43 - Universal 3D File Format
| Public Presentation (April 2007)</tag>
					<comment>From ECMA. Includes useful description of the architecture and status of the U3D format.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://sourceforge.net/projects/u3d/</link>
					<tag>Universal 3D Sample Software</tag>
					<comment>Software libraries for writing, reading, extending, rendering, and interacting with U3D-formatted data</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The resources listed below serve as introductions to the underlying architecture of the U3D model and file format.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://vaastavanand.com/blog/2017/12/30/Introduction-to-U3D-file-format</link>
							<tag>A Beginner&apos;s Introduction to U3D file format | blog post from December 30, 2017</tag>
							<comment>By Vaastav Anand</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://sourceforge.net/p/u3d/code/HEAD/tree/releases/Gold12Update/Docs/IntermediateFormat/IDTF%20Format%20Description.pdf</link>
							<tag>IDTF (Intermediate Data Text File) Format Description
Version 100 (8 March 2005)</tag>
							<comment>An intermediate text-based format used in the U3D sample software.  The textual examples in the document provide a useful explanation of the semantic structure of U3D. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.pdf3d.com/u3d/</link>
					<tag>Information on U3D from PDF3D (vendor of PDF3D SDK PRO, a toolkit for embedding 3D artwork in PDF documents)</tag>
					<comment>Includes section on early history of U3D format (courtesy of Robert Lansdale of Okino Computer Graphics). Also includes comparison of U3D with the Product Representation Compact (PRC) format.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://3dpdfconsortium.org/u3d/</link>
					<tag>The U3D File Format | on 3DPDF Consortium website</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.archives.gov/files/applied-research/ncsa/8-an-overview-of-3d-data-content-file-formats-and-viewers.pdf</link>
					<tag>An Overview of 3D Data Content, File Formats and Viewers | 2008 report from the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA)</tag>
					<comment>Uses four elements of a 3D model to compare a selection of popular formats: geometry, appearance, scene, and animation</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://files.archivists.org/conference/austin2009/researchforum/PeterBajcsy-SAA-ResearchForum2009.pdf</link>
					<tag>Slideshow on Key Aspects in 3D File Format Conversions | 2008 presentation from NCSA </tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://all3dp.com/3d-file-format-3d-files-3d-printer-3d-cad-vrml-stl-obj/</link>
					<tag>8 Most Common 3D File Formats of 2018: All you need to know about 3D file formats</tag>
					<comment>Also describes the four key elements of a 3D model as geometry, appearance, scene, and animation.  Discusses the selected formats in terms of support for these elements.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Some resources on the early history of the U3D format.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article/file?type=supplementary&amp;id=info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0069446.s001</link>
							<tag>A brief history of 3-d PDF | Appendix 1 of Embedding and publishing interactive, 3-dimensional, scientific
figures in Portable Document Format (PDF) files</tag>
							<comment>By David G. Barnes </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20091214013050/https://www.okino.com/conv/imp_u3d.htm</link>
							<tag>2009 view of Okino Computer Graphics page on its Universal-3D (.u3d) Geometry Import Converter</tag>
							<comment>Includes a section entitled History of the U3D File Format.  Via the Internet Archive</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.cnet.com/news/intel-macromedia-see-3d-in-webs-future/</link>
							<tag>Intel, Macromedia see 3D in Web&apos;s future. C|net article from January 2, 2002.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.cnet.com/news/intels-3d-divorce-rate/</link>
							<tag>Intel&apos;s 3D divorce rate.  C|net article from June 18, 2004.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.computer.org/csdl/mags/co/2005/08/r8023.pdf</link>
							<tag>Making 3D Technology Universal (August 2005)</tag>
							<comment>Article by David Geer in Computer magazine.  Describes 3DIF as a cross-industry group of about 40 developers and corporate users of 3D graphics technology.  Mentions competing formats, including X3D, FBX, VRML, and  </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://sechel.de/talks/2008_StefanSechelmann_U3D.pdf</link>
							<tag>Presentation on Universal 3D File Format (2008)| by Stefan Sechelmann</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://mirror.hmc.edu/ctan/macros/latex/contrib/movie15/doc/movie15.pdf</link>
					<tag>The
movie15
Package (LaTeX) | by Alexander Grahn</tag>
					<comment>Has Appendix B with list of file extensions and Internet Media Types (MIME types) that includes .u3d and model/u3d for the Universal 3D File Format.  </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://forum.solidworks.com/thread/88561</link>
					<tag>SolidWorks support forum | Why has the u3d export format been removed in 2015?</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Articles and other resources relating to embedding 3D artwork using U3D encoding of the model into PDF documents.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/258825876_Simplified_Generation_of_Biomedical_3D_Surface_Model_Data_for_Embedding_into_3D_Portable_Document_Format_PDF_Files_for_Publication_and_Education</link>
							<tag>Simplified Generation of Biomedical 3D Surface Model Data for Embedding into 3D Portable Document Format (PDF) Files for Publication and Education (2013) | By Axel Newe and Thomas Ganslandt. </tag>
							<comment>Has extensive background and list of references on U3D and its use in PDF.  See reference below for the PubMed presentation of the same article.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3829830/</link>
							<tag>Simplified Generation of Biomedical 3D Surface Model Data for Embedding into 3D Portable Document Format (PDF) Files for Publication and Education (2013) | By Axel Newe and Thomas Ganslandt. </tag>
							<comment>The PubMed presentation incorporates links to closely related articles on the use of 3D PDFs in the medical literature.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://peerj.com/articles/794/</link>
							<tag>Towards an easier creation of three-dimensional data for embedding into scholarly 3D PDF (Portable Document Format) files (2015) | by Axel Newe </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/321302874_U3D_File_Format_Analyzing_and_3DPDF_Generating_Method</link>
							<tag>U3D File Format Analyzing and 3DPDF Generating Method (2017) | Conference paper by Nan Zhang et al.</tag>
							<comment>Full text published in proceedings of Advances in Image and Graphics Technologies: 12th Chinese conference, IGTA 2017, Beijing, China, June 30 – July 1, 2017, Revised Selected Papers</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30087092</link>
							<tag>Three-Dimensional Portable Document Format (3D PDF) in Clinical Communication and Biomedical Sciences: Systematic Review of Applications, Tools, and Protocols. (2018)</tag>
							<comment>By Axel Newe and Linda Becker.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://mirror.hmc.edu/ctan/macros/latex/contrib/media9/doc/media9.pdf</link>
							<tag>The
media9
Package (LaTeX) | by Alexander Grahn</tag>
							<comment>A LaTeX package for embedding interactive Adobe Flash (SWF) and 3D files (Adobe
U3D &amp; PRC) as well as video and sound files or streams (FLV, MP4/H.246, MP3)
into PDF documents with Adobe Reader-9/X compatibility.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.elsevier.com/authors/author-services/data-visualization/interactive-u3d-models</link>
							<tag>Interactive U3D models | from Elsevier instructions for authors</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://helpx.adobe.com/acrobat/user-guide.html?topic=/acrobat/morehelp/multimedia_and_3d_models.ug.js</link>
							<tag>Adobe Acrobat User Guide: section on multimedia and 3D models</tag>
							<comment>Is specific that support is only for editions 1 and 3 of ECMA-363.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://helpx.adobe.com/acrobat/kb/supported-file-formats-acrobat-reader.html</link>
							<tag>Supported file formats in Acrobat and Reader</tag>
							<comment>Is specific that U3D support is only for editions 1 and 3 of ECMA-363.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0069446</link>
					<tag>Embedding and Publishing Interactive, 3-Dimensional, Scientific Figures in Portable Document Format (PDF) Files (2013)</tag>
					<comment>By David G. Barnes et al.  This article describes the use of the Product Representation Compact (PRC) format instead of U3D.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/702</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/702</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM on Universal 3D File Format.  PUID: fmt/702.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q974182</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q974182</tag>
					<comment>Information in WikiData about Universal 3D. WikiData Title ID: Q974182</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
