<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000050" titleName="RealVideo, Version 10" shortName="RealVideo_10" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2011-04-05</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Partial</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>RealVideo, Version 10</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>video formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>RealVideo</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>RealMedia</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>File format for video streaming.  May be structured as "single stream," where the content is represented in one datastream, or as the scalable SureStream type, where a file contains multiple versions of content encoded at different data rates, with the selection of the stream for enduser presentation determined at delivery time. Streams may be encoded as constant bitrate, variable bitrate (encoded to provide target average bitrate), or for constant visual quality (producers may select a not-to-exceed instantaneous bitrate).  In RealNetworks literature, version 9 is differentiated from version 10 only in terms of coding efficiency; this description applies to both.</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>File format for video streaming.  In RealNetworks literature, version 9 is differentiated from version 10 only in terms of coding efficiency; this description applies to both.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Generally a final-state (end-user delivery) format.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>RealVideo 9, 8, and G2 SVT (Scalable Video Technology), not documented at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>RealVideo, including versions earlier than 10, is used as streaming format for most video presented in American Memory, along with <fddLink id="fdd000052">QuickTime</fddLink>.  American Memory RealVideo has a data rate on the order of 20 kb/s, with a picture size of approximately 160x120 [less?], and a frame rate less than 15 fps.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>For file-based compressed video, considerations of quality and sustainability mean that <fddLink id="fdd000028">MPEG-2</fddLink> preferred over RealVideo; <fddLink id="fdd000035">MPEG-1</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000037">MPEG-4</fddLink> may be acceptable. Uncompressed or losslessly compressed copies are preferred to compressed (for future development).</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			Proprietary format with little public documentation, although licenses for certain classes of developers may provide access to source code.
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>Limited documentation
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Widely adopted for streaming web content and other online applications, starting in the mid-1990s.  As of March 2012, although streaming media capabilities are increasingly important, the need for proprietary solutions such as Real Video has reduced, given the emergence of openly documented alternatives. For example, <fddLink id="fdd000081">MPEG-4_AVC</fddLink> (aka H.264), was adopted by Apple for its iPod/iPad devices, and is now widely used.  Although those developing HTML5 would like to require browsers to support one streaming video format, no obvious candidate has emerged, in part because H.264 must be licensed.  See <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML5_video">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML5_video</a>.  A new option is VP8, acquired by Google with On2 Technologies, openly described in November 2011 at <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc6386.txt">http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc6386.txt</a>, and made available under a royalty-free license.</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			Licensing for RealVideo and RealAudio, and for related production and delivery tools, is described at <a href="https://helixcommunity.org/content/licenses">https://helixcommunity.org/content/licenses</a>, an entity of RealNetworks, Inc.  Licensing includes open source and research and development arrangements that provide access to the source code for the codecs.
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			Depends upon algorithms and tools to read; will require sophistication and documentation to build tools.
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			Documentation for RealNetworks <i>HelixProducer</i> software indicates that embedded "Clip Information" (bibliographic or descriptive metadata) may include strings of 255 characters for <i>title</i>, <i>author</i>, and <i>copyright</i> owner identification; a string of 1,023 characters for <i>keywords</i>; a string of 64 kb for <i>description</i>; and a one-byte code for <i>content rating</i> (audience identification).  Additional technical metadata is also embedded in RealMedia files.
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>
			Playback of surround sound requires multiple speakers.
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>
			A legal action in 2000 identified two technological protection measures in RealVideo.  The first, "called the 'Secret Handshake' by RealNetworks, ensures that files hosted on a RealServer will only be sent to a RealPlayer. The Secret Handshake is an authentication sequence which only RealServers and RealPlayers know. By design, unless this authentication sequence takes place, the RealServer does not stream the content it holds. . . . By ensuring that RealMedia files hosted on a RealServer are streamed only to RealPlayers, RealNetworks can ensure that a second security measure, which RealNetworks calls the 'Copy Switch,' is given effect. The Copy Switch is a piece of data in all RealMedia files that contains the content owner's preference regarding whether or not the stream may be copied by end-users. RealPlayers are designed to read this Copy Switch and obey the content owner's wishes." (<a href="http://www.law.uh.edu/faculty/cjoyce/copyright/release10/Real.html">RealNetworks, Inc. v. Streambox, Inc.</a>; United States District Court for the Western District of Washington; 2000 U.S. Dist., LEXIS 1889.)
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:movingImageQF>
			<fdd:normalVideo>Good support.</fdd:normalVideo>
			<fdd:clarity>Moderate to very good, given that RealVideo is a format for compression. RealNetworks literature suggests that RealVideo does not use block-based compression (as is the case, for example, for MPEG-2).  The literature also cites three other quality factors: the option for Quality-Based Encoding, readiness for HDTV ("supports all HD formats and resolutions including 720p and 1080i"), and support for 60 field-per-second interlaced content.  The quality of any given file will depend on the type and extent of compression, and the encoding option selected.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:beyondVideo>A sequence of Web pages can be synchronized for display with the playback of streaming media in a RealMedia player when HTML-page URLs are embedded in a RealMedia clip.</fdd:beyondVideo>
		</fdd:movingImageQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>rm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Note that streaming applications require an associated <i>ram</i> (RealMedia Metafile) file.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>rv</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Note that streaming applications require an associated <i>ram</i> (RealMedia Metafile) file.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>rmvb</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Variable bitrate.  Note that streaming applications require an associated <i>ram</i> (RealMedia Metafile) file.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.rn-realmedia</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://service.real.com/help/faq/rp8/configrp8win.html">RealNetworks web page</a>; this MIME type was associated with extension <i>rm</i>.  No examples found in <a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">IANA MIME Media Types</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>video/vnd.rn-realvideo</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://service.real.com/help/faq/rp8/configrp8win.html">RealNetworks web page</a>; this MIME type was associated with extension <i>rv</i>.  No examples found in <a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">IANA MIME Media Types</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 2E 52 4D 46</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: .RMF</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html">Gary Kessler's File Signatures Table</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>Hex: 2E 52 4D 46 00 00 00 12 00</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>ASCII: .RMF</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://filext.com/">The File Extension Source</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>No formal specification is available.  See <a href="#useful">Useful References</a> below for sources that provide some information about the codec and its output data.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RealVideo</link>
					<tag>RealVideo page from Wikipedia</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://docs.real.com/docs/rn/rv10/RV10_Tech_Overview.pdf</link>
					<tag>Promotional description of RealVideo 10 from RealNetworks, Inc.</tag>
					<comment>Includes some technical information about the compression algorithm.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.realnetworks.com/helix/streaming-media-white-papers/</link>
					<tag>Resource Library for Helix</tag>
					<comment>Helix is the professional product line from Real Networks for producing and delivering streaming video.  The library provides access to product manuals, including an archive for non-current product versions.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://community.helixcommunity.org/Realcodecs/index</link>
					<tag>RealAudio and RealVideo Technology for Helix</tag>
					<comment>Includes Overview of RealAudio 10 and RealVideo 10.  As of March 2012, several of the links to additional information fail to access more information.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://service.real.com/help/library/guides/helixproducer/htmfiles/toc_def.htm</link>
					<tag>Documentation of the HelixProducer product</tag>
					<comment>Sheds light on many features of the RealVideo format.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://service.real.com/help/faq/rp8/configrp8win.html</link>
					<tag>RealNetworks web page</tag>
					<comment>Lists (incidentally) Internet Media (MIME) Types .</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.law.uh.edu/faculty/cjoyce/copyright/release10/Real.html</link>
					<tag>RealNetworks, Inc. v. Streambox, Inc.</tag>
					<comment>United States District Court for the Western District of Washington; 2000 U.S. Dist., LEXIS 1889 </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/</link>
					<tag>IANA MIME Media Types</tag>
					<comment>Official page; RealMedia not listed.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.garykessler.net/library/file_sigs.html</link>
					<tag>Gary Kessler's File Signatures Table</tag>
					<comment>Source for magic numbers.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://filext.com/</link>
					<tag>The File Extension Source</tag>
					<comment>For file extensions and magic numbers.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
