<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000551" titleName="Braille Ready Format" shortName="BRF" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2022-11-09</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Braille Ready Format</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Braille Ready Format (BRF) is a simple text file representing finished braille pages.  BRF (<a href="https://www.duxburysystems.com/documentation/dbt%2411.2/brf_files.htm">pronounced</a> <i>brif</i>
with a short <i>i</i> sound, rhyming with <i>cliff</i>) does not have an official standard but the 2021 document <a href="https://www.braillists.org/wp-content/uploads/ho_x023.docx">BRF Files</a> by Matthew Horspool for the Braillists Foundation contains technical details about the structure and use of BRF files. Horspool explains that BRF files are sometimes referred to as <i>formatted braille</i> in that it is &quot;a text-based format which allows us to store and retrieve combinations of braille dots, in the same way as a plain text file allows us to store and retrieve combinations of print letters and numbers.&quot;</p>
			<p>
				<b>Structure of BRF</b>
			</p>
			<p>BRF files save the textual data in ASCII form by replacing the braille symbols with ASCII characters thereby converting the data into a computer-readable format that can eventually be shown on a braille notetaker or embosser. The Braille Plus glossary entry for <a href="https://brailleplus.net/glossary-of-terms/braille-ready-file/">BRF</a> states that BRF files generally contain 25 lines per page, with each line holding up to 39 characters. Mathematical expressions and symbols, as well as graphics, can be converted into words before being translated into BRF. Most BRF files written in the English language use the 6-dot braille patterns defined in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Braille_Code">Computer Braille Code</a> to represent all  ASCII characters. (Note that since January 2016, Computer Braille Code is no longer official in the US, according to the <a href="https://www.afb.org/blindness-and-low-vision/braille/what-braille">American Foundation for the Blind</a>, and is replaced by <a href="https://iceb.org/Rules%20of%20Unified%20English%20Braille%202013.pdf">UEB Braille or Unified English Braille</a>  as the main code for reading material in English-speaking countries. Horspool adds that &quot;BRF files which originate in countries in which English is not the native language may not use the US computer braille code for their assignments. Whilst it is rare to find a BRF file that was encoded using the UK computer braille code, it is common to find BRF files encoded using, say, the French computer braille code if the file originated in France.&quot;) Braille files use ASCII characters  and there are 63 unique combinations of dots in braille, plus a 64th combination of no dots at all (a space). Each of these combinations is assigned an ASCII character on the computer keyboard. </p>
			<p>According to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Braille_ASCII">Wikipedia</a>, "BRF is a file that can represent <a href="https://www.perkins.org/resource/world-braille-usage/">contracted or uncontracted (i.e. grade 1 or grade 2)</a> Unified English Braille, English Braille and non-English languages. BRF files contain plain Braille ASCII plus spaces, Carriage Return, Line Feed, and Form Feed ASCII control characters. The spaces, Carriage Returns, Line Feeds, and Form feeds are sufficient to specify how the braille is formatted. Previously BRF contained some additional specialized formatting instructions, but now BRF is formatted exactly like Web-Braille/BARD."</p>
			<p>Horspool notes that, "since layout is strict in BRF files, anomalies occur when embossing them on pages which don't conform exactly to the layout of the BRF file, or when reading them on devices with a different line length to the BRF file. This is particularly true where the line or page length of the file is longer than the line or page length of the page or device."</p>
			<p>While BRF files can be opened in a simple text editor, the content is coded for braille interpretation. The ASCII characters are recognizable but also include formatting instructions. Horspool provides this example: <i>Hello, my name is Matthew.</i> is represented in BRF as <i>,hello1 my "n is ,mat!w4</i>
. </p>
			<p>
				<b>Uses of BRF Files</b>
			</p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://www.braillists.org/wp-content/uploads/ho_x023.docx">BRF files</a> have two primary uses: embossing hard copy versions of braille documents; and reading and writing braille on electronic devices such as notetakers and braille displays. See <a href="#sustainability">Adoption</a> for more information.
			</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Braille Ready Format (BRF) is a simple text file representing finished braille pages as ASCII characters.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Created for middle-state to final-state, BRF file format is used for saving braille text in a compact form. </fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>eBRF is under development to extend BRF files to include braille text and tactile graphics in one file with enhanced navigation. Project started by American Printing House for the Blind in 2022. Not described separately at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The National Library Service (NLS) for the Blind and Print Disabled provides BRF files as part of its <a href="https://nlsbard.loc.gov/nlsbardprod/login/NLS">Downloadable Books and Magazines</a>. NLS also supplies a specification for the <a href="https://www.loc.gov/nls/about/organization/standards-guidelines/contract-specifications/delivery-of-braille-book-and-magazine-files-via-the-internet/">Delivery of Braille Book and Magazine Files via the Internet</a>. In addition, it provides a list of <a href="https://www.loc.gov/nls/enrollment-equipment/equipment-needed-for-nls-materials/digital-audiobook-players/">Commercial Players Compatible with NLS Digital Talking Books</a> which support BRF files.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The National Library Service (NLS) for the Blind and Print Disabled requires BRF files for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/nls/about/organization/standards-guidelines/contract-specifications/braille-deliverable-package-2022/">braille material produced for NLS</a>. The Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement has not yet expressed any format preference for braille content.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Partially documented but there is no authoritative specification. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>Partially documented in the 2021 document <a href="https://www.braillists.org/wp-content/uploads/ho_x023.docx">BRF Files</a> by Matthew Horspool for the Braillists Foundation. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>BRF files are the de facto standard and widely adopted in braille notetaking devices and translators including the <a href="https://www.duxburysystems.com/default.asp">Duxbury Braille Translator (DBT)</a>, <a href="https://www.brailleblaster.org/">BrailleBlaster</a>, <a href="https://store.humanware.com/hus/braille-devices">Humanware's BrailleNote Touch devices</a>, the open source <a href="http://liblouis.org/">Liblouis</a>, and many more.  Sources for BRF files include <a href="https://nlsbard.loc.gov/nlsbardprod/login/NLS">National Library Service for the Blind and Print Disabled Downloadable Books and Magazines</a> (login required), part of the Library of Congress <a href="https://www.loc.gov/nls/">National Library Service (NLS)</a>, <a href="https://www.bookshare.org/cms/help-center/training-and-resources/braille">Bookshare Braille Central</a>, and <a href="https://readingservices.rnib.org.uk/">Royal National Institute of Blind People (RNIB) Reading Services</a>.
			</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>None. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>ASCII characters can be read in a simple text editor but require braille translation to be understood.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>None. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>Specialized software or hardware that can open and read BRF files is required. <a href="https://www.bookshare.org/cms/help-center/training-and-resources/braille">Bookshare</a> notes that &quot;most devices will not recognize BRF automatically. Most users either open the BRF file in a software program, like Duxbury, which allows them to view, edit, or emboss the book, or transfer the file to a braille note taker.&quot;</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>Low Support. BRF files allow users to store and retrieve combinations of braille dots in the same way as a plain text file allows us to store and retrieve combinations of print letters and numbers. There&apos;s no official standard for BRF, so there is no straightforward one-to-one mapping of characters.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>BRF files contain plain braille ASCII plus spaces, Carriage Return, Line Feed, and Form Feed ASCII control characters. The spaces, Carriage Returns, Line Feeds, and Form Feeds are sufficient to specify how the braille is formatted.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>A BRF file is formatted entirely using just blank lines and spaces. As a result, readers can’t easily navigate through a big file or take advantage of other conveniences, like links for footnotes and endnotes. BRF files generally contain 25 lines per page, with each line holding up to 39 characters. Transcribing a single printed page can result in several braille pages; the exact ratio depends on the nature of the document.</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>
				<a href="https://brailleplus.net/glossary-of-terms/braille-ready-file/">Mathematical expressions and symbols,</a> as well as graphics, can be converted into words before being translated into BRF files.
</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>None</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>brf</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.file-extensions.org/brf-file-extension">https://filext.com/file-extension/BRF</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>bfm</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://brailleplus.net/glossary-of-terms/braille-ready-file/">https://brailleplus.net/glossary-of-terms/braille-ready-file/</a>. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM has no corresponding entry as of October 2022.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata has no corresponding entry as of October 2022.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>A new effort is underway to develop a expanded version of BRF called <i>eBRF</i>. According to the <a href="https://www.aph.org/establishing-a-new-braille-file-standard-with-the-ebrf/">American Printing House for the Blind</a>, BRF or a "braille txt file is formatted entirely using just blank lines and spaces. As a result, readers can’t easily navigate through a big file or take advantage of other conveniences, like links for footnotes and endnotes. There are also no ways to join braille content and embossed graphics in the same electronic experience." Starting in April 2022, APH is spearheading a new file format called eBRF which will mitigate these issues by providing braille text and tactile graphics in one file with enhanced navigation. The APH states: "The goal of the eBRF project is to create a new braille file standard that seamlessly contains both braille and tactile graphics. This interactive file will include formatting, like headings, tables, and glossaries. Enhanced navigation will allow students to effectively jump to sections, chapters, or pages and utilize links to access footnotes or other referenced material. Users can also decide the format they would like to view tables in, whether it be spatially or in a listed form. The eBRF will be easy to create and open and will work on single- and multi-line braille displays, and embossers can emboss both braille and graphics in a single print job. The eBRF, used with displays like our upcoming Dynamic Tactile Device (DTD), will display full pages of braille text, graphics, and even braille music, giving students access to instructional materials at the same time as their sighted peers." As of this writing, there is no published specification or technical details for eBRF. </fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>BRF is the de facto file format for electronic braille content. The history of braille is described in the 2000 book <a href="https://archive.org/details/brailleintonextm00edit">Braille Into the Next Millennium</a> (available for download from the Internet Archive), a 600-page anthology of articles by more than two dozen international experts in the field of braille that was published jointly by the Library of Congress&apos;s National Library Service (NLS) and the Friends of Libraries for Blind and Physically Handicapped Individuals in North America. Braille was long produced on paper by the slate and stylus method (in which the paper is inserted between the two parts of a slate, and the stylus is used to press each individual dot into the paper) and later, a <i>brailler</i> (similar to a typewriter, except that it has only six keys plus the spacebar). In November 1986, <a href="https://www.brailleauthority.org/">Braille Authority of North America (BANA)</a> approved the Computer Braille Notation, an adaptation of braille for precise representation of computer-related materials, for publication. It was officially adopted in 1987. <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.braillists.org/wp-content/uploads/ho_x023.docx</link>
					<tag>BRF Files
Presented by Matthew Horspool for the Braillists Foundation, Tuesday 4 May 2021 at 7:30 PM
</tag>
					<comment>Informal document with information about layout, structure, uses etc. </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.duxburysystems.com/documentation/dbt%2411.2/brf_files.htm</link>
					<tag>Importing Formatted Braille (BRF) Files from Duxbury Systems</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.duxburysystems.com/default.asp</link>
					<tag>Duxbury Systems DBT: Braille Translation Software</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://brailleplus.net/glossary-of-terms/braille-ready-file/</link>
					<tag>Braille Plus Inc Glossary entry for Braille Ready File</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Wikipedia Sources</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Braille_Code</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for Computer Braille Code</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Braille_ASCII</link>
							<tag>Wikipedia entry for Computer Braille ASCII</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Library of Congress sources</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.loc.gov/nls/</link>
							<tag>National Library Service for the Blind and Print Disabled (NLS) homepage</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.loc.gov/nls/enrollment-equipment/equipment-needed-for-nls-materials/digital-audiobook-players/</link>
							<tag>NLS Digital Audiobook Players</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.loc.gov/nls/about/organization/standards-guidelines/contract-specifications/delivery-of-braille-book-and-magazine-files-via-the-internet/</link>
							<tag>NLS Delivery of Braille Book and Magazine Files via the Internet (February 2020)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.loc.gov/nls/about/organization/standards-guidelines/contract-specifications/braille-deliverable-package-2022/</link>
							<tag>NLS Braille Deliverable Package 2022</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://nlsbard.loc.gov/nlsbardprod/login/NLS</link>
							<tag>National Library Service for the Blind and Print Disabled Downloadable Books and Magazines</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.afb.org/blindness-and-low-vision/braille/what-braille</link>
					<tag>American Foundation for the Blind: What Is Braille?</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://iceb.org/Rules%20of%20Unified%20English%20Braille%202013.pdf</link>
					<tag>International Council on English Braille: The Rules of
Unified English Braille. 2nd Edition 2013</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.perkins.org/resource/world-braille-usage/</link>
					<tag>Perkins School for the Blind: World braille usage</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.brailleblaster.org/</link>
					<tag>Braille Blaster</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://store.humanware.com/hus/braille-devices</link>
					<tag>Humanware Braille devices</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://liblouis.org/</link>
					<tag>Liblouis software</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.bookshare.org/cms/help-center/training-and-resources/braille</link>
					<tag>Bookshare Braille Central</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://readingservices.rnib.org.uk/</link>
					<tag>Royal National Institute of Blind People (RNIB) Reading Services</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.aph.org/establishing-a-new-braille-file-standard-with-the-ebrf/</link>
					<tag>Establishing a New Braille File Standard with the eBRF. April 6, 2022. The American Printing House for the Blind.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://archive.org/details/brailleintonextm00edit</link>
					<tag>Braille Into the Next Millennium. Link from Internet Archive. Download options available.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.brailleauthority.org/</link>
					<tag>Braille Authority of North America (BANA)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
