<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000452" titleName="NCBIArch_3, NCBI/NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange Document Type Definition (NLM DTD), Version 3.0" shortName="NCBIArch_3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>container-bundle</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2017-03-08</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Formal name: NCBI/NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange Document Type Definition (DTD), version 3.0.  Common name: NLM DTD, version 3.0</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>
				<a href="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/3.0/">Version 3.0</a> of the Archiving and Interchange DTD was released by the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), a division of the National Library of Medicine (NLM) on November 21, 2008.  Often referred to as the NLM DTD, the Journal Archiving and Interchange Tag Library was intended as a common format in which publishers and archives can exchange final journal article content.  See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink> for a description of the early versions of this format and characteristics of the family of DTDs as a whole.</p>
			<p>Version 3.0 is a non-backward compatible release of the NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange Tag Suite. The changes in version 3.0 reflect requests made by users and improvements identified as necessary for the Tag Suite&apos;s future usability.  Major categories of changes included: some elements were renamed to make the naming more consistent throughout the tag set; markup for some aspects of the article models that had proved confusing or hard to use correctly was adjusted; and some wrapper elements were added to keep related-material together.  See <a href="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/3.0/index.html?chap=chg-rpt">Change Report: Version 3.0</a> for more details.</p>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink> for more information about the structure and characteristics of the family of DTDs as a whole.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Version 3.0 of an XML-based specification for journal articles, developed by the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), a division of the National Library of Medicine (NLM) and intended as a common format in which publishers and archives can exchange final journal content.  Three major versions of this NLM DTD were published before it was superseded by JATS (Journal Archiving Tag Suite), as standardized through NISO.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Generally used for exchanging works in their final state.  A related Publishing DTD (built from the same tag set) is intended as an initial- or middle-state format for authors and publishers.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000451</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>JATS_1</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>JATS, Journal Article Tag Suite, NISO Z39.96, versions 1.x</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000175</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>NCBIArch_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>NCBI/NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD, versions 2.x</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000174</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>NCBIArch_1</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>NCBI/NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD, versions 1.x</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000076</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML_DTD</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>XML Document Type Definition (DTD)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink>
			</p>
		</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink>
			</p>
		</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Openly documented. All components of the Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD Suite are in the public domain.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>See <a href="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/#id48886">NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange Tag Suite | Tag Suite Versions</a> for links to documentation for all versions of the NLM DTD.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The NLM DTD and its successor, <fddLink id="fdd000451">JATS</fddLink>, are used by a number of scholarly publishers when submitting articles marked up in XML to an external archive.  According to information provided by <a href="http://www.portico.org/digital-preservation/">Portico</a> on article submissions in 2016 for its archival service, 40 publishers submitted a total of over one million articles in version 3.0 of the Archiving and Interchange DTD, and 9 publishers submitted about 120,000 articles in version 3.0 of the Publishing DTD.  More publishers used versions 2.x but for fewer articles.</p>
			<p>The British Library allows journal publishers to deposit copies to the Legal Deposit Libraries by submitting content to Portico and authorizing Portico to transmit a copy to the British Library.  For this purpose, the British Library has chosen version 3.0 of the NLM DTD as the format for Portico to use for such transmissions.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No licensing or patent issues. The tag sets are in the public domain.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Rates highly for transparency. Text content for articles is in XML, and hence viewable in basic editors, web browsers, etc.
		Elements have understandable tag-names, and document instances are in natural reading order.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>The DTD includes a rich set of elements for metadata at the article and journal level.  The &lt;article&gt; element is expected to include the article content and full descriptive metadata.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>
			None.
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>
			None.  
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>
				<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink>
				</p>
			</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:beyondText/>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>xml</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>For textual content files. </fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink>
			</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink>
			</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/tag-library/3.0/index.html</link>
					<tag>NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD Tag Library, Version 3.0</tag>
					<comment>November 2008</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/#id48886</link>
					<tag> NLM Journal Archiving and Interchange Tag Suite</tag>
					<comment>Provides access to all versions of the tag suite before it became the NISO Journal Article Tag Suite (JATS)</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih.gov/pub/archive_dtd/archiving/3.0/</link>
					<tag>DTD, W3C XML Schema (.xsd),and RNG (.rng) specifications.</tag>
					<comment>The DTD version was considered primary, with the schema derived for convenience.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>
						<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000174">NCBIArch_1</fddLink>.</p>
					</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
