<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000011" titleName="Linear Pulse Code Modulated Audio (LPCM)" shortName="LPCM" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>sound</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2008-02-19</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Linear Pulse Code Modulated Audio (LPCM)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>LPCM</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>PCM</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>audio formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>recorded sound formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>Pulse code modulation (PCM) with linear quantization. PCM is a digital representation of an analog signal where the magnitude of the signal is sampled regularly at uniform intervals, then quantized to a series of symbols in a digital (usually binary) code. PCM has been used in digital telephone systems and is also the standard form for digital audio on audio compact disks (Red Book format; see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Pulse code modulation (PCM) with linear quantization. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Used at all stages in production and archiving workflows.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000016</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PCM</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Pulse Code Modulated Audio</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000002</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>WAVE_LPCM</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>WAVE Audio File with LPCM Audio</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000003</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>WAVE_BWF_LPCM_1</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Broadcast WAVE File Format, Version 1, with LPCM Audio</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000116</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>AIFF_LPCM</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>AIFF File Format with LPCM Audio</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000142</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>AES3</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>AES3, Digital Audio Interface Format</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000346</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>Matroska_LPCM</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Matroska File Format with LPCM Audio Encoding </fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>
			<fddLink id="fdd000002">WAVE_LPCM</fddLink> is used as the best digital format for audio converted for American Memory and in preservation reformatting by the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division and the American Folklife Center.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>
			<fddLink id="fdd000003">WAVE_LPCM_BWF</fddLink> or <fddLink id="fdd000002">WAVE_LPCM</fddLink>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Widely described and documented.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>The history of PCM is varied and extends back to at least the 1930s. Documentation that is relevant to digital sound recording includes the following:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<fddLink id="fdd000142">AES3</fddLink>, <i>AES standard for digital audio -- Digital input-output interfacing -- Serial transmission format for two-channel linearly represented digital audio data</i>, includes encoding for stereo/two-channel recordings</li>
				<li>
					<i>Multimedia Programming Interface and Data Specifications 1.0</i>.  IBM Corporation and Microsoft Corporation, August 1991.  Pertains to the use of LPCM in WAVE (see <fddLink id="fdd000002">WAVE_LPCM</fddLink>). Available online, e.g., at <a href="http://www.tactilemedia.com/info/MCI_Control_Info.html">http://www.tactilemedia.com/info/MCI_Control_Info.html</a>
				</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 60908: <i>Audio recording - Compact disc digital audio system (1999-02), covers the use of 16-bit LPCM in compact disks.</i>
				</li>
				<li>See also Red Book information in <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Very widely used for encoding bitstreams.  Used on audio CDs, Digital Audio Tape (DAT).  Default bitstream encoding for <fddLink id="fdd000001">WAVE</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000005">AIFF</fddLink>.  One of the bitstream encodings supported for sound on DVD-Video.  Coders and decoders available as chips. The open source <a href="https://mediaarea.net/MediaConch/">MediaConch</a> toolset (a component of the EU-based <a href="http://www.preforma-project.eu/index.html">PREFORMA</a> project) is an implementation checker, policy checker, reporter, and fixer for <fddLink id="fdd000341">FFV1</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska</fddLink> and LPCM which will further facilitiate adoption. </fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>None.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>Linear PCM is a simple, uncompressed representation comparable in transparency to uncompressed bit-mapped images. </p>
			<p>From Appendix 1.1 of the <a href="http://www.ercim.eu/publication/ws-proceedings/Delos-NSF/SpokenWord.pdf">report</a> of the EU-US Working Group on Spoken-Word Audio Collections [SWAG]: &quot;Linear PCM data, irrespective of sampling rate, word length, method of packing data into bytes and left-to-right or right-to-left arrangement of bits and bytes, can be decoded by relatively simple trial-and-error, and we can expect this to be the case indefinitely.  PCM is in this sense a &apos;natural&apos; representation for audio, and has very good long-term prospects regardless of the remaining problems of format migration.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Not applicable.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Good support.</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>
				<p>Linear PCM captures and encodes audio without lossy compression.  Fidelity for LPCM is enhanced by higher sample rates and sample sizes.  Some LPCM coders and decoders on the market today support sampling rates up to 192kHz and/or sample sizes up to 32 bits.  File or media formats that use LPCM for bitstream encoding may constrain sampling rate or bit-depth.  Audio CDs use 44.1 kHz sampling rate with 16-bit samples; DAT tape uses 48 kHz sampling and 16 bits. The Audio Engineering Society standard AES5 recommends sampling frequencies, as described in the notes for <fddLink id="fdd000142">AES3</fddLink>.</p>
				<p>In the WAVE format syntax, the limits on sample rate (a 32-bit integer, up to 0xFFFFFFFF, or 4,294,967,295) and sample size (a 16-bit integer, up to 65,535 bits/sample) are high enough to place no practical limit on fidelity.  In practice, as 24-or 32-bit sample sizes and higher sampling rates (DVD Audio supports up to 192Khz) become more common, the overall limit on file size, set by individual computer operating systems, becomes a constraint.  With 192kHz sampling and 24 bits/sample, about half an hour of stereo can be stored in a 4 Gbyte file (a typical Windows limit).</p>
			</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>Not applicable; LPCM encodes a single channel of sound.  Stereo and two-channel audio is supported by interleaving two LPCM streams; see <fddLink id="fdd000142">AES3</fddLink>.  Formats like RF63 (&quot;extended WAVE&quot;), <fddLink id="fdd000006">AES31</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink> (and others) provide a means for bundling and synchronizing multiple LPCM bitstreams.</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:samples>Not applicable.</fdd:samples>
			<fdd:beyondSound>Not applicable.</fdd:beyondSound>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>raw</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The extension normally depends upon file wrapper used. However, LPCM data may be stored in &quot;raw&quot; form, with &quot;.raw&quot; as a file extension.  A variant of this encoding is captured by devices manufactured by Snell &amp; Wilcox, reportedly carring an &quot;.aes&quot; extension; see also <fddLink id="fdd000142">AES3</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q3241497</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q3241497">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q3241497</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>The Wikipedia <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Book_(audio_CD_standard)">article on the Red Book standard</a> (accessed June 1, 2010) reports: &quot;Red Book is the standard for audio CDs (Compact Disc Digital Audio system, or CD-DA). It is named after one of the Rainbow Books, a series of books (bound in different colors) that contain the technical specifications for all CD and CD-ROM formats.

The first edition of the Red Book was released in 1980 by Philips and Sony; it was adopted by the Digital Audio Disc Committee and ratified as IEC 60908. The standard is not freely available and must be licensed from Philips. As of 2004, the cost per the relevant Philips order form is US$5,000. As of 2009, the IEC 60908 document is also available as a PDF download for US$260&quot;</fdd:general>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>AES3-2003.  AES standard for digital audio -- Digital input-output interfacing -- Serial transmission format for two-channel linearly represented digital audio data</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>AES5-2003. AES recommended practice for professional digital audio -- Preferred sampling frequencies for applications employing pulse-code modulation</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:specReference>IEC 60908 Ed. 2.0 Bilingual, Audio recording - Compact disc digital audio system</fdd:specReference>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ercim.eu/publication/ws-proceedings/Delos-NSF/SpokenWord.pdf</link>
					<tag>SWAG report.</tag>
					<comment>EU-US project report on Spoken Word Archiving that includes brief discussion of recording formats.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AES3</link>
					<tag>AES3 (Wikipedia article)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.preforma-project.eu/index.html</link>
					<tag>PREFORMA, PREservation FORMAts for culture information/e-archives</tag>
					<comment>Collaborative EU-funded project with goal of "implementing good quality standardised file formats" including Matroska, FLAC and FFV1</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://mediaarea.net/MediaConch/</link>
					<tag>MediaConch: Open source implementation checker, policy checker, and reporter for Matroska, FFV1, &amp; PCM</tag>
					<comment>Part of EU-based PREFORMA project</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q3241497</link>
					<tag>WikiData entry for Q3241497</tag>
					<comment>Information in WikiData about LPCM. WikiData Title ID: Q3241497.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
		<fdd:citations>
			<fdd:citation>
				<fdd:bookReference>
					<bookRefDetail rel="au">Jayant, Nuggehally S.</bookRefDetail>, and <bookRefDetail rel="au">Peter Noll</bookRefDetail>.  <bookRefDetail rel="btitle">Digital Coding of Waveforms</bookRefDetail>. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice Hall, <bookRefDetail rel="date">1984</bookRefDetail>.</fdd:bookReference>
			</fdd:citation>
		</fdd:citations>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
