<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000495" titleName="PDF/E-1, Engineering Document Format, ISO 24517-1:2008" shortName="PDF/E-1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>model</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>text</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
				</fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
			</fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2019-04-04</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>ISO 24517-1. Document Management - Engineering document format using PDF. Part 1: Use of PDF 1.6 (PDF/E-1)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>3D model formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>Portable Document Format (PDF)</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>PDF/E-1 is a constrained form of Adobe PDF intended to be suitable for exchange of 2D and 3D documentation in building and manufacturing workflows.  The PDF/E-1 standard is maintained by a working group with representatives from government and industry, and active support from Adobe Systems Incorporated.  The working group is WG 7 of <i>Technical Committee ISO/TC 171, Document management applications, Subcommittee SC 2, Application issues</i> [ISO TC171/SC2/WG5]. </p>
			<p>Among the objectives for PDF/E-1 were:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Accurate printing of engineering drawings and predictable behavior in conforming viewers.</li>
				<li>Support for 3D artwork using the <fddLink id="fdd000491">U3D</fddLink> format.</li>
				<li>Support for incorporating detailed engineering data.</li>
				<li>Support for review and commenting.</li>
				<li>Metadata associated with individual parts of a document, stored in XMP without compression.</li>
				<li>Secure document exchange
in self-contained file, with digital signatures.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Constraints in PDF/E documents include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>No external content or arbitrary actionable code in Postscript or JavaScript (except Javascript associated with 3D rendering) is permitted.  No XFA-based forms are permitted.</li>
				<li>Audio and video clips must be entirely self-contained and embedded within a single stream.</li>
				<li>All colors must be specified in a device-independent manner, and consistently within a document.</li>
				<li>ICC-based color profiles must be embedded.</li>
				<li>All fonts used must be embedded and also must be legally embeddable for unlimited, universal rendering.</li>
				<li>All metadata must be represented in XMP. All metadata properties must use either the predefined schemas defined in Chapter 4 of the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20050318195738/http://www.adobe.com/products/xmp/pdfs/xmpspec.pdf">XMP Specification</a>, or extension schemas that comply with the XMP Specification.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>PDF/E-1 files may include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>JavaScript associated with 3D content;</li>
				<li>Transparency and layers in graphics;</li>
				<li>Multimedia;</li>
				<li>Embedded files;</li>
				<li>Encryption, digital rights management (DRM), and digital signatures.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Suitable for exchange of 2D and 3D documentation in building and manufacturing workflows. Published as ISO 24517-1:2008, Document management – Engineering document format using PDF 1.6.  </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Intended for exchange of engineering documentation in workflows for manufacturing and building.  Also used for final-state documentation of designs.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000030</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF (Portable Document Format) Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000276</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PDF_1_6</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PDF, Version 1.6</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000491</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>U3D_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Universal 3D (U3D) format family. ECMA-363</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>ISO 24517-1 specifies that the only supported encoding for a 3D content stream is U3D.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>No direct experience</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>The Library of Congress has not yet expressed any format preferences for digital models used as designs or surrogates for 3-dimensional objects.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>An open international standard, published by ISO in 2008.  Maintained by a working group (WG7) under <a href="https://www.iso.org/committee/53674.html">ISO/TC 171 SC2</a>, the subcommittee for Document Management Applications, Application Issues.   From 2002 to 2016, AIIM (The Association for Information and Image Management) acted as secretariat and U.S. Technical Advisory Group (TAG) to ISO/TC 171 SC 2 (see <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150910070337/http://www.aiim.org/Research-and-Publications/Standards/Committees/TAG">AIIM | U.S. TAG to ISO/TC 171</a> from 2015).   In 2017, the 3D PDF Consortium was approved by the American National Standards Institute (ANSI) as a standards developer and has assumed the role of secretariat and U.S. TAG Administrator for ISO/TC 171 SC 2  (see <a href="http://3dpdfconsortium.org/2017/07/26/3d-pdf-consortium-approved-ansi-us-tag-administrator-pdf-iso-standards/">3D PDF Consortium Approved by ANSI as US TAG Administrator for PDF ISO Standards</a>).</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/42274.html">ISO 24517-1:2008. Document management -- Engineering document format using PDF -- Part 1: Use of PDF 1.6 (PDF/E-1)</a>.  The standard cannot be used without <a href="https://www.adobe.com/content/dam/acom/en/devnet/pdf/pdf_reference_archive/PDFReference16.pdf">PDF Reference, Fifth Edition, Version 1.6</a>, which it uses as a normative reference.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>The compilers of this resource have found little information as to the degree to which the formal PDF/E-1 standard has been used in practice, apart from the statement in <a href="https://www.pdfa.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/1145_von_Seggern.pdf">PDF’s ISO-standardized subsets: a tour</a>, a May 2018 slideshow from the PDF Association, that there has been almost no practical use of PDF/E-1.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>There are circumstances that suggest why adoption has not been widespread.  PDF/E-1 only supports U3D for 3D content.  Support for a different 3D encoding, Product Representation Compact (PRC), was introduced by Adobe in Acrobat 8.1 in 2007, before PDF/E-1 was published as ISO 24517-1:2008 or PDF 1.7 was published as ISO 32000-1:2008.  PRC has advantages over U3D, particularly in supporting a very efficient specialized compression mechanism.  Before PDF 1.7 was approved by ISO, Adobe documented an extension to PDF 1.7, <fddLink id="fdd000313">PDF_1_7_ext03</fddLink>, which supported 3D content using PRC and a standardized way to represent geospatial locations, another feature of importance in some engineering contexts. For these reasons, engineering workflows were probably better served by what is often called &quot;3D PDF&quot; than by the formal PDF/E-1 standard.</p>
			<p>In October 2018, the U.S. Department of Defense issued an <a href="https://www.action-engineering.com/wp-content/uploads/MIL-STD-31000B-AS-PUBLISHED-31-OCT-2018.pdf">update to its MIL-STD-31000 standard</a>, which defines Technical Data Packages (TDP) as required in association with contracts.  The purpose of a TDP is &quot;to provide an authoritative technical description of an item which is clear, complete and accurate, and in a form and format adequate for its intended use.&quot;  This update introduces the concept of the 3Di (3-Dimensional Intelligent) PDF viewable TDP.  The definition for 3Di technical data is &quot;A 3-dimensional viewable representation of an item provided in a widely available software format (e.g. ISO 32000-1 Portable Document Format (PDF)).  This representation details the complete technical description of the required design configuration to include but not limited to geometry, topology, relationships, tolerances, attributes, metadata and other features necessary to define a component or assembly.&quot;  It seems likely to the compilers of this resource that this standard will have an influence on the way the market for tools to create and render engineering documentation in PDF develops. <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>A draft for PDF/E-2 has been circulated for comments as ISO 24517-2, to be
based
on
PDF
version
2.0
(as
defined
in
ISO
32000-­2)
rather
than
on PDF
version
1.6.  But the process stalled.  <a href="https://www.pdflib.com/pdf-knowledge-base/future-iso-standards/">Future ISO standards based on PDF 2.0</a> from PDFlib states &quot;PDF/A-4e is targeted at the engineering community. It is slated as successor of the existing PDF/E-1 standard ISO 24517-1 which is based on PDF 1.6. The previous plan to define a new flavor PDF/E-2 as ISO 24517-2 has been canceled. Instead, PDF/A-4e adds RichMedia annotations for 3D content in U3D or PRC format to the base PDF/A-4 format.&quot; <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.  In the meanwhile, there seems little reason for use of PDF/E-1, since PDFs based on PDF 2.0 (ISO 32000-2) can incorporate 3D in both U3D and PRC formats, and also take advantage of other features introduced with PDF 2.0 that are useful in engineering workflows, such as embedding of related files.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>See <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>Depends upon compliant software to render and display.  Building tools requires sophistication.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Support for embedding granular metadata for parts of a document is good.  Use of XMP is mandatory and basic descriptive and identifying metadata uses properties defined in the standard.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>One objective of PDF/E is self-containment.  Fonts and ICC color profiles used must be embedded.  No external content is permitted.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>PDF/E-1 allows encryption, to support secure transmission and digital signatures.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>May include images in JPEG or JPEG 2000 compression for color or grayscale, and Group 4, Group4, or JBIG2 for monochrome images. See <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>See <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>All colors are specified in a device-independent manner, either directly by the use of a device
independent color space, or indirectly by the use of an OutputIntent.  If used, ICCBased color spaces shall be embedded as ICC profile streams.  Note: 3D content is specified in an unqualified RGB color space.</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>See <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:beyondImage>Support for 3D artwork in U3D format.</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>Good support for text indexing and extraction is possible, but not guaranteed.  PDF 1.6, on which PDF/E-1 is based, does not require Unicode mapping for all text.  See <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>The logical structure of a PDF/E-1 document is only represented explicitly if the creator or a process during creation takes steps to incorporate structural tagging.  Tagging is permitted in a PDF/E-1 document.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>PDF/E-1 is designed for reliable representation of page-layout, including use of fonts as intended by the creator.  Fonts must be embedded.</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>Can be represented as images.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>Supports commenting and review.  Supports embedded audio and video.</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
		<fdd:otherQF>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>3D Model Geometry</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>Quality and functionality of all aspects of any embedded 3D artwork depends on the model encoding used for the model.  See <fddLink id="fdd000491">U3D_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
		</fdd:otherQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>pdf</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The standard does not indicate that a different extension should be used to distinguish PDF from PDF/E.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000030">PDF_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Indicator for profile, level, version, etc.</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>The standard specifies that the PDF/E version shall be specified using the metadata element <i>pdfe:ISO_PDFEVersion</i> with value <i>PDF/E-1</i>.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for example of tagging within the XMP metadata in a PDF/E-1 file.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/493</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/493">https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/493</a>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q2043942</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2043942">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2043942</a>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>Self-identification of a PDF/E-1 file is found marked up in XML within a mandatory metadata chunk.   A file would identify itself with XML equivalent to:<br/>&lt;rdf:Description rdf:about=&quot;&quot; xmlns:pdfe=&quot;http://www.aiim.org/pdfe/ns/id/&quot;&gt;
<br/>   &lt;pdfe:ISO_PDFEVersion&gt;PDF/E-1&lt;/pdfe:ISO_PDFEVersion&gt;<br/>  &lt;/rdf:Description&gt;</p>
			<p>ISO 24517-1:2008 states, &quot;Neither the version number in the header of a PDF file, nor the value of the Versionkey in the Catalog of a PDF file shall be used in determining whether a file is in accordance with this part of this International Standard.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The PDF/E working group was formed in March 2004.  Participants included Adobe Systems Inc., Autodesk, Bentley Systems, Hewlett Packard, Intel, TerraGo (formerly Layton Graphics), Océ (a Canon subsidary), Dell, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, U.S. National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency, Boeing, Caterpillar, Honeywell, Xerox.   PDF/E (ISO 24517-1:2008) was approved by ISO in 2007 and published in 2008.</p>
			<p> According to a 2018 presentation, <a href="https://www.pdfa.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/1145_von_Seggern.pdf">PDF’s ISO-standardized subsets: a tour</a>, the next part of <fddLink id="fdd000318">PDF/A</fddLink> (ISO 19005), to be based on PDF 2.0, will incorporate a profile, PDF/A-4e, that will serve as the next generation of the PDF/E standard.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iso.org/standard/42274.html</link>
					<tag>ISO 24517-1:2008.  Document management -- Engineering document format using PDF -- Part 1: Use of PDF 1.6 (PDF/E-1)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.adobe.com/content/dam/acom/en/devnet/pdf/pdf_reference_archive/PDFReference16.pdf</link>
					<tag>PDF Reference, Fifth Edition, version 1.6. November 2004</tag>
					<comment>Adobe Systems Incorporated.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://3dpdfconsortium.org/pdf-e/</link>
					<tag>3D PDF Consortium | PDF/E</tag>
					<comment>Appointed as secretariat in 2017 for future development and maintenance of most ISO standards based on PDF</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20121123055316/http://www.aiim.org/Research-and-Publications/Standards/Committees/PDFE</link>
					<tag>AIIM | PDF/Engineering</tag>
					<comment>Public page for the PDF/E working group after publication of ISO 24517-1:2008.  AIIM hosted the activity from 2004 through 2017.  Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDF/E</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for PDF/E</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources relating to early standardization activity for PDF/E.  Most links are via Internet Archive or archive.is.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20121205150411/http://www.aiim.org/documents/standards/PDF-E/pdf-epressrelease.pdf</link>
							<tag>March 2004 press release from AIIM and NPES on formation of PDF/E working group</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://talkingpdf.org/pdf-for-engineering-pdfe/</link>
							<tag>TalkingPDF | PDF/E (undated)</tag>
							<comment>Describes high level objectives and participants in standardization effort.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://archive.is/20130131031110/http://www.pdfzone.com/c/a/Document-Management/PDFE-Draft-Standard-Speeds-Toward-ISO/</link>
							<tag>PDFZone | PDF/E Draft Standard Speeds Toward ISO (March 14, 2005)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20121205150038/http://www.aiim.org/documents/standards/PDF-E/What%20is%20PDF_E_Mar_07_AIIM.pdf</link>
							<tag>PDF/E Overview (March 2007)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20130202210338/http://www.aiim.org/documents/standards/PDF-E/PDF_E_FAQ-Edits_Jan.pdf</link>
							<tag>PDF/E-1 FAQ (March 2008)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20090206171842/http://www.adobe.com/enterprise/pdfs/pdf-eready-guide-ue.pdf</link>
					<tag>Creating PDF/E-ready files (March 2008)</tag>
					<comment>Adobe&apos;s instructions for using Acrobat&apos;s PDFMaker to create PDF/E files.  Link via Internet Archive.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to support for PRC (Product Representation Compact) within future version of PDF/E</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://3dpdfconsortium.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/7-minutes-with-prc.pdf</link>
							<tag>7 Minutes with a PDF Standard (July 2013)</tag>
							<comment>Describes use of PRC (Product Representation Compact) as 3D artwork within PDF, supported in Acrobat 3D (version 8) from May 2007. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20120907095416/http://www.aiim.org/documents/standards/PDF-E/PRC_FAQ_final.pdf</link>
							<tag>PRC (Product Representation Compact) Format FAQ</tag>
							<comment>Undated (but prior to September 7, 2012)</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources that indicate what to expect from a future version of PDF for engineering documents.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.pdf3d.com/about-pdfe/</link>
							<tag>PDF3D | About PDF/E</tag>
							<comment>Mentions plans for PDF/E-2</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.3dpdfconsortium.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/pdfa-meet-pdfe.pdf</link>
							<tag>3D PDF Consortium | PDF/A, meet PDF/E (July 31, 2013)</tag>
							<comment>Has useful summary of PDF/E-1 characteristics as well as expected additions for PDF/E-2.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.pdflib.com/pdf-knowledge-base/future-iso-standards/</link>
							<tag>Future ISO standards based on PDF 2.0</tag>
							<comment>States, &quot;The previous plan to define a new flavor PDF/E-2 as ISO 24517-2 has been canceled.&quot;  </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.pdfa.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/1145_von_Seggern.pdf</link>
							<tag>PDF Association | PDF’s ISO-standardized subsets: a tour</tag>
							<comment>States that PDF/E will become PDF/A-4e.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to MIL-STD-31000B (U.S. Department of Defense Standard Practice: Technical Data Packages).  An update was released in October 2018. This revision introduced the concept of 3Di PDF viewable Technical Data Packages (TDPs) as a recommended option for engineering documentation requirements in acquisition contracts.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.action-engineering.com/blog/2018/11/dod-releases-mil-std-31000b-31-october-2018-update</link>
							<tag>Action Engineering | DOD Releases MIL-STD-31000B 31 October 2018 Update</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.action-engineering.com/wp-content/uploads/MIL-STD-31000B-AS-PUBLISHED-31-OCT-2018.pdf</link>
							<tag>MIL-STD-31000B (31 October 2018). Superseding MIL-STD-31000A (26 February 2013)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/493</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/493</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM about PDF/E-1.  PUID: fmt/493</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2043942</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q2043942</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about PDF/E-1.  Wikidata Title ID: Q2043942</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
