<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000478" titleName="HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 3.2" shortName="HTML_3_2" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2018-03-14</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 3.2</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>markup languages</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>HyperText Markup Language (HTML) is the standard markup language for creating web pages and web applications.  This format description is for HTML version 3.2, standardized under the auspices of the World Wide Web Consortium (<a href="https://www.w3.org/">W3C</a>).  The <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html32">HTML 3.2 Reference Specification</a> was published as a W3C Recommendation in January 1997.  This was the first HTML specification published by W3C after taking over responsibility for the markup language from the <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/wg/html/">HTML Working Group of the Internet Engineering Task Force</a> (IETF).</p>
			<p>The introduction to the specification includes, &quot;HTML 3.2 is W3C&apos;s specification for HTML, developed in early `96 together with vendors including IBM, Microsoft, Netscape Communications Corporation, Novell, SoftQuad, Spyglass, and Sun Microsystems. HTML 3.2 adds widely deployed features such as tables, applets and text flow around images, while providing full backwards compatibility with the existing standard HTML 2.0.&quot;  The Document Type Definition (DTD) included in the specification states, &quot;HTML 3.2 aims to capture recommended practice as of early &apos;96.&quot;</p>
			<p>Several features proposed as extensions to HTML 2.0 through IETF RFCs were incorporated into HTML 3.2.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>A standard markup for tables, using a subset of the proposal in <a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1942.txt">RFC 1942</a> (May 1996).</li>
				<li>An extension to the form feature to support uploading of files.  See <a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1867.txt">RFC 1867</a> (November 1995).</li>
				<li>Support for a client-side mechanism for image maps, which allow users to access different documents by clicking different areas in an image.  See <a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1980.txt">RFC 1980</a> (August 1996).</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Another feature new since HTML 2.0 was &lt;DIV&gt;, a grouping element with a CLASS attribute, intended to identify different kinds of containers, e.g. chapter, section, abstract, or appendix.</p>
			<p>A new &lt;APPLET&gt; element was introduced to support the running of applets in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java_(programming_language)">Java programming language</a> (not to be confused with JavaScript) in boxes on an HTML page.  This element is no longer supported by several browsers.  It was deprecated in <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20111205115900/http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html40-971218/html40.pdf">HTML 4.0</a>, in favor of the more general &lt;OBJECT&gt; element.  See <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/applet">&lt;applet&gt;: The Embed Java Applet element</a> at MDN (formerly the Mozilla Developer Network) and <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/17013405/are-applets-now-deprecated">Are applets now deprecated?</a> from Stack Overflow.</p>
			<p>Control of text flow was enhanced by the addition of adding a CLEAR attribute to the &lt;BR&gt; element.  This technique for allowing an image to &quot;float&quot; with text wrapping round it was deprecated in later versions of HTML, along with many other presentational elements and attributes, in favor of using CSS to achieve the same effect.</p>
			<p>Included in the DTD were &quot;placeholder&quot; elements &lt;SCRIPT&gt; and &lt;STYLE&gt;, intended to facilitate transition to the next version of HTML, which was expected to promote further separation of document structure from the layout to represent that structure. These tags would be used for &quot;client-side&quot; scripts and style sheet markup embedded in HTML documents rather than stored in linked external files.  Browsers were instructed to avoid showing the contents of these element.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>primary markup language used for creating pages and applications on the World Wide Web. HTML 3.2 was published in April 1997 as a W3C Recommendation by the World Wide Web Consortium.  Superseded by HTML 4.0 in December 1997 and HTML 4.01 in December 1999.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>The primary use of HTML is as a final-state format for web pages made available on the Internet.  Early HTML files were often created directly in a text editor.  By the time the specification for HTML 3.2 was published, visual (WYSIWIG) editors were available.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000475</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HTML_family</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>HTML File Format Family</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000477</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HTML_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 2.0</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000479</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>HTML_4_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>	HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 4.0</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000465</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>SGML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Standard Generalized Markup Language (SGML). ISO 8879:1986</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress home page archived on June 16, 1997 used HTML 3.2.  By May 2000, HTML 4.0 Transitional was used.  See also <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>
			<p>HTML 3.2, produced under the auspices of the W3C, is a non-proprietary format, openly developed and published, and freely implementable.</p>
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>
				<a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html32">Version 3.2 of the HTML specification</a> was published as a W3C Recommendation in January 1997.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>HTML 3.2 was widely used in the late 1990s and pages using this version of HTML are still to be found on the Web.  Some features permitted in HTML 3.2 are not supported in some browsers current as of March 2018. For example, the &lt;ISINDEX&gt; element is largely unsupported and the &lt;APPLET&gt; introduced in HTML 3.2 was already deprecated in favor of the &lt;OBJECT&gt; element  in HTML 4.0. Obsolete tags can be identified at <a href="https://caniuse.com/#search=isindex">CanIUse</a> or in the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/html5/obsolete.html">latest HTML 5.x specification</a>.</p>
			<p>See also <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p> No concerns.  See <a href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/copyright-software-19980519.html">W3C IPR Software Notice</a> that was applicable from 1995 to 1998 and the revised <a href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Legal/copyright-software-19980720">W3C Software Notice and License</a> introduced in August 1998. See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>All HTML files can be opened and viewed in text editors.  See also <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>
				<p>The character encoding specified for HTML 3.2 corresponds to ISO Latin-1 character set, comprising 191 graphic characters, including the alphabets of most
Western European languages.  Characters that could not be entered on a keyboard could be incorporated by using SGML-style entities.  For example, a lower-case e with acute accent could be typed as &amp;eacute; or &amp;#233; (the equivalent code in ISO Latin-1 as a decimal number).  For other textual characteristics of HTML documents, see <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</p>
			</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>Like previous versions of HTML, HTML 3,2 included structural elements for paragraphs, headings, ordered and unordered lists.  Also defined were &quot;blockquote&quot; blocks for wrapping a quotation from another source and two special list blocks, one for &quot;menus&quot; and another for &quot;directories.&quot;  HTML 3.2 also provided a &lt;DIV&gt; element that could be used, for example, to group paragraphs into a chapter.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>
				<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</p>
			</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>The HTML 3.2 specification includes no support for representing mathematics.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>HTML was developed specifically to support linking among online resources.  HTML 3.2 included support for forms that allowed users to enter data, for example, terms that could be used to query a database or user name and password to log in to a website.  HTML 3.2 also introduced the ability to embed  a Java applet in a rectangular area of a web page.</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC &quot;-//W3C//DTD HTML 3.2 Final//EN&quot;&gt;</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>The specification for HTML 3.2 requires that a conforming document start with a document type declaration that begins with &apos;&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC &quot;-//W3C//DTD HTML 3.2 Final//EN&quot;&gt;&apos;.   Note that lower case characters may be used.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/98</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/98">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/98</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q41676372</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q41676372">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q41676372</a>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general/>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The first formal standard for the HTML format was version 2.0, and published as RFC 1866 in November 1995 by the IETF. During 1995, the popularity of the web and conflicting ideas for new features, including from the emerging browser vendors, overwhelmed the IETF working group. A version 3.0 for HTML had been prepared as an IETF Internet Draft, but expired in September 1995 without moving to the IETF Standards track. A November 1995 meeting resulted in the forming of a new group under the auspices of the W3C, founded in 1994.  The new group consisted largely of representatives from browser vendors. The IETF HTML Working group disbanded in December 1995 and the W3C became the home for HTML standardization. The version of HTML described in this document was HTML 3.2, issued as a W3C Recommendation, in January 1997.</p>
			<p>The next version for HTML published was for <fddLink id="fdd000479">HTML 4.0</fddLink>, issued as a W3C Recommendation in December 1997.  See <fddLink id="fdd000475">HTML_family</fddLink> for more details on the chronology of HTML versions.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html32</link>
					<tag>W3C Recommendation | HTML 3.2 Reference Specification. 14-Jan-1997</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for HTML</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Below are links to IETF RFCs for extensions to HTML 2.0 that were incorporated in their entirety or in part into HTML 3.2.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1867.txt</link>
							<tag>IETF RFC 1867 | Form-based File Upload in HTML  (plain text)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1942.txt</link>
							<tag>IETF RFC 1942 | HTML Tables  (plain text)</tag>
							<comment>Incorporated into HTML 3.2 in part.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1980.txt</link>
							<tag>IETF RFC 1980 | A Proposed Extension to HTML : Client-Side Image Maps  (plain text)</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.w3.org/People/Raggett/html3/CoverPage.html</link>
					<tag>Internet Draft for HTML 3.0, published as draft-ietf-html-specv3-00.txt in April 1995.</tag>
					<comment>This Internet Draft did not progress to the IETF RFC stage.  However, many of the features described influenced HTML 3.2.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>PRONOM provides records for chronological versions of the HTML format that have distinguishing signatures (via a DOCTYPE declaration) and a record for generic HTML (recognizable only by the existence of opening and closing &lt;HTML&gt; or &lt;BODY&gt; tags, including tags in lower case).</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/98</link>
							<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/98</tag>
							<comment>HTML 3.2.  PUID: fmt/98.  With DOCTYPE declaration for 3.2</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/96</link>
							<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/96</tag>
							<comment>HTML (generic).  PUID: fmt/96</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q41676372</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q41676372</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about HTML 3.2.  Wikidata Title ID: Q41676372.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
