<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000208" titleName="AES3 Digital Audio Interface, SMPTE Extensions" shortName="AES3_SMPTE" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>sound</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
				</fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
			</fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>unitary</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2012-02-16</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Format for Non-PCM Audio and Data in an AES3 Serial Digital Audio Interface (formal name); Non-PCM AES3 (common name)</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>AES3</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers (SMPTE) extensions to the <fddLink id="fdd000142">AES3</fddLink> interface that specify a method for transmitting <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink> compressed audio (instead of the <fddLink id="fdd000011">LPCM</fddLink> uncompressed audio specified in AES3) and other types of data. The SMPTE extensions permit the inclusion of, and picture-synchronize with, multichannel surround sound within the technical confines of television technology. AC-3 audio, also known as Dolby Digital, is used in theater systems, DVDs, and can be incorporated in MPEG-2 streams. The other types of data specified in the extensions include "null data" (to permit preamble sync codes to be inserted into the data stream) and time stamp data to support synchronization.  Additional SMPTE specifications concern wrapping tracks encoded in what they call the AES3 format in <fddLink id="fdd000013">MXF</fddLink>.  See the list of <a href="#specs">Format specifications</a> below.</p>
			<p>The main thrust of <fddLink id="fdd000142">AES3</fddLink> and this extension thereof concerns cabling and the physical interface between devices (see <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below).  This Web site, however, is primarily devoted to encodings and file, wrapper, or bundling formats.  At times, the SMPTE standards refers to AES3 as an encoding (e.g., SMPTE standard 382M, <i>Mapping AES3 Streams and Broadcast Wave Audio to the MXF Generic Container</i>) and this has led to its inclusion at this Web site.</p>
			<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AES3">Wikipedia article on AES3</a> (consulted on March 8, 2011) reports that the specification is &quot;officially known as AES3 and frequently called AES/EBU and also published as part of IEC 60958.&quot;</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers (SMPTE) extensions to the AES3 interface that specify a method for transmitting AC-3 compressed audio (instead of the LPCM uncompressed audio specified in AES3) and other types of data. The SMPTE extensions permit the inclusion of, and picture-synchronize with, multichannel surround sound within the technical confines of existing television technology. AC-3 audio, also known as Dolby Digital, is used in theater systems, DVDs, and can be incorporated in MPEG-2 streams. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Most often used as a middle state (&quot;post-production&quot;) or final state (&quot;release, dissemated, broadcast&quot;) format.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Extension of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000209</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>AC-3</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>AC-3 Compressed Audio (Dolby Digital), Revision A</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>MPEG-2 program stream or file with <fddLink id="fdd000028">MPEG-2</fddLink> and AES3 Digital Audio Interface, SMPTE Extensions (Dolby and surround audio encoding).  Not described at this Web site at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>MXF File, OP1a, AES3 Audio in Generic Container, not described at this Web site at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>MXF File, OP1a, SDTI-CP in Generic Container, not described at this Web site at this time.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>Not determined; Library collections include DVDs and are known to include files with MPEG-2 video with &quot;layer II&quot; audio streams.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>Not determined.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Open standard. Developed by the Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers (SMPTE), using an Audio Engineering Society (AES) standard as the basis.
		</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>Covered by a variety of SMPTE and AES documents; see <a href="#specs">Format specifications</a> below.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Appears to be widely adopted, apparently to the greatest degree for DVDs and MPEG-2 video streams; <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>None on the interface specification; see also <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink>.</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>The interface specification is transparent; see also <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink>.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>See <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink>.</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>The AES3 specification used as a basis covers wiring and cable connectors.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Good support.</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>See <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink>.</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>See <fddLink id="fdd000209">AC-3</fddLink>.</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:samples>Not applicable</fdd:samples>
			<fdd:beyondSound>Capable of including data that supports synchronization with video picture streams.</fdd:beyondSound>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>In general, not applicable; the encoded data will be in one of the &quot;used by&quot; formats listed in Relationships above.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>aes</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>Reported as an extension for raw data adhering to SMPTE ST 302 (Mapping of AES3 Data into an MPEG-2 Transport Stream) when saved as a file by Snell  Wilcox devices.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>Not applicable.</fdd:sigValueNA>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>The main body of <fddLink id="fdd000142">AES3</fddLink> specifies signal transmission via a single shielded twisted wire pair.  Annex D, however, discusses the carriage of AES3 signals on structured wiring, e.g., the "category 5" cables associated with computer network installations, a topic that receives extended treatment in AES47, which specifies the method of carrying multiple channels of audio in linear PCM or AES3 format across an asynchronous transfer mode (ATM) network.  Elaborations on audio signal transfer are the topics of AES10-2003, <i>AES Recommended Practice for Digital Audio Engineering --  Serial Multichannel Audio Digital Interface (MADI)</i> (Revision of AES10-1991), and AES50-2005, <i>AES standard for digital audio engineering -- High-resolution multi-channel audio interconnection.</i>
		</fdd:general>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>SMPTE specifications available to members or for purchase via <a href="https://www.smpte.org/standards/">https://www.smpte.org/standards/</a>.  The standards catalog is part of SMPTE&apos;s <a href="https://www.smpte.org/digital-library">https://www.smpte.org/digital-library</a>, implemented through the IEEE Xplore Digital Library.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7291630</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 302-2007. Television - Mapping of AES3 Data into MPEG-2 Transport Stream</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7290787</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 331-2011. Television - Element and Metadata Definitions for the SDTI-CP</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7291909</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 337-2008. Television - Format for Non-PCM Audio and Data in AES3 Serial Digital Audio Interface</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7292080</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 338-2010. Television - Format for Non-PCM Audio and Data in AES3 - Data Types</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7292020</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 339-2008. Television - Format for Non-PCM Audio and Data in AES3 - Generic Data Types</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7290784</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 340-2015. Television - Format for Non-PCM Audio and Data in AES3 - ATSC A/52 (AC-3) Data Type</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7292005</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 341-2000. Television - Format for Non-PCM Audio and Data in AES3 - Captioning Data Type</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=7292191</link>
							<tag>SMPTE ST 369-2002. Television - Type D-11 Data Stream and AES3 Data Mapping over SDTI</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>AES specifications available to members or for purchase via <a href="http://www.aes.org/publications/standards/">http://www.aes.org/publications/standards/</a>
					</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.aes.org/publications/standards/search.cfm?docID=13</link>
							<tag>AES3-2009 (r2014): AES standard for digital audio engineering - Serial transmission format for two-channel linearly represented digital audio data</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.aes.org/publications/standards/search.cfm?docID=14</link>
							<tag>AES5-2008 (r2013): AES recommended practice for professional digital audio - Preferred sampling frequencies for applications employing pulse-code modulation</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AES3</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia article on AES3</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
