<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000618" titleName="Exchangeable Image File Format (Exif) Family" shortName="EXIF_Family" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>still-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>sound</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
				</fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
			</fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>family</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrComposition>container-wrapper</fdd:gdfrComposition>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>binary</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>unstructured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>sampled</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2023-11-03</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Exchangeable Image File Format (Exif) Family</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>raster image formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>metadata formats</fdd:keyword>
			<fdd:keyword>audio formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>The Exchangeable Image File Format (Exif) family is based on a specification that combines established file encoding standards such as <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000001">WAV</fddLink> with structured, embedded metadata referred to as <i>Exif</i> data. These specifications primarily focus on recording technical information. The first version of the <a href="https://www.jeita.or.jp/english/">JEIDA (Japan Electronic Industry Development Association)</a> authored specification published in 1996 is titled <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20131111073619/http://www.exif.org/Exif2-1.PDF">Exchangeable image file format
for Digital Still Cameras: Exif </a> and was primarily associated with digital photography (with the goal to document &quot;the method of recording image data in files&quot;). However, starting with version 2.1, this was expanded to sound recordings to capture "the method of writing audio data in files." In essence, they define the formats of images, sounds, tags, and other metadata found within files generated by digital still cameras and similar systems.</p>
			<p>The Exif specification is divided into two main categories: image file specifications and audio file specifications. The image file specifications support <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF</fddLink>- and <fddLink id="fdd000018">JFIF/JPEG</fddLink>-based encoded files, while the audio file specifications are geared toward WAVE files. While the <a href="https://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/download_e.html?DC-008-Translation-2023-E">Exif specification</a> defines criteria for TIFF, JPEG, and WAV files, Exif data may also appear in other formats that don't adhere strictly to the specification.
			</p>
			<p>The official title of this standard is "Exchangeable image file format for digital still camera" ,however, the standard caters to both still image and audio files, encompassing the Exif image and the Exif audio file specification. It's worth noting that this standard is applicable to various devices, including digital cameras, digital video cameras (DVC), smartphones, digital photo frames, PCs, and printers, all of which have functionalities related to capturing, generating, recording, displaying, editing, and printing images.</p>
			<p>Exif metadata tags include descriptive metadata, copyright details, camera settings, technical image data, date and time information, geographic data, and thumbnail storage.</p>
			<p>Specifically for image data, the metadata fields include number of pixels, pixel aspect ratio (required to be square 1:1), pixel composition and sampling (describing color space with the required values of RGB 4:4:4 and either Y:Cb:Cr = 4:2:2 or Y:Cb:Cr = 4:2:0), and image data arrangement.</p>
			<p>For audio data, metadata fields include sampling frequency (with defined values per compression scheme), bit size, channels (monaural or stereo [2 ch])) and compression scheme (with options of uncompressed <fddLink id="fdd000016">Pulse Code Modulation [PCM]</fddLink>, uncompressed <fddLink id="fdd000039">µ-Law or Mu-Law</fddLink> or compressed Adaptive Differential PCM Sound Format [ADPCM]) within a <fddLink id="fdd000001">WAVE Audio File Format</fddLink> container.</p>
			<p>When these formats are used as Exif/DCF (Design rule for Camera File System) files in conjunction with the DCF Standard (which guarantees interoperability among various device types), their scope extends to devices, systems, recording media, and application software designed to handle them (as specified in <a href="https://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/download_e.html?DC-008-Translation-2023-E">Version 3.0</a> of the specification).</p>
			<p>See <a href="#notes">History</a> for a timeline of the Exif specification versions and <a href="#sustainabilityFactors">Self Documentation</a> for version-declaring embedded metadata.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>The Exchangeable Image File Format (Exif) family comprises a group encoding standards including but not limited to JPG, TIFF, and WAV with defined embedded metadata primarily focuses on recording technical information. The standard is published by CIPA (Camera and Imaging Products Association) and applies to various devices, from cameras to PCs, and encompasses descriptive metadata, copyright information, camera settings, and more. </fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Generally applied by cameras in initial-state picture creation; may also be used for middle- and final-state archiving or end-user delivery.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000146</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>EXIF_2_2</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Exif Exchangeable Image File Format, Version 2.2</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000147</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>JPEG_EXIF</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Details about Exif data for JPEG in <a href="">Exif Specification version 3</a>. </fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000145</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>TIFF_UNC_EXIF</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Details about Exif data for TIFF in <a href="">Exif Specification version 3</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:titleName>WAVE with Exif Metadata</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Not described separately at this time. Details about Exif data for WAV in <a href="">Exif Specification</a>.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>The Prints and Photographs Division and the Manuscript Division have collections containing digital-camera generated photographs in <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG_EXIF</fddLink> as well as <fddLink id="fdd000147">TIFF_UNC_EXIF</fddLink>. Specific Exif versions are unknown.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See the Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement for format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/stillimg.html">still image works</a> and <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/audio.html">audio works</a>. The RFS does not mandate or suggest the use of Exif data.</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Fully documented; developed under the auspices of JEITA (Japan Electronics and Information Technology Industries Association). Since 2009, JEITA and CIPA (Camera and Imaging Products Association) have jointly managed the Exif standard.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			Fully documented. The most recent version, as of this writing in November 2023 is  <a href="">Exchangeable image file format for digital still cameras: version 3</a>. Jointly published as CIPA: DC-008-2023 and JIETA: CP-3451F.		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>Supported by almost all digital cameras. Widely supported by smartphone cameras and PC cameras, digital photo frames, printers, and similar. See a non-definitive list of formats and tags on the <a href="https://exiftool.org/TagNames/index.html">ExifTool Tag Names table index</a>. 
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>.
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			See <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>.
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>The Exif version is stored as 4 bytes at the start of the file classified as A1, A2, B1, and B2. A1 and A2 hold the upper part of the version and B1 and B2 store the lower. When updating the standard version, the following rules apply:</p>
			<p>1. If changes allow data readers to recognize conventional information and skip data with new functions, the lower part of the version (B1, B2) changes.</p>
			<p>2. If there's a risk that an older data reader might malfunction due to new specs, the upper part of the version (A1, A2) changes.</p>
			<p>Players should support playback of files from earlier versions of the standard. See section 4.6.6.1.1 of <a href="https://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/download_e.html?DC-008-Translation-2023-E">the specification</a> for more details. 
			</p>
			<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>. Exif tags are included in <a href="../content/tiff_tags.shtml">Tags for TIFF and Related Specifications</a>.
			</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None. The standard states that all players must be future-compatible with versions earlier than the supported standard.
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None. However, the standard supports the ability for custom metadata fields to be added. Some camera manufacturers use this to store encrypted metadata. The specification does not mention encryption. For an example of encrypted metadata fields added by a manufacturer, see Phil Harvey's Exiftool <a href="https://exiftool.org/TagNames/Nikon.html">page on Nikon cameras</a>.
		</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:stillImageQF>
			<fdd:normalImage>Good support. The presence of Exif data does not influence typical image rendering.</fdd:normalImage>
			<fdd:clarity>See <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>.
			</fdd:clarity>
			<fdd:colorMaint>
				<p>See <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>.
				</p>
				<p>Version 2.0 introduced sRGB support.</p>
				<p>Versions 2.2 and forward have tags which permit the identification of files that use sRGB.1.  Exif 2.2 also allows the identification of the Adobe RGB color profile. There appears to be no Exif tag for the ICC profile for a capture device.  See <fddLink id="fdd000146">Exif Exchangeable Image File Format, Version 2.2</fddLink> for more detail.</p>
			</fdd:colorMaint>
			<fdd:graphics>No support for vector graphics.</fdd:graphics>
			<fdd:multispectral>None.</fdd:multispectral>
			<fdd:beyondImage>Supports thumbnails and audio content. See below for more detail on audio quality and functionality.</fdd:beyondImage>
		</fdd:stillImageQF>
		<fdd:soundQF>
			<fdd:normalSound>Good support. The presence of Exif data does not influence typical audio playback.</fdd:normalSound>
			<fdd:fidelity>Good, depending on encoding, sampling frequency, and word length.  Exif supports the following encodings: <fddLink id="fdd000011">LPCM</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000039">μ-Law</fddLink> PCM (conforming to ITU-T G.711) for uncompressed audio data; IMA ADPCM (Adaptive Differential PCM) for compressed audio data.  Highest fidelity from LPCM is limited in this standard to CD quality (44.1 kHz sampling and 16 bit words).</fdd:fidelity>
			<fdd:channels>
				<p>Stereo or monoaural only.</p>
				<p>See specifications for <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20131230103425/http:/exif.org/specifications.html">Version 2.2</a> and <a href="https://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/download_e.html?DC-008-Translation-2023-E">Version 3.0</a> for more details.</p>
			</fdd:channels>
			<fdd:samples>None.</fdd:samples>
			<fdd:beyondSound>None beyond the above described still image support.</fdd:beyondSound>
		</fdd:soundQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>wav</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>jpg</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>tif</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>
				
From <a href="">Exif Specification version 3</a> and previous versions with "wav" added starting version 2.1.  While the container formats may accept other extensions, such as "jpeg" or "tif", the Exif specification declares only these values.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>
					See <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>.
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>
					See <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>.
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>x-fmt/397</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Exchangeable Image File Format (Audio), Version 2.0. Short name 	Exif Audio (2.0). See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/397">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/397</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>x-fmt/389</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Exchangeable Image File Format (Audio), Version 2.1. Short name 	Exif Audio (2.1). See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/389">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/389</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See also <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF Uncompressed File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See also <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG Encoded File with Exif Metadata</fddLink>
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q196465</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata entry for Exif format. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q196465">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q196465</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q26383099</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata entry for Exif image family. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26383099">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26383099</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q43976633</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>Wikidata entry for Exif audio family. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q43976633">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q43976633</a>.
					</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>Global positioning system (GPS) support was introduced in Version 2.0.  Further improvements to GPS support were added in Version 2.2.</p>
			<p>Supporting tags for composite images were added in Version 2.32.</p>
			<p>Version 3.0 added support for UTF-8/Unicode, Box-structured data, and added or changed the definitions for several tags including: Title, Photographer, ImageEditor, CameraFirmware, RAWDevelopingSoftware, ImageEditingSoftware, MetadataEditingSoftware, Software, Artist, ImageUniqueID, GPSAltitudeRef, GPSMeasureMode, XResolution, YResolution, ResolutionUnit, and FlashpixVersion. UTF-8 character support became Exif compliant in this version.</p>
			<p>When Exif is utilized with JPEG files, it stores Exif data within one of JPEG's predefined utility Application Segments known as APP1 (with the segment marker 0xFFE1). Essentially, this segment functions as a container for an entire TIFF file. In the case of Exif usage with TIFF files, including those embedded within other TIFF files, the TIFF Private Tag 0x8769 establishes a sub-Image File Directory (IFD) that houses Exif-specific TIFF Tags. Furthermore, Exif defines a Global Positioning System sub-IFD through the TIFF Private Tag 0x8825 to store location data, and it specifies an "Interoperability IFD" within the Exif sub-IFD using the Exif tag 0xA005.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>EXIF was developed by Japan Electronic Industries Development Association (JEIDA).  In 2000, JEIDA and the Electronic Industries Development Association (EIAJ) merged to form the <a href="http://www.jeita.or.jp/english/about/what/">Japan Electronics and Information Technology Industries Association</a> (JEITA). In 2009 the <a href="http://www.cipa.jp/guide/documents/e/en0203.pdf">Camera and Imaging Products Association</a> (CIPA) joined JEITA in the management of the Exif standard.  CIPA was established in 2002 as a successor to the Japan Camera Industry Association (JCIA). CIPA consists of companies engaged in the development, production, or distribution of digital cameras, imaging-related products, and software.</p>
			<p>About JEITA: "The Japan Electronics and Information Technology Industries Association (JEITA) was formed on November 1, 2000, through the merger of the Electronic Industries Association of Japan (EIAJ) and Japan Electronic Industries Development Association (JEIDA). JEITA is a new industry organization in Japan with activities covering both the electronics and information technology (IT) fields." (<a href="http://www.jeita.or.jp/english/about/what/">http://www.jeita.or.jp/english/about/what/</a>).</p>
			<p>About CIPA: The Camera and Imaging Products Association (CIPA) was established in 2002 as a successor organization to the Japan Camera Industry Association (JCIA).  JCIA participated in the original development of Exif.  CIPA &quot;is an industry association consisting of companies engaged in the development, production, or distribution of digital cameras, imaging-related products, and software&quot; (<a href="http://www.cipa.jp/guide/documents/e/en0203.pdf">http://www.cipa.jp/guide/documents/e/en0203.pdf</a>).</p>
			<p>Timeline for Exif development:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Version 1.0.  Published October 1995.</li>
				<li>Version 1.1.  Published May 1997</li>
				<li>Version 2.0.  Published November 1997.</li>
				<li>Version 2.1.  Published December 1998.</li>
				<li>Version 2.2. </li>
				<li>Version 2.21.  Published September 2003 as a set of changes.  Promoted as &quot;Exif Print.&quot;</li>
				<li>Unified Version 2.21.  Published September 2009.</li>
				<li>Version 2.3.  Published April 2010.</li>
				<li>Version 2.3 (Revised 2012).  Published December 2012 (with two explanations corrected).</li>
				<li>Version 2.31: Published in July 2016.</li>
				<li>Version 2.32: Published in May 2019.</li>
				<li>Version 3.0: Published in May 2023.</li>
			</ul>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20131230103425/http://exif.org/specifications.html</link>
					<tag>Specifications for Exif 2.1 and 2.2 from former Exif.org site</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/e/DC-008-2010_E.pdf</link>
					<tag>Specifications for Exif Version 2.3</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/e/DC-008-2012_E.pdf</link>
					<tag>Specifications for Exif Version 2.3 (2012 Revision)</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/e/DC-008-Translation-2016-E.pdf</link>
					<tag>Specifications for Exif Version 2.31</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/download_e.html?DC-010-2020_E</link>
					<tag>Specifications for Exif Version 2.32</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.cipa.jp/std/documents/download_e.html?DC-008-Translation-2023-E</link>
					<tag>Exif Version 3.0</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>See also <fddLink id="fdd000147">JPEG_EXIF</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000145">TIFF_UNC_EXIF</fddLink> and <fddLink id="fdd000146">EXIF_2_2</fddLink>.</fdd:intro>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://exiftool.org/TagNames/index.html</link>
					<tag>ExifTool Tag Names</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/content/tiff_tags.shtml</link>
					<tag>Library of Congress - TIFF Tags</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.jeita.or.jp/english/about/what/</link>
					<tag>Japan Electronics and Information Technology Industries Association (JEITA) - About JEITA.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.cipa.jp/guide/documents/e/en0203.pdf</link>
					<tag>Camera and Imaging Products Association (CIPA) - About CIPA</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/corkami/pics/blob/master/binary/tiff_exif.png</link>
					<tag>GitHub - TIFF/Exif File Format Structure. Ange Albertini's binary infographic for TIFF with Exif data.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.media.mit.edu/pia/Research/deepview/exif.html</link>
					<tag>MIT Media Lab - DeepView: Exif Data Visualization</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.iptc.org/news/exif-3-0-released-featuring-utf-8-support/</link>
					<tag>IPTC News - Exif 3.0 Released Featuring UTF-8 Support</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Wikidata entries:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q196465</link>
							<tag>Wikidata entry for Exif format</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26383099</link>
							<tag>Wikidata entry for Exif image family.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q43976633</link>
							<tag>Wikidata entry for Exif audio family.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Pronom entries:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/397</link>
							<tag>PRONOM entry for x-fmt/397, Exchangeable Image File Format (Audio), Version 2.0. Short name 	Exif Audio (2.0). </tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/389</link>
							<tag>PRONOM entry for x-fmt/389, Exchangeable Image File Format (Audio), Version 2.1. Short name 	Exif Audio (2.1).</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/x-fmt/396</link>
							<tag>PRONOM entry for x-fmt/396, Exchangeable Image File Format (Audio), Version 2.2. Short name 	Exif Audio (2.2).</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
