<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000395" titleName="OOXML Format Family -- ISO/IEC 29500 and ECMA 376" shortName="OOXML_Family" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-1.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>spreadsheet</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>presentation</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>dataset</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>any</fdd:gdfrGenre>
			</fdd:gdfrGenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrForm>text</fdd:gdfrForm>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:gdfrDomains>
			<fdd:gdfrDomain>
				<fdd:value>office/business</fdd:value>
			</fdd:gdfrDomain>
		</fdd:gdfrDomains>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2017-02-21</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Office Open XML (OOXML, ISO/IEC 29500, ECMA 376) Format Family</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:keywords>
			<fdd:keyword>document formats</fdd:keyword>
		</fdd:keywords>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>This description is an overview of the <i>family</i> of formats defined by <i>ISO/IEC 29500:  Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- Office Open XML File Formats</i> and the corresponding <i>ECMA 376</i> specifications.</p>
			<p>This family of XML-based formats was designed by Microsoft to match the functionality of the proprietary binary formats that had been used as the default formats in Microsoft Office applications (Word, Excel, and PowerPoint) through Office 2003 and be fully compatible with the existing corpus of documents.  In December 2005, a Technical Committee of the ECMA standardization organization (TC45) was established to review documentation for the proposed Office Open XML specification submitted by Microsoft.  The committee incorporated expertise from large customers using Microsoft Office for enterprise systems, software vendors already developing products to read, write, and transform office documents, and archival institutions with an interest in long-term preservation.  The resulting document was approved as ECMA 376 in December 2006 and was then submitted for standardization through ISO/IEC JTC 1 in early 2007.  Approval as ISO/IEC 29500 followed in early 2008. ISO/IEC 29500 incorporated many detailed changes and a restructuring of the parts.  One important change was to separate the specifications for markup that supports the functional requirements of the three main content categories from the specifications for elements and attributes that support backwards compatibility and legacy formats.  Legacy markup was documented in a new part under the title <i>Transitional Migration Features</i>.  Files that comply with ISO/IEC 29500 Part 1 are termed "Strict" and files that comply with Part 4 (which is structured as textual modifications to Part 1) are termed "Transitional."</p>
			<p>The primary members of the OOXML Format Family are document formats for the key office productivity content categories:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>DOCX for word-processing files, specified via WordprocessingML.  See <fddLink id="fdd000397">DOCX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</li>
				<li>XLSX for spreadsheet files, specified via SpreadsheetML.  See <fddLink id="fdd000398">XLSX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</li>
				<li>PPTX for presentation/slideshow files, specified via PresentationML.  See <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Key supporting members of the format family include:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>A package format based on ZIP that is used as a container by all three primary OOXML content categories and other non-OOXML file formats, such as Visio .vsdx and Open XML Paper Specification .oxps files.  See <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</li>
				<li>A markup language, Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (MCE), for supporting extensibility of an XML-based format over time, so that files created by future application versions and using new elements and attributes in new namespaces can be structured in a way that earlier application versions can still read the files and take appropriate actions when faced with markup using the new namespaces.  Any of the three primary content types can include markup using the MCE namespace and schema.  Like OPC, MCE can be applied beyond OOXML.  See <fddLink id="fdd000396">MCE/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>WordprocessingML, SpreadsheetML, and PresentationML are specified in Parts 1 and 4 of ISO/IEC 29500.  Part 1 defines the Strict variant of these three formats.  Part 4, written as a supplement to Part 1, specifies additional markup to support compatibility with various legacy applications.  The Transitional variant of each of these formats allows markup documented in Part 4 in addition to that documented in Part 1.  In addition to the three main markup languages (MLs), the standard defines several supporting markup languages and schemas: DrawingML, which includes markup for graphical elements in any of the three main document types, including embedded images, vector graphics for diagrams, and analytical charts derived from data in a document; Office Math Markup Language (OMML), which supports the display of mathematics in the context of applications that support collaborative editing and tracked changes within mathematical expressions; a schema for bibliographies; and several supporting schemas for document properties (core, extended, and custom).  Part 4 includes the specification for VML, a deprecated graphics language superseded by DrawingML.</p>
			<p>Several closely related formats are covered completely or in large part by the ISO/IEC 29500 and ECMA 376 specifications.  These include documents used as templates for other documents and macro-enabled variants of the primary content types.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>Overview of the family of formats defined by ISO/IEC 29500:  Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- Office Open XML File Formats.  Includes DOCX, XLSX, and PPTX.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>OOXML can be used in any production phase for office documents, as they are created (initial state), exchanged for editing and review (middle-state), and published (final-state).</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000363</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>OPC/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Open Packaging Conventions (Office Open XML) , ISO/IEC 29500-2:2008-2012</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000397</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>DOCX/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>DOCX Transitional (Office Open XML), ISO 29500:2008-2012, ECMA-376</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Uses WordprocessingML in an <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink> package.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000400</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>DOCX/OOXML_Strict_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>DOCX Strict (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-1:2008-2012, ECMA-376, Editions 2-4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Disallows legacy markup permitted in DOCX Transitional to support backwards compatibility.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000398</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XLSX/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>XLSX Transitional (Office Open XML), ISO 29500:2008-2012, ECMA-376</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Uses SpreadsheetML in an <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink> package.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000401</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XLSX/OOXML_Strict_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>XLSX Strict (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-1:2008-2012, ECMA-376, Editions 2-4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Disallows legacy markup permitted in XLSX Transitional to support backwards compatibility.  Permits storage of dates in profile of ISO 8601 date and time format.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000399</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PPTX/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PPTX Transitional (Office Open XML), ISO 29500:2008-2012, ECMA-376</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Uses PresentationML in an <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink> package.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000402</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>PPTX/OOXML_Strict_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>PPTX Strict (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-1:2008-2012, ECMA-376, Editions 2-4</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
				<fdd:comment>Disallows legacy markup permitted in PPTX Transitional to support backwards compatibility.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has subtype</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Other application-specific formats fully defined by OOXML as specified in ISO/IEC 29500.  These include .dotx, .potx, and .xltx, template files as used and produced by Microsoft Office products since Office 2007.  The template formats are not described separately at this web site; they are essentially identical to the corresponding document formats, which are described as subtypes and linked above.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has modified version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:comment>Other application-specific formats closely related to OOXML.  These include .docm, .pptm, and .xlsm files, macro-enabled formats as produced by Microsoft Office products since Office 2007.  The macro-enabled variant formats are not described at this web site at this time.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for more on Microsoft Office use of macros.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>May contain</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000396</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>MCE/OOXML_2012</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (Office Open XML), ISO 29500-3:2008-2015</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Subtype of</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000355</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>ZIP_6_2_0</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>ZIP File Format, Version 6.2.0 (PKWARE)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000075</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>
			<p>LC was represented on ECMA TC45 during the initial standardization processes and continues to be active in the maintenance through SC34/WG4.</p>
			<p>For other aspects of LC experience with OOXML, see individual subtypes, particularly <fddLink id="fdd000397">DOCX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000398">XLSX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>
			<p>The Library of Congress Recommended Format Statement (RFS) includes OOXML as an accepted format for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/textmus.html">textual works in digital form</a> and <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/textmus.html">electronic serials</a>. See individual subtypes, particularly <fddLink id="fdd000397">DOCX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000398">XLSX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
		</fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Family of formats based on international open standard.  Maintained by ISO/IEC JTC1 SC34/WG4.  Originated by Microsoft Corporation and first standardized through ECMA International in 2006.  Approval as ISO/IEC 29500 was in 2008.</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<p>
				<i>ISO/IEC 29500, Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Parts 1-4.</i>  Latest version (2016 as of February 2017) is available from <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/">ISO/IEC Publicly Available Standards</a>.</p>
			<p>All editions of the OOXML standards as published by ECMA are available from <a href="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm">ECMA-376: Office Open XML File Formats</a>.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below for a chronology.</p>
			<p>Annex L of Part 1 is a Primer (informative rather than normative) that introduces key features of the constituent markup languages, including WordprocessingML, SpreadsheetML, and PresentationML, relating elements and attributes to intended functionality through examples.</p>
		</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>
			<p>Widely adopted.  See individual subtypes for more detail.</p>
			<p>In addition to end user applications that support OOXML, some open-source software libraries are available.  <a href="https://libopc.codeplex.com/">libOPC</a> provides support for reading and writing the OPC packages and also support for processing markup using the Markup Compatibility and Extensibility (MCE) mechanisms defined in the standard.  In June 2014, Microsoft released its <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/bb448854.aspx">Open XML SDK</a> (first released for use in 2007), as open source.  <a href="https://poi.apache.org/">Apache POI - the Java API for Microsoft Documents</a> provides some open source support for OOXML documents, but admits that not all features are handled, with XSLX support being &quot;most developed.&quot;</p>
			<p>As applications have introduced support for OOXML, some developers have run into interoperability problems.  Many of these have been forwarded as defect reports to the working group maintaining ISO/IEC 29500 and resolved through clarifications or small corrections in new editions of the OOXML standard or statements by Microsoft as to variations from the standard in Word, Excel, and PowerPoint in <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee908652.aspx">[MS-OI29500]</a> (Office Implementation Information for ISO/IEC 29500 Standards Support) and <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee908654.aspx">[MS-OE376]</a> (Office Implementation Information for ECMA-376 Standards Support).</p>
		</fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>
			<p>The specification originated from Microsoft Corporation.  Current and future versions of ISO/IEC 29500 and ECMA-376 are covered by Microsoft&apos;s <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/openspecifications/dn646765">Open Specification Promise</a>, whereby Microsoft &quot;irrevocably promises&quot; not to assert any claims against those making, using, and selling conforming implementations of any specification covered by the promise (so long as those accepting the promise refrain from suing Microsoft for patent infringement in relation to Microsoft&apos;s implementation of the covered specification).</p>
		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>
			<p>For transparency of the package containing the constituent parts of the DOCX file, see <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
			<p>Inside the OPC package, the OOXML formats are XML-based and inherently more transparent than their binary predecessors.  See individual subtypes for more detail.</p>
		</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>
			<p>See individual subtypes, in particular <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, the package format that is used by the other formats.</p>
		</fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>
			<p>None, beyond XML-aware software.  See individual subtypes, in particular <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, the package format that is used by the other formats.</p>
		</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>Encryption is not permitted within the OPC package [<fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink>] used to wrap all OOXML documents as of 2014.  However, an OPC package may be encrypted and some applications using this container format as the basis for a more specific format, may use encryption during interchange or DRM for distribution.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:otherQF>
			<fdd:factor>
				<fdd:tag>See individual subtypes</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:note>
					<p>See individual subtypes, particularly <fddLink id="fdd000397">DOCX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000398">XLSX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</p>
				</fdd:note>
			</fdd:factor>
		</fdd:otherQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>docx</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>xlsx</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>pptx</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>And extensions used by other formats based on the OOXML specifications.  See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> below.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.document</fdd:sigValue>
					<fdd:sigValue>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.presentationml.document</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>From <a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/media-types.xhtml">IANA assignments site</a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>File signature</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000354">ZIP_PK</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>XML namespace declaration</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/.../2006/main</fdd:sigValue>
						<fdd:sigValue>http://purl.oclc.org/ooxml/.../main</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>The first pattern is for the Transitional variants of the three OOXML document types, with the ellipses being replaced by <i>wordprocessingml</i>, <i>spreadsheetml</i>, or <i>presentationml</i> as appropriate.  The second pattern applies to the Strict variants of the three document types, with the same substitutions for the ellipses.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>fmt/189</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/189">http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/189</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>The Wikidata:WikiProject Informatics/File formats resource provides records for a large number of OOXML subtypes. See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:WikiProject_Informatics/File_formats/Lists/File_formats">Wikidata:WikiProject Informatics/File formats/Lists/File formats</a>.  See also descriptions of subtypes on this website, for example, <fddLink id="fdd000397">DOCX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000398">XLSX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>
			<p>
				<b>File extensions used:</b>  The extensions listed below are commonly used.  They are not defined in ISO/IEC 29500, but most of them are specified in the many MIME type registrations made with IANA, using the pattern <i>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument...</i>.  Macro-enabled versions of the primary document types and of templates are for files that do not technically comply with the OOXML standard, which does not permit the use of macros.  But the files do use the <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink> package specification and many parts of the package follow the official standard.  See note below for more on macro-enabled files, which are documented by Microsoft.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Wordprocessing file extensions: .docx (document); dotx (template). Not strictly OOXML but very closely related: .docm (macro-enabled document); .dotm (macro-enabled template)</li>
				<li>Spreadsheet file extensions: .xlsx (spreadsheet); .xltx (template).  Not strictly OOXML but very closely related:  .xlsm (macro-enabled spreadsheet); .xltm (macro-enabled template); .xlsb (XML-based structure with binary data, for faster loading and smaller files, intended to address early performance problems for very large .xlsx spreadsheets)</li>
				<li>Presentation file extensions: .pptx (presentation for editing); .ppsx (slideshow for running); .potx (presentation template); .pptm (macro-enabled presentation for editing); .ppsm (macro-enabled slideshow for running); .potm (macro-enabled template)</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				<b>Macro-enabled variants:</b>  The macro-enabled variants of the OOXML formats are straightforward extensions of the primary formats without macros.  They use <fddLink id="fdd000363">OPC/OOXML_2012</fddLink> as a package, simply adding a few parts that contain the macros and associated data.  Macros for Office are written in Visual Basic for Applications (VBA).  Note that macros do not work in Office for Mac 2008. In Office for Mac 2011 (the latest version as of 2014), macros are supported.  However, not all macros originally written for a Windows version of Office will run on a Mac without modification to take account of differences between the implementations of VBA for the Windows and Mac (OS X) versions of Office, for example those that use ActiveX or other Windows-specific features.  The additional parts for macros are defined in three supplementary documents:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc313094.aspx">[MS-OVBA]</a> specifies the format for a file that holds the macro code for a VBA (Visual Basic for Applications) Project.  All the macros for a workbook are included in a single file/part.</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd925808.aspx">[MS-OFFMACRO]</a>, applicable to Office 2007, specifies the structure that connects the VBA Project part to the workbook, including an optional part for VBA Supplemental Data, and two parts that support use of older macros from Excel 4.0 (Macro Sheets and International Macro Sheets).</li>
				<li>
					<a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd947889.aspx">[MS-OFFMACRO2]</a> performs the same function as [MS-OFFMACRO], but is applicable to Office 2010 and Office 2013.  The two specifications are almost identical except for the standards they reference and one small new feature added to VBA with version 7.0.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Note that the VBA Editor used to develop macros and distributed as part of desktop Office applications for Windows (but hidden from users by default), offers the ability to export VBA macro code as a .BAS file (which is a regular text file).  Microsoft applications offer a Save As option to drop the macro-related parts from a macro-enabled file and create a regular document. This is commonly done to archive a snapshot of a document or spreadsheet in which macros are used to update the file, perhaps based on external data.  Apache Open Office and LibreOffice offer options as to how to handle macros on import of .xlsm files.  Neither application can run all VBA macros as-is, although, according to <a href="https://help.libreoffice.org/Common/Using_Microsoft_Office_and">Using Microsoft Office and LibreOffice</a> in late 2014, &quot;recent versions of LibreOffice can run some Visual Basic scripts&quot; if the feature is enabled.</p>
		</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>The first XML-based formats for Word and Excel were included in the release of Office 2003; these were flat XML files. These are <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa214923.aspx">partially documented</a> on the Microsoft Development Network (MSDN) site.  These formats were precursors to OOXML, with both similarities and significant differences.</p>
			<p>The original OOXML specification was published as ECMA-376 in 2006.  The primary difference between that version and the version published as ISO/IEC 29500:2008 was the split between the Strict variants of DOCX, XLSX, and PPTX (as specified in Part 1) and the Transitional variants (as defined in Part 4 in conjunction with Part 1).   All versions since ISO/IEC 29500:2008 specify essentially the same format.  The editions published by ISO/IEC in 2011 and 2012 consisted primarily of clarifications and corrections. In particular, modifications to Part 4 (Transitional Migration Features) have been intended to ensure that the specification corresponds to the corpus of existing documents and that interoperability between existing applications was improved rather than disrupted.  See individual subtypes, particularly <fddLink id="fdd000397">DOCX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, <fddLink id="fdd000398">XLSX/OOXML_2012</fddLink>, and <fddLink id="fdd000399">PPTX/OOXML_2012</fddLink> for more detail for the three primary OOXML document types.  The chronology of editions specifying the OOXML family of formats is:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>ECMA-376, 1st edition (December 2006)</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500:2008</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, 2nd edition (December 2008) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500:2008]</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500:2011</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, 3rd edition (June 2011) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500:2011]</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500:2012</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, 4th edition (December 2012) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500:2012]</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, Part 1, 4th edition (December 2012) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-1:2012]; ECMA-376, Part 4, 4th edition (December 2012) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-4:2012]</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500-3:2015</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, Part 3, 5th edition (2015) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-3:2015]</li>
				<li>ISO/IEC 29500-1:2016; ISO/IEC 29500-4:2016</li>
				<li>ECMA-376, Part 1, 5th edition (October 2016) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-1:2016]; ECMA-376, Part 4, 5th edition (October 2016) [specification identical to ISO/IEC 29500-4:2016]</li>
			</ul>
			<p>A new edition of Part 3 of the specification, for Markup Compatibility and Extensibility, was published in early 2015.  The intent of the update was to clarify the text and to emphasize the applicability of MCE beyond OOXML to support interoperability.  The new edition does not introduce new features but does remove some flexibility that had not been exploited in practice and is deemed unnecessary. Most importantly, it makes the process for handling MCE on file import much clearer.</p>
			<p>Another chronology of relevance to digital archivists is the support for OOXML formats in different versions of the Office software. See <a href="https://interopevents.com/uploads/1477126591368-Office%20File%20Formats.pdf">Office File Formats Overview</a> from October 2016 for a Microsoft summary of the chronology.  Files created by the Microsoft Office applications have a /docProps/app.xml part that contains properties for the document as a whole, including &lt;Application&gt; and &lt;AppVersion&gt;.  Values for AppVersion are numeric, representing internal version numbers used by Microsoft during development.  The integral part of the AppVersion values in files created by versions of Microsoft Office are: 12 = Windows Office 2007 or Office for Mac 2008; 14 = Windows Office 2010 or Mac Office 2011; 15 = Windows Office 2013 and Office for Mac 2016; 16 = Windows Office 2016.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<b>Office 2007:</b> Read, Transitional only.  Write (as default), Transitional only.  Based on ECMA-376, Edition 1.  Also introduced read/write support for ODF 1.1.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Office 2010:</b> Read, Transitional and Strict.  Write (as default), Transitional only.  Based on ISO/IEC 29500:2008.  Also read/write support for ODF 1.1</li>
				<li>
					<b>Office for Mac 2011:</b> Read, Transitional only.  Write (as default), Transitional only.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Office 2013:</b> Read, Transitional and Strict.  Write, Transitional (as default), Strict (as option).  Based on ISO/IEC 29500:2011.  Introduced read/write support for ODF 1.2.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Office 2016:</b> Read, Transitional and Strict.  Write, Transitional (as default), Strict (as option).  Based on ISO/IEC 29500:2012.</li>
				<li>
					<b>Office for Mac 2016:</b> Read, Transitional and Strict.  Write, Transitional.  Based on ISO/IEC 29500:2012.  As of early 2017, there was not a desktop Office for Mac that can write Strict.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Note that although versions of Office dated 2016 were released for both Windows and the Mac OS, they do not declare the same AppVersion value.  The Windows and Mac versions of Office do not have identical codebases.  Tests of the most recent iPad version of Excel in December 2014 and February 2017 revealed &quot;Microsoft Macintosh Excel&quot; for the value for Application and &quot;15.0300&quot; as the value for Appversion. Thus, it appears that the iPad versions of Office apps are related to Office for Mac.  The compilers of this resource have not had the opportunity to check AppVersions in files created using Office 365 or Android apps.  <a href="../contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>
			<p>With Office 2016, Microsoft is strongly encouraging subscription-based access and frequent updates.  Format support may be adjusted in updates.  For example, Office for Mac 2016 (first released in mid-2015), introduced support for export to ODF in the June 2016 update.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-376.htm</link>
					<tag>ECMA-376: Office Open XML File Formats</tag>
					<comment>Provides access to all chronological published versions of all parts.  </comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>The latest version of each part of ISO/IEC 29500 is made available at no charge from ISO. The formal title is <i>Information technology -- Document description and processing
languages -- Office Open XML File Formats </i>
					</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC Publicly Available Standards</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c071691_ISO_IEC_29500-1_2016.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-1:2016, Fundamentals and Markup Language Reference</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c071691_ISO_IEC_29500-1_2016_Electronic_inserts.zip</link>
							<tag>Schemas in W3C XML Schema language and in RELAX NG for the Strict variant of PPTX, etc.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061796_ISO_IEC_29500-2_2012.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-2:2012, Open Packaging Conventions</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c065533_ISO_IEC_29500-3_2015.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-3:2015, Markup Compatibility and Extensibility</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c071692_ISO_IEC_29500-4_2016.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-4:2016, Transitional Migration Features</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c071692_ISO_IEC_29500-4_2016_Electronic_inserts.zip</link>
							<tag>Schemas in W3C XML Schema language and in RELAX NG for the Transitional variant of PPTX, etc.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Previous versions of ISO/IEC 29500, although not listed under <a href="http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/">ISO/IEC Publicly Available Standards/</a> can be found at their earlier URLs:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061750_ISO_IEC_29500-1_2012.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-1:2012, Fundamentals and Markup Language Reference</tag>
							<comment>Superseded but still accessible as of February 2017</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061750_ISO_IEC_29500-1_2012_Electronic_inserts.zip</link>
							<tag>Schemas in W3C XML Schema language and in RELAX NG for the Strict variant of DOCX.</tag>
							<comment>Superseded but still accessible as of February 2017.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061797_ISO_IEC_29500-3_2012.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-3:2012, Markup Compatibility and Extensibility</tag>
							<comment>Superseded but still accessible as of February 2017</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061798_ISO_IEC_29500-4_2012.zip</link>
							<tag>ISO/IEC 29500-4:2012, Transitional Migration Features</tag>
							<comment>Superseded but still accessible as of February 2017</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c061798_ISO_IEC_29500-4_2012_Electronic_inserts.zip</link>
							<tag>Schemas in W3C XML Schema language and in RELAX NG for the Transitional variant of DOCX.</tag>
							<comment>Superseded, but still accessible as of February 2017.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_Open_XML</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for Office Open XML</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/memento/TC45-M.htm</link>
					<tag>TC45 - Office Open XML Formats
- Activities</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://www.ecma-international.org/news/TC45_current_work/OpenXML%20White%20Paper.pdf</link>
					<tag>Office Open XML Overview</tag>
					<comment>Published by ECMA TC45 in 2006 when OOXML was submitted to ECMA for ballot by members.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_software_that_supports_Office_Open_XML</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia list of software supporting Office Open XML</tag>
					<comment>Not necessarily kept up-to-date.  In September 2014, several links had been detected by Wikipedia&apos;s automated link-checking tool as &quot;dead links.&quot;</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Office_mobile_apps</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry on Microsoft Office mobile apps</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Microsoft provides many pages related to OOXML in blogs, tutorials, and reference materials.  Much of this documentation is aimed at programmers writing applications that manipulate OOXML markup directly, perhaps using the Open XML SDK.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/office/bb448854.aspx</link>
							<tag>Welcome to the Open XML SDK 2.5 for Office</tag>
							<comment>In June 2014, the Open XML SDK was made available as open source.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://openxmldeveloper.org/</link>
							<tag>OpenXMLDeveloper.org</tag>
							<comment>A community site hosted by Microsoft, with discussion forums, tutorial materials, and news related to the OpenXML Software Development Kit (SDK).</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://openxmldeveloper.org/discussions/formats/default.aspx</link>
							<tag>Formats:  Discussions about working with different Open XML Formats</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://blogs.office.com/2012/08/13/new-file-format-options-in-the-new-office/</link>
							<tag>New file format options in the new Office [Office 2013]</tag>
							<comment>Announces support for writing files in DOCX Strict and ODF 1.2 formats.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa338205%28v=office.12%29.aspx</link>
							<tag>Introducing the Office (2007) Open XML File Formats</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://support.office.com/en-us/article/Open-XML-Formats-and-file-name-extensions-5200d93c-3449-4380-8e11-31ef14555b18</link>
							<tag>Open XML Formats and file name extensions</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/gg548604.aspx</link>
							<tag>Word, Excel, and PowerPoint Standards Support</tag>
							<comment>Includes full technical specifications for extensions Microsoft has introduced using the techniques specified in ISO/IEC 29500, Part 3, Markup Compatibility and Extensibility.  See descriptions for individual subtypes for more detail.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee908652.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OI29500]: Office Implementation Information for ISO/IEC 29500 Standards Support</tag>
							<comment>Documents variations from ISO/IEC 29500:2012 in Office 2010, Office 2013 and Office 2016</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee908654.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OE376]: Office Implementation Information for ECMA-376 Standards Support</tag>
							<comment>Documents variations from ECMA-376, Edition 1 in Office 2007 and Office 2010.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://download.microsoft.com/download/0/F/1/0F1B141A-9C69-4BEA-97EE-BDC50C7DA114/day2/20160420_Open_session8.pdf</link>
							<tag>Office File Formats Overview (April 2016)</tag>
							<comment>Presentation from DevDays Asia 2016 in Taipei, April 2016.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c045245_ISO_IEC_TR_29166_2011.zip</link>
					<tag>ISO/IEC TR 29166:2011 Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- Guidelines for translation between ISO/IEC 26300 and ISO/IEC 29500 document formats</tag>
					<comment>Highlights challenges to conversion between OOXML and ODF formats.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://officeopenxml.com/whatIsOOXML.php</link>
					<tag>What is OOXML?</tag>
					<comment>Includes extensive explanatory documentation on the three primary OOXML content categories and DrawingML. By Daniel Dick, principal attorney editor at Thomson Reuters.  The site is in no way affiliated with his employer.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://wiki.documentfoundation.org/Feature_Comparison:_LibreOffice_-_Microsoft_Office</link>
					<tag>Feature Comparison: LibreOffice - Microsoft Office</tag>
					<comment>As of late 2014, this page compares features of LibreOffice 4.3.4 and Microsoft Office 2013, highlighting differences.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://web.archive.org/web/20150904034314/http://blogs.fsfe.org/the_unconventional/2014/09/12/ooxml/</link>
					<tag>Making the best of MS Office files.  September 2014 blog post by &apos;the unconventional.&apos;</tag>
					<comment>Includes useful guidance for creating interoperable documents.  However, the author does not realize that users can choose to use ODF natively in Microsoft Word.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Although not fully defined within ISO/IEC 29500, variants of the XLSX, DOCX, and PPTX formats can be macro-enabled, to support automated dynamic functionality not supported by the markup defined in the standard.  Microsoft Office supports the use of VBA (Visual Basic for Applications) as a macro language and has documented markup extensions used to wrap macros in macro-enabled document packages.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd925808.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OFFMACRO]: Office Macro-Enabled File Format</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd947889.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OFFMACRO2]: Office Macro-Enabled File Format Version 2</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc313094.aspx</link>
							<tag>[MS-OVBA]: Office VBA File Format Structure</tag>
							<comment>Specifies the Office VBA File Format Structure, a persistence format for embedding macros within a host document</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/PRONOM/fmt/189</link>
					<tag>PRONOM entry for fmt/189</tag>
					<comment>Information in PRONOM from UK National Archives about Microsoft Office Open XML.  PUID: fmt/189.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Resources related to treatment of macros when importing macro-enabled files into other applications or saving macros and documents separately.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://help.libreoffice.org/Common/Using_Microsoft_Office_and</link>
							<tag>Using Microsoft Office and LibreOffice</tag>
							<comment>Includes discussion of treatment of macros in macro-enabled OOXML files read in to LibreOffice.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://wiki.openoffice.org/wiki/Documentation/OOo3_User_Guides/Calc_Guide/Load_Save_options</link>
							<tag>Apache Open Office Help: Choosing options for loading and saving documents</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387068,00.asp</link>
							<tag>Save and Restore Your Macros</tag>
							<comment>From 10 Essential Microsoft Word 2010 Tips for Advanced Users, PC Magazine, June 16, 2011. The same Alt-F11 technique works for desktop versions of other Microsoft Office applications. </comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa214923.aspx</link>
					<tag>Welcome to the Microsoft Office Word 2003 XML Software Development Kit (SDK) [Word 2003 XML Reference]</tag>
					<comment>Documentation for working with the flat XML format used in Office 2003, a precursor to OOXML.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Microsoft commitments to interoperability include a set of interoperability principles, a promise of open specifications for certain high-volume products, and a program of documentation and &quot;Interop&quot; events.</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/openspecifications/dn646764</link>
							<tag>Microsoft Interoperability Program and Principles</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/openspecifications/dn646765</link>
							<tag>Microsoft Open Specification Promise</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://interopevents.com/uploads/1477127699476-Introducing%20Microsoft&apos;s%20Commitment%20to%20Interoperabilty.pdf</link>
							<tag>Introducing Microsoft&apos;s Commitment to Interoperability (presentation from late 2016)</tag>
							<comment>Explains to an audience of potential developers at DevDays Asia meeting how Microsoft provides open specifications of its high-volume products and supports developers.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>Links that provide background for Microsoft commitments to interoperability:</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://news.microsoft.com/2009/12/16/microsoft-statement-on-european-commission-decision/</link>
							<tag>Microsoft Statement on European Commission Decision -- December 16, 2009</tag>
							<comment>Microsoft made commitments to open documentation and other support for interoperability in this statement.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkId=179741</link>
							<tag>Persistent link to the December 16, 2009 Microsoft Statement on European Commission Decision</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://news.microsoft.com/download/archived/presskits/eu-msft/docs/MicrosoftInteroperabilityUndertaking16Dec2009.doc</link>
							<tag>Microsoft Interoperability Undertaking, Dec 16, 2009</tag>
							<comment>Public undertaking to address competition concerns from the European Commission.</comment>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
