<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fdd:FDD id="fdd000554" titleName="Outline Processor Markup Language (OPML) 2.0" shortName="OPML_2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">
	<fdd:properties>
		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
			<fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
				<fdd:gdfrGenre>text</fdd:gdfrGenre>
				<fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
					<fdd:gdfrSubgenre>dataset</fdd:gdfrSubgenre>
				</fdd:gdfrSubgenres>
			</fdd:gdfrGenreAndSubgenres>
		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>
		<fdd:formatCategories>
			<fdd:category>file-format</fdd:category>
			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>
		</fdd:formatCategories>
		<fdd:gdfrConstraint>structured</fdd:gdfrConstraint>
		<fdd:gdfrBasis>symbolic</fdd:gdfrBasis>
		<fdd:updates>
			<fdd:date>2022-12-07</fdd:date>
		</fdd:updates>
		<fdd:draftStatus>Full</fdd:draftStatus>
	</fdd:properties>
	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>
		<fdd:fullName>Outline Processor Markup Language (OPML) 2.0</fdd:fullName>
		<fdd:description>
			<p>Outline Processor Markup Language (OPML) is an XML-based format, specifically <fddLink id="fdd000263">XML 1.0</fddLink>, for <i>outlines</i> where each node contains a set of named attributes with string values. An <a href="http://opml.org/spec2.opml">outline</a>, in this context, is &quot;a tree, where each node contains a set of named attributes with string values.&quot; The OPML specification, which is open, is developed and maintained by Dave Winer at <a href="http://opml.org/">opml.org</a>. The current version, covered in this document, is <a href="http://opml.org/spec2.opml">version 2.0</a>. See <a href="#notes">History</a> for information about previous versions.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Structure of OPML</b>
			</p>
			<p>OPML is a hierarchical, ordered list of elements:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>opml: root element that must contain the <i>version</i> attribute and one head and one body element. For OPML 2.0, the value is <i>opml version=&quot;2.0&quot;</i>. See <a href="#sign">File Signifiers</a> section for values for other OPML versions.</li>
				<li>head: contains zero or more optional elements: title (title of document); dateCreated (date-time when the document was created); dateModified (date-time when the document was last modified); ownerName (string, the owner of the document); ownerEmail (string, email address of the owner of the document); ownerId (http address of a web page that contains information that allows a human reader to communicate with the author of the document via email or other means. It also may be used to identify the author. No two authors have the same ownerId); docs (http address of documentation for the format used in the OPML file); expansionState (comma-separated list of line numbers that are expanded); 
vertScrollState (number, stating which line of the outline is displayed on the top line of the window): windowTop (number, the pixel location of the top edge of the window); windowLeft (number, the pixel location of the left edge of the window); windowBottom (number, the pixel location of the bottom edge of the window); windowRight (number, the pixel location of the right edge of the window)</li>
				<li>body: contains one or more outline elements.</li>
				<li>outline: element containing at least one required attribute, <i>text</i>, and zero or more additional attributes and zero or more sub-elements. No attribute may be repeated within the same outline element. Other optional attributes include <i>type</i>, <i>isComment</i>, <i>isBreakpoint</i>, <i>created</i>, and <i>category</i>.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Subscription lists, especially <a href="https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html">RSS</a> or Really Simple Syndication feeds, are identified as sub-element of the body element with a node of type <i>rss</i> or an outline element that contains nodes of type <i>rss</i>.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Uses of OPML</b>
			</p>
			<p>According to the <a href="http://opml.org/spec2.opml">specification</a>, the goals of OPML are "to provide a way to exchange information between outliners and Internet services that can be browsed or controlled through an outliner"; serve as a "file format for an outliner application, which is why OPML files may contain information about the size, position and expansion state of the window the outline is displayed in"; and, as a "format for exchanging subscription lists between feed readers and aggregators" especially RSS feeds. <a href="http://opml.org/spec2.opml">opml.org</a> includes sample files for various uses.</p>
			<p>
				<b>Issues with OPML</b>
			</p>
			<p>
				<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OPML#Criticism">Wikidata</a> lists some criticisms of OPML including issues with the requirement that syntax in date-time elements must conform to the outdated <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc822">RFC 822</a> specification which has been long superseded by <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc5322">RFC 5322</a>, issues with the "expansionState" attribute, and general potential interoperability issues because "OPML documents relies almost entirely on the undocumented conventions of content producers." Issues with the OPML specification are included on the <a href="https://github.com/scripting/opml.org/issues">opml.org GitHub repo</a>.</p>
		</fdd:description>
		<fdd:shortDescription>OPML is an XML format used to provide a way to exchange information between outliners and Internet services. It is widely used for RSS feeds and managing subscription lists.</fdd:shortDescription>
		<fdd:productionPhase>Middle state as an exchange platform. The purpose of this format is to provide a way to exchange information between outliners and Internet services that can be browsed or controlled through an outliner, especially for RSS feeds.</fdd:productionPhase>
		<fdd:relationships>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Defined via</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo>
					<fdd:id>fdd000075</fdd:id>
					<fdd:shortName>XML</fdd:shortName>
					<fdd:titleName>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</fdd:titleName>
				</fdd:relatedTo>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo/>
				<fdd:comment>OPML 1.0. <a href="http://2005.opml.org/spec1.html">Specification</a> published September 15, 2000. Not described separately at this time. See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> for more information.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
			<fdd:relationship>
				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>
				<fdd:relatedTo/>
				<fdd:comment>OPML 1.1. <a href="http://opml.org/history/aboutOpml11.opml">Information about version updates</a> published January 24, 2005. Not described separately at this time. See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> for more information.</fdd:comment>
			</fdd:relationship>
		</fdd:relationships>
	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>
	<fdd:localUse>
		<fdd:experience>None.</fdd:experience>
		<fdd:preference>See the Recommended Formats Statement for the Library of Congress format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/text.html">textual works</a>. </fdd:preference>
	</fdd:localUse>
	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
		<fdd:disclosure>Fully documented and open specification. Developed and maintained by Dave Winer at <a href="http://opml.org/">opml.org</a>. The specification declares &quot;it&apos;s an open format, meaning that other outliner and service developers are welcome to use the format to be compatible with Radio UserLand, the OPML Editor, or for any other purpose.&quot;</fdd:disclosure>
		<fdd:documentation>
			<a href="http://opml.org/spec2.opml">OPML 2.0</a> specification which is frequently updated. The <a href="https://github.com/scripting/opml.org">opml.org GitHub repository</a> backs up the opml.org website. In addition to the specification, there is an <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20071008052335/http://www.dlese.org/Metadata/opml/2.0/opml.xsd">XML schema</a> for validating OPML 2.0 developed by the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20070910025930/http://www.dlese.org/Metadata/opml/2.0/index.htm">Digital Library for Earth System Eduction (DLESE) Program Office</a> (link via Internet Archive). There is also a <a href="http://static.userland.com/gems/radiodiscuss/opmlDtd.txt">DTD</a> for OPML version 1.</fdd:documentation>
		<fdd:adoption>According to Renée Christian in <a href="https://history-computer.com/what-are-opml-files-and-how-do-you-open-edit-and-use-them/">What are OPML Files, and How Do You Open, Edit, and Use Them?</a> from August 2022, &quot;the hierarchical structure of OPML facilitates the accurate exchange between software applications of large volumes of data, regardless of the operating system used. This makes them a high-utility file type that is used in a wide range of applications... Most programs that handle RSS feed data are able to import or export OPML files.&quot; OPML implementers include the aggregator <a href="https://developer.feedly.com/v3/opml/">Feedly</a>, <a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/how-subscribe-news-feeds-and-blogs">Mozilla Thunderbird</a>, <a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/share-or-export-rss-feeds-5b514f38-8671-447c-8c25-7f02cc0833e0">Microsoft Outlook</a> starting with Outlook 2007, even <a href="https://manuals.playstation.net/document/en/psp/current/network/rss/opml.html">Sony PlayStation</a> legacy system 1000, 2000, 3000 and N1000 models to "to collectively register multiple channels that are stored in the file"; <a href="https://antennapod.org/documentation/general/backup">AntennaPod</a> open source podcast player; <a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/live-bookmarks-migration">Firefox</a> browser bookmarks; and many more. <a href="http://opml.org/compatibleApps.opml">opml.org</a> maintains a list of OPML compatible applications. </fdd:adoption>
		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>No known license or patent concerns for generation and use of the format. </fdd:licensingAndPatents>
		<fdd:transparency>XML is human-readable and designed for straightforward automatic parsing. For the contents to be understood, a well-documented DTD, XML Schema, or other specification is needed. Human-comprehensible element tags are advantageous for transparency.</fdd:transparency>
		<fdd:selfDocumentation>Well-defined XML structure include declaration of the OPML version (in the version attribute) as well as information about the title, creation dates and more in the head, body and outline elements. </fdd:selfDocumentation>
		<fdd:externalDependencies>None.</fdd:externalDependencies>
		<fdd:techProtection>None.</fdd:techProtection>
	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>
	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
		<fdd:textQF>
			<fdd:normalText>See <fddLink id="fdd000075">XML</fddLink>.</fdd:normalText>
			<fdd:structure>See <fddLink id="fdd000075">XML</fddLink>.</fdd:structure>
			<fdd:layout>See <fddLink id="fdd000075">XML</fddLink>.</fdd:layout>
			<fdd:mathDiag>See <fddLink id="fdd000075">XML</fddLink>.</fdd:mathDiag>
			<fdd:beyondText>See <fddLink id="fdd000075">XML</fddLink>.</fdd:beyondText>
		</fdd:textQF>
	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>
	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
		<fdd:signifiersGroup>
			<fdd:filenameExtension>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>opml</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://file.org/extension/opml">https://file.org/extension/opml </a>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:filenameExtension>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:sigValue>text/x-opml</fdd:sigValue>
				</fdd:sigValues>
				<fdd:note>See <a href="https://mimeapplication.net/text-x-opml">https://mimeapplication.net/text-x-opml</a>. Not registered at IANA.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:internetMediaType>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000075">XML</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:internetMediaType>
			<fdd:magicNumbers>
				<fdd:sigValueNA>See related format.</fdd:sigValueNA>
				<fdd:note>See <fddLink id="fdd000075">XML</fddLink>.</fdd:note>
			</fdd:magicNumbers>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Indicator for profile, level, version, etc.</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>2.0</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>For OPML 2.0, the required <i>version</i> attribute in the top level <i>opml</i> element is <i>opml version=&quot;2.0&quot;</i>. For OPML versions 1.0 and 1.1, the attribute values are 1.0 and 1.1 respectively. See <a href="http://opml.org/spec2.opml">OPML specification</a>.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>
					<fdd:note>PRONOM has no corresponding entry as of December 2022.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
			<fdd:other>
				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>
				<fdd:values>
					<fdd:sigValues>
						<fdd:sigValue>Q836370</fdd:sigValue>
					</fdd:sigValues>
					<fdd:note>See <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q836370">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q836370</a>. Note that Wikidata does not specify versions.</fdd:note>
				</fdd:values>
			</fdd:other>
		</fdd:signifiersGroup>
	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>
	<fdd:notes>
		<fdd:general>The <a href="https://github.com/VIPnytt/OPMLParser">difference</a> between version 2.0 and 1.0 is the &quot;text&quot; attribute, which is optional in version 1.0. The difference between version 1.0 and version 1.1 is less clear and in fact, in a post on opml.gov from January 24, 2005 titled <a href="http://opml.org/history/aboutOpml11.opml">About OPML 1.1</a>, specification author Dave Winer explains that the addition of an optional <i>cloud</i> element to the OPML head element was under consideration because <i>cloud</i> was added to RSS in <a href="http://backend.userland.com/rss092#ltcloudgtSubelementOfLtchannelgt">version 0.92</a>. He explains that "this allows a server to implement update-notification, a lightweight publish-subscribe mechanism that works over various Internet protocols." However, due to changes in priorities and personal reasons, the <i>cloud</i> element was never actually added to OPML. He states "if you see an OPML 1.1 file, you should treat it like an OPML 1.0 file. That's it. Enjoy!"</fdd:general>
		<fdd:history>
			<p>According to Renée Christian in <a href="https://history-computer.com/what-are-opml-files-and-how-do-you-open-edit-and-use-them/">What are OPML Files, and How Do You Open, Edit, and Use Them?</a>,  &quot;OPML was developed by a US-based software company called UserLand in 2000. UserLand used OPML as a native file format for <a href="http://radio.userland.com/">Radio UserLand</a>, an RSS aggregator and blogging tool." Dave Winer, the designer of the OPML format , founded UserLand in 1988. The current version of OPML is 2.0. The first version, <a href="http://2005.opml.org/spec1.html">version 1.0</a>, was published in 2000. <a href="http://opml.org/history/aboutOpml11.opml">Version 1.1</a> was never formally finalized or published although a <a href="http://radio-weblogs.com/0001015/userland/opml11/states.opml">version 1.1 sample file</a> is available and displays the version number in the header metadata.</p>
		</fdd:history>
	</fdd:notes>
	<fdd:formatSpecifications>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://opml.org/spec2.opml</link>
					<tag>OPML 2.0 official specification from opml.org. Frequently updated.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://2005.opml.org/spec1.html</link>
					<tag>Legacy document for OPML 1.0 Specification. Superseded by OPML 2.0. Dated 9/15/2000.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:formatSpecifications>
	<fdd:usefulReferences>
		<fdd:urls>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlGroup>
					<fdd:intro>opml.org Resources</fdd:intro>
					<fdd:urlList>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://opml.org/</link>
							<tag>Homepage of opml.org</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://opml.org/history/aboutOpml11.opml</link>
							<tag>History of development of OPML version 1.1</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>http://opml.org/compatibleApps.opml</link>
							<tag>OPML-compatible apps</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
						<fdd:urlReference>
							<link>https://github.com/scripting/opml.org</link>
							<tag>opml.org Github repo: A repository to back up the opml.org website.</tag>
						</fdd:urlReference>
					</fdd:urlList>
				</fdd:urlGroup>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</link>
					<tag>W3C RSS feed validation service</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OPML</link>
					<tag>Wikipedia entry for OPML</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc822</link>
					<tag>IETF RFC 822: Standard For The Format Of ARPA Internet Text Messages. 8/13/1982</tag>
					<comment>Now obsolete</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc5322</link>
					<tag>IETF RFC 5322: Internet Message Format. 2008.</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20071008052335/http://www.dlese.org/Metadata/opml/2.0/opml.xsd</link>
					<tag>XML schema for validating OPML 2.0 developed by the Digital Library for Earth System Eduction (DLESE) Program Office</tag>
					<comment>From Internet Archive</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://web.archive.org/web/20070910025930/http://www.dlese.org/Metadata/opml/2.0/index.htm</link>
					<tag>Digital Library for Earth System Eduction (DLESE) Program Office homepage</tag>
					<comment>From Internet Archive</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://static.userland.com/gems/radiodiscuss/opmlDtd.txt</link>
					<tag>DTD for OPML version 1. From Digital Library for Earth System Eduction (DLESE) Program Office</tag>
					<comment>From Internet Archive</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://history-computer.com/what-are-opml-files-and-how-do-you-open-edit-and-use-them/</link>
					<tag>What are OPML Files, and How Do You Open, Edit, and Use Them? by Renée Christian in History-Computercom. Last updated 12/8/2022</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://developer.feedly.com/v3/opml/</link>
					<tag>Feedly OPML API</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/how-subscribe-news-feeds-and-blogs</link>
					<tag>Mozilla Support: How to Subscribe to News Feeds and Blogs</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/live-bookmarks-migration</link>
					<tag>Mozilla Support: What happened to my Live Bookmarks?</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/share-or-export-rss-feeds-5b514f38-8671-447c-8c25-7f02cc0833e0</link>
					<tag>Microsoft: Share or export RSS Feeds</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://manuals.playstation.net/document/en/psp/current/network/rss/opml.html</link>
					<tag>PlayStation: Importing OPML files</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://antennapod.org/documentation/general/backup</link>
					<tag>AntennaPod: Backing up your episodes</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://file.org/extension/opml</link>
					<tag>File.org: OPML File</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://mimeapplication.net/text-x-opml</link>
					<tag>MIME types database: Mime Text/x-opml</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://github.com/VIPnytt/OPMLParser</link>
					<tag>OPML parser for PHP</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://backend.userland.com/rss092</link>
					<tag>Legacy version of RSS specification including cloud subelement</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://radio.userland.com/</link>
					<tag>Radio UserLand homepage</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>http://radio-weblogs.com/0001015/userland/opml11/states.opml</link>
					<tag>	OPML version 1.1 sample file
</tag>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
			<fdd:url>
				<fdd:urlReference>
					<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q836370</link>
					<tag>Wikidata entry for Q836370</tag>
					<comment>Information in Wikidata about OPML (no version information). Wikidata Title ID: Q836370.</comment>
				</fdd:urlReference>
			</fdd:url>
		</fdd:urls>
	</fdd:usefulReferences>
</fdd:FDD>
