<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><fdd:FDD id="fdd000578" titleName="VP8 Video Codec" shortName="VP8" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:fdd="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1 http://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/schemas/fdd/v1/fdd-v1-2.xsd">	<fdd:properties>		<fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>			<fdd:gdfrGenre>moving-image</fdd:gdfrGenre>		</fdd:gdfrGenreSelection>		<fdd:formatCategories>			<fdd:category>encoding</fdd:category>		</fdd:formatCategories>		<fdd:updates>			<fdd:date>2024-04-28</fdd:date>		</fdd:updates>		<fdd:draftStatus>Preliminary</fdd:draftStatus>	</fdd:properties>	<fdd:identificationAndDescription>		<fdd:fullName>VP8 Video Codec</fdd:fullName>		<fdd:keywords>			<fdd:keyword>compression codec</fdd:keyword>			<fdd:keyword>video codec</fdd:keyword>		</fdd:keywords>		<fdd:description>			<p>VP8 is a video data compression codec format, originally released as a proprietary format by<a href="https://www.on2.com/">On2 Technologies</a> in 2008, but after acquiring On2 in 2010 <a href="https://www.google.com/">Google</a> announced the VP8 codecsoftware open source under the WebM Open Web Media Project. According to <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/">WebM Project</a>,<a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc6386/">VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide (RFC 6386)</a> was published by the <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/">Internet EngineeringTask Force (IETF)</a> in November 2011. The RFC 6386 document describes the VP8 format,stating &quot;this document is not an Internet Standard Track specification; it is published forinformational purposes.&quot; IETF also has published an Internet Standards Track document, <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc7741">RTPPayload Format for VP8 Video</a>, describing the RTP payload specification used in VP8 codec,RFC 6386.</p>			<p>				<b>VP8 Compressed Video Data Format:</b>			</p>			<p>Per <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/pdfrfc/rfc6386.txt.pdf">RFC 6386 document</a>, &quot;Like many modern video compression schemes, VP8 is based ondecomposition of frames into square subblocks of pixels, prediction of such subblocks usingpreviously constructed blocks, and adjustment of such predictions (as well as synthesis ofunpredicted blocks) using a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discrete_cosine_transform">discrete cosine transform (DCT)</a>.&quot; One special case uses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamard_transform">Walsh-Hadamard transform (WHT)</a> instead of DCT. “Unlike some similar schemes, VP8 specifies exactvalues for reconstructed pixels. This greatly facilitates the verification of the correctness of adecoder implementation and also avoids difficult-to-predict visual incongruities between suchimplementations. VP8’s use of basic concepts and sophisticated usage of contextual probabilitiesresults in a significant reduction in data rate at a given quality.”</p>			<p>Google developers&#39; paper, <a href="https://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//pubs/archive/37073.pdf">Technical Overview of VP8, an Open Source Video Codec for theWeb</a>, 2011, provides a review of the VP8 format and its technical features, stating “Compared toother video coding formats, VP8 has many distinctive technical features that help it to achievehigh compression efficiency and low computational complexity for decoding at the same time.</p>			<p>				<b>VP8 Design Assumptions for an Internet/Web-Based Video Application:</b>			</p>			<ul>				<li>Low Bandwidth Requirement – operate in quality range from “watchable video” to“visually lossless”.</li>				<li>Web Video Format – 420 color sampling, 8-bit per channel color depth, progressive scan,and maximum image dimensions 16383 x 16383 pixels. (VP8 works exclusively with an<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YUV">YUV 4:2:0 image format</a>).</li>				<li>Support Wide Range of Client Hardware, connected to the Web, from low power mobile devices to advanced desktop computers.</li>			</ul>			<p>				<b>VP8 Technical Features:</b>			</p>			<ul>				<li>Hybrid Transform, adaptive <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantization">quantization</a>.</li>				<li>Flexible Reference Frames (Intra Prediction).</li>				<li>Efficient Intra/Inter Prediction.</li>				<li>High Performance Sub-Pixel Interpolation.</li>				<li>Adaptive In-Loop Deblocking Filtering.</li>				<li>Frame Level <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_coding">Adaptive Entropy Coding</a>.</li>				<li>Parallel Processing in Decoders.</li>			</ul>			<p>				<b>Uses of VP8:</b>			</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.fileformat.com/">FileFormat.com's</a>, <a href="https://docs.fileformat.com/video/vp8/">What is a VP8 File?</a>, states “VP8 is announced by Google as one of the bestvideo formats having the best picture quality data rate and encoding speed. The best advantage ofVP8 is that it is a royalty-free substitute for <fddLink id="fdd000081">H.264</fddLink>. It is a specific format for encoding anddecoding high-quality video as a file or a bitstream.”</p>			<p>Per the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">Wikipedia VP8 page</a>, “VP8 is mainly used in connection with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebRTC">WebRTC</a> and as a formatfor short looped animations, as a replacement for the <fddLink id="fdd000133">Graphics Interchange Format (GIF)</fddLink>.”</p>		</fdd:description>		<fdd:shortDescription>VP8 is an open-source, royalty free video data compression codec format for encoding and decoding high-definition video for the web.</fdd:shortDescription>		<fdd:productionPhase>Generally, a final-state (end-user video delivery) format.</fdd:productionPhase>		<fdd:relationships>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:id>fdd000518</fdd:id>					<fdd:shortName>WebM</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>WebM</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>					<br/>					<a href="https://www.webmproject.org/about/faq/">WebMProject.org</a>, “WebM files consist of video streams compressed with the VP8 orVP9 video codec.”<br/>					<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebM">WebM Wikipedia page</a>, WebM - Container for VP8/VP9/AV1 (video) Vorbis/Opus(audio).</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:id>fdd000577</fdd:id>					<fdd:shortName>WebP</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>WebP</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>					<br/>					<a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/webp">WebP Project Page</a>, “WebP file consists of VP8 or VP8L image data.”</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:shortName>AV1</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>AOMedia1</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>					<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">P8 Wikipedia page</a>, “The emerging royalty-free internet video format AV1 from theAlliance for Open Media (AOMedia) are based on VP8.” Not described separately on thiswebsite at this time.<br/>				See links for information: AV1 Wikipedia (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AV1">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AV1</a>),				AOMedia.org (<a href="https://aomedia.org/">https://aomedia.org/</a>),				GitHub AOMedia Codec (<a href="https://aomediacodec.github.io/av1-spec/av1-spec.pdf">https://aomediacodec.github.io/av1-spec/av1-spec.pdf</a>).</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:id>fdd000481</fdd:id>					<fdd:shortName>HMTL_5</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 5</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>					<br/>As stated on <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/">Developer.Mozilla.org's</a> Document, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Media/Formats/Video_codecs#vp8">Web Video Codec Guide</a>, "There is good browser support for VP8 in HTML content, especially within WebM files...Web browsers are required to support VP8 for WebRTC, but not all browsers that do so also support it in HTML audio and video elements."</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Used by</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:id>fdd000308</fdd:id>					<fdd:shortName>EPUB_3_0</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>EPUB, Electronic Publication, Version 3.0 (2011).  ISO/IEC TS 30135:2014</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has earlier version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:shortName>VP7</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>VP7 Video Codec</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>					<br/>Per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">VP8 Wikipedia page</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On2_Technologies#TrueMotion_VP7">VP7</a> is the predecessor to VP8. Not described separately on thiswebsite at this time. See <a href="#notes">Notes</a> for more information on previous versions.</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>			<fdd:relationship>				<fdd:typeOfRelationship>Has later version</fdd:typeOfRelationship>				<fdd:relatedTo>					<fdd:id>fdd000579</fdd:id>					<fdd:shortName>VP9</fdd:shortName>					<fdd:titleName>VP9 Video Codec</fdd:titleName>				</fdd:relatedTo>				<fdd:comment>Per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">VP8 Wikipedia page</a>, VP8’s direct successor is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP9">VP9</a>.</fdd:comment>			</fdd:relationship>		</fdd:relationships>	</fdd:identificationAndDescription>	<fdd:localUse>		<fdd:experience>The Library of Congress has VP8 in containers, including WebM, in it&apos;s collections. </fdd:experience>		<fdd:preference>See the Library of Congress Recommended Formats Statement for format preferences for <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/resources/rfs/moving.html">moving image works</a>.</fdd:preference>	</fdd:localUse>	<fdd:sustainabilityFactors>		<fdd:disclosure>			<p>Open source, royalty free format. Per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">VP8 Wikipedia page</a>, “VP8 was released as an open and royalty-free format in May 2010 after Google acquired On2 Technologies.”</p>			<p>Per <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/about/faq/">WebMProject.org</a>, “VP8 and VP9 are highly-efficient video compressiontechnologies (video &quot;codecs&quot;) developed by the WebM Project. Anyone may use thesecodecs for no charge.”</p>		</fdd:disclosure>		<fdd:documentation>			<p>				<a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc6386/">VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide (RFC 6386)</a>			</p>			<p>According to <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/">WebM Project</a>, VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide (RFC 6386) waspublished by the <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/">Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</a> in November 2011. The RFC6386 document describes the VP8 format, stating &quot;this document is not an InternetStandard Track specification; it is published for informational purposes.&quot;</p>			<p>				<a href="https://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//pubs/archive/37073.pdf">Technical Overview of VP8, an Open Source Video Codec for the Web</a>			</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.webmproject.org/code/">VP8 Source and Contribute Code</a> downloads at <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/">WebMProject.org</a>.</p>		</fdd:documentation>		<fdd:adoption>			<p>				<a href="https://bloggeek.me/">BlogGeek.me</a>, the <a href="https://bloggeek.me/webrtcglossary/vp8/">WebRTC Glossary VP8</a>, states “VP8 is available in all browsers thatsupport WebRTC. It is one of the mandatory to implement video codecs in WebRTC.”</p>			<p>According to the <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/about/faq/">WebMProject.org</a>, “VP8 and VP9 deliver high-quality video whileefficiently adapting to varying processing and bandwidth conditions across a broad rangeof devices. High-efficiency bandwidth usage and reduced storage requirements can helppublishers recognize immediate cost savings. Also, the relative simplicity of VP8/VP9makes it easy to integrate into existing environments, and requires comparatively littlemanual tuning in the encoder to produce high-quality results.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">VP8 Wikipedia page</a> states, “<a href="https://www.opera.com/">Opera</a>, <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/new/">Firefox</a>, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2010/06/03/webm-chrome/">Chrome</a>, and <a href="https://www.chromium.org/chromium-projects/">Chromium</a> support playingVP8 video in the <fddLink id="fdd000481">HTML5</fddLink> video tag...VP8 can multiplexed into the <fddLink id="fdd000342">Matroska</fddLink>-basedcontainer format <fddLink id="fdd000518">WebM</fddLink> along with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vorbis">Vorbis</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opus_(audio_format)">Opus</a> audio. The image format WebP(fdd000577) is based on VP8’s intra-frame coding.”</p>			<p>The <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/code/">Reference Implementation</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libvpx">libvpx</a>, the free software video codec from Google,provides software implementation for the VP8 and VP9 codec formats.</p>			<p>				<a href="http://wiki.webmproject.org/vp8-implementations">Wiki.WebMProject.org, VP8 Implementations</a>, provides list of encoders and decoders,software and hardware.</p>			<p>Up-to-date browser support for VP8 (WebP image format, based on VP8 video format)on <a href="https://caniuse.com/?search=vp8">CanIUse.com</a>.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.5kplayer.com/">5KPlayer</a> is a downloadable VP8/VP9 video player for decoding and playback ofMKV/WebM files on Mac and Windows.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:adoption>		<fdd:licensingAndPatents>			<p>				<a href="https://www.webmproject.org/cross-license/">VP8 Patent Cross-License</a>, “The VP8 Cross-License Agreement helps create a royalty-free ecosystem for VP8 and allows the web community to further support the WebMProject.”</p>			<p>According to Sean Cassidy's An Analysis of VP8, a New Video Codec for the Web, available for download from <a href="https://scholarworks.rit.edu/theses/3184/">RIT Scholar Works</a>,2011, VP8 has a “perpetual patent grant – something which gives the implementor a no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable patent license to use or sell VP8, and the officialreference implementation is open source.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:licensingAndPatents>		<fdd:transparency>			<p>Depends upon algorithms and tools to read. Per <a href="https://editor.tips/">Editor.tips</a>, <a href="https://editor.tips/file/vp8">VP8 File Editor</a>, “To edit afile with the VP8 extension, we usually need dedicated software.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://flixier.com/tools/webm-editor">Flixier</a> is an online WebM Editor.</p>			<p>				<a href="http://www.inmatrix.com/files/zoomplayer_download.shtml">Zoom Player Max</a> media player and <a href="http://www.codecian.com/">CodecVisa</a> analyzer are downloadable software thatsupport VP8 video codec.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:transparency>		<fdd:selfDocumentation>			<p>Supports the inclusion of metadata, but little to no information found describing VP8metadata.</p>			<p>				In An Analysis of VP8, a New Video Codec for the Web (available for download from <a href="https://scholarworks.rit.edu/theses/3184/">RIT Scholar Works</a>, 2011, Sean Cassidy wrote “InVP8, a plane is a set of two-dimensional data with metadata describing the type of thatdata.”</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:selfDocumentation>		<fdd:externalDependencies>			<p>None beyond availability of supporting software.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:externalDependencies>		<fdd:techProtection>			<p>None.</p>			<p>				<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>		</fdd:techProtection>	</fdd:sustainabilityFactors>	<fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>		<fdd:movingImageQF>			<fdd:normalVideo>				<p>Good support. <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/">WebMProject.org</a> provides the <a href="https://www.webmproject.org/docs/encoder-parameters/">VP8 Encode Parameter Guide</a> detailing some encodercontrols, along with a sample encoder, command line usage, and parameter summaries.“Different encoders or tools will map these controls in different ways,” but they areprovided to give users “idea of what to look for.”</p>				<p>Vivid Labs Team a Medium.com, wrote in <a href="https://medium.com/videocoin/proof-of-transcoding-as-a-new-consensus-mechanism-ca9ccf3fa168">Proof of Transcoding as a New ConsensusMechanism</a>, 2019, “Today some of the most utilized codecs are H265. H264, VP9, andVP8 because they achieve high degrees of compression... High-quality compression isessential because it transforms large video files into smaller files while preserving amajority of the quality of the original file. Smaller video files require less storage, whichmakes it easier to distribute them across many platforms, and makes the end-userplayback experience seamless.”</p>				<p>According to Mike R. in <a href="https://getstream.io/blog/real-time-messaging-protocol/">RTMP Streaming without Flash: Why the Real-Time MessagingProtocol Still Matters</a>, Updated May 2021, “The media server does important transcodingwork behind the scenes to make this smooth cross-platform experience possible. In aprocess known as transmuxing, the server repackages the original media into manydifferent versions of varying resolution, quality, and bitrate, and even outputs multipledelivery protocols like HLS, m3U8, and VP8 to meet the needs of different playbackdevices.” When users switch from one resolution to another (I.e., 480p to 720p) on astreaming service (YouTube.com) they are asking the service to play back the same videobut a different (resolution in this example) file.</p>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:normalVideo>			<fdd:clarity>				<p>Varies according to encoding. Per <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/pdfrfc/rfc6386.txt.pdf">RFC 6386 document</a>, “In a complete video playback system, the displayed framesmay or may not be identical to the reconstructed frames. Many systems apply a final levelof filtering (commonly referred to as postprocessing) to the reconstructed frames prior toviewing. Such postprocessing has no effect on the decoding and reconstructions ofsubsequent frames (which are predicted using the completely specified reconstructedframes) and is beyond the scope of this document. In practice, the nature and extent ofthis sort of postprocessing is dependent on both the taste of the user and on thecomputational facilities of the playback environment.”</p>				<p>					<a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/contact_format.shtml">Comments welcome</a>.</p>			</fdd:clarity>			<fdd:beyondVideo>				<p>					<a href="http://wiki.webmproject.org/">Wiki.WebMProject.com</a>, Alpha Channel - defines method supporting WebM video withVP8 alpha channel information on supported browsers.</p>			</fdd:beyondVideo>		</fdd:movingImageQF>	</fdd:qualityAndFunctionalityFactors>	<fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>		<fdd:signifiersGroup>			<fdd:filenameExtension>				<fdd:sigValueNA>Not applicable.</fdd:sigValueNA>				<fdd:note/>			</fdd:filenameExtension>			<fdd:internetMediaType>				<fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:sigValue>video/vp8</fdd:sigValue>				</fdd:sigValues>				<fdd:note>Per VP8 Wikipedia. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8</a>				</fdd:note>			</fdd:internetMediaType>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Pronom PUID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValueNA>See note.</fdd:sigValueNA>					<fdd:note>No PRONOM PUID as of May 2023.</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q1063970</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>VP8, open and royalty-free video coding format. RFC6386On2, TrueMotion VP8. <a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1063970">(https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1063970)</a>					</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q26259220</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>libvpx, codec library implementing VP8 and VP9 encodersand decoders. VP8/VP9 Codec SDK, WebM Project VP8/VP9 Codec, vpxenc, vpxdec. (<a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26259220">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26259220</a>)				</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q47303825</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>RFC 7741: RTP Payload Format for VP8 Video. Requestfor comments publication, RFC7741, RTP Payload Format for VP8 Video. (<a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q47303825">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q47303825</a>)</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q47483716</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>RFC 6386: VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide. Requestfor comments publication, RFC6386, VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide. (<a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q47483716">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q47483716</a>)</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>			<fdd:other>				<fdd:tag>Wikidata Title ID</fdd:tag>				<fdd:values>					<fdd:sigValues>						<fdd:sigValue>Q111586188</fdd:sigValue>					</fdd:sigValues>					<fdd:note>ffvp8, FFmpeg decoder for the VP8 video format. (<a href="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q111586188">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q111586188</a>)</fdd:note>				</fdd:values>			</fdd:other>		</fdd:signifiersGroup>	</fdd:fileTypeSignifiers>	<fdd:notes>		<fdd:general>			<p>Previous Format Versions:</p>			<p>According to <a href="https://www.pcmag.com/encyclopedia/term/on2">PCMag.com’s On2 page</a>, “Founded in 1992 as The Duck Corporation, it was combined with another company in 1999 to become On2.com. In 2001, it was renamed On2 Technologies, and in 2010 was acquired by Google. On2's TrueMotion was its first codec line for full-screen CD and DVD compression. Subsequent codecs used the VP designation such as VP3, VP4, VP5, VP6, etc.”</p>			<ul>				<li>			Per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On2_Technologies#Technology">On2 Technologies Wikipedia</a>:				 				<ul>						<li>TrueMotion S</li>						<li>TrueMotion RT</li>						<li>TrueMotion 2</li>						<li>TrueMotion VP3/4 (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP3">VP3</a>)</li>						<li>TrueMotion VP5/6 (VP5)</li>						<li>TrueMotion VP7</li>					</ul>				</li>			</ul>		</fdd:general>		<fdd:history>			<p>VP8 was initially developed by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On2_Technologies">On2 Technologies</a> and released September 13, 2008, as On2TrueMotion VP8. According to Wikipedia, On2 Technologies was a small, publicly tradedcompany that designed video codec technology. It was acquired by Google in February of 2010.On2’s VP8 technology became the core of Google’s WebM video file format.</p>		</fdd:history>	</fdd:notes>	<fdd:formatSpecifications>		<fdd:urls>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.webmproject.org/vp9/</link>					<tag>Draft VP9 Bitstream and Decoding Process Specification on WebM Project page</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>		</fdd:urls>	</fdd:formatSpecifications>	<fdd:usefulReferences>		<fdd:urls>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>WebM Project</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/</link>							<tag>WebJ Project Home Page</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/docs/</link>							<tag>Documentation</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/code/</link>							<tag>Developer Overview</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/about/faq/</link>							<tag>Frequently Asked Questions</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/cross-license/</link>							<tag>VP8 Patent Cross-License</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/docs/encoder-parameters/</link>							<tag>VP8 Encode Parameter Guide</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.webmproject.org/docs/container/</link>							<tag>WebM Container Guidelines</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Wiki.WebMProject</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>http://wiki.webmproject.org/</link>							<tag>Welcome to the WebM Wiki!</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>http://wiki.webmproject.org/vp8-implementations</link>							<tag>VP8 Implementations</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>http://wiki.webmproject.org/alpha-channel</link>							<tag>Alpha Channel</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Internet Engineering Task Force</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/</link>							<tag>Datatracker</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/rfc6386/</link>							<tag>VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc7741</link>							<tag>RTP Payload Format for VP8 Video</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.on2.com/</link>					<tag>Google On2 Technologies</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//pubs/archive/37073.pdf</link>					<tag>Google Research - Technical Overview of VP8, an Open Source Video Codec for the Web</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://gix.github.io/media-types/</link>					<tag>Gix.GitHub.io - Media Foundation and DirectShow Media Types</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://scholarworks.rit.edu/theses/3184/</link>					<tag>ScholarWorks.rit.edu - An Analysis of VP8, a New Video Codec for the Web</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Wikipedia.com</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP8</link>							<tag>VP8</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libvpx</link>							<tag>libvpx</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebM</link>							<tag>WebM</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebRTC4</link>							<tag>WebRTC</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_coding</link>							<tag>Adaptive Coding</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantization</link>							<tag>Quantization</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YUV</link>							<tag>YUV</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discrete_cosine_transform</link>							<tag>Discrete Cosine Transform</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamard_transform</link>							<tag>Handamard Transform</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vorbis</link>							<tag>Vorbis</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opus_(audio_format)</link>							<tag>Opus (audio format)</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VP9</link>							<tag>VP9</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AV1</link>							<tag>AV1</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luma_(video)</link>							<tag>Luma (video)</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Alliance for Open Media</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://aomedia.org/</link>							<tag>Home Page</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://aomediacodec.github.io/av1-spec/av1-spec.pdf</link>							<tag>AV1 Bitstream &amp; Decoding Process Specification</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://docs.fileformat.com/video/vp8/</link>					<tag>Fileformat.com - What is a VP8 File?</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>BlogGeek.me</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://bloggeek.me/webrtcglossary/vp8/</link>							<tag>VP8</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://bloggeek.me/vp8-vs-vp9-quality-or-bitrate/</link>							<tag>VP8 vs VP9 - Is This About Quality or Bitrate?</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://bloggeek.me/webrtc-media-server/</link>							<tag>What Exactly is a WebRTC Media Server?</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://medium.com/videocoin/proof-of-transcoding-as-a-new-consensus-mechanism-ca9ccf3fa168</link>					<tag>Medium.com - Proof of Transcoding as a New Consensus Mechanism</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://getstream.io/blog/real-time-messaging-protocol/</link>					<tag>GetStream.io - RTMP Streaming without Flash: Why the Real-Time Messaging ProtocolStill Matters</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://rcpmag.com/articles/2010/05/20/google-goes-open-source-with-webm-vp8-codec.aspx?m=1</link>					<tag>RCPMag.com - Google Goes Open Source with WebM, VP8 Codec</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Codecs_and_containers</link>					<tag>Wiki.ArchLinux.org - Codec and Containers</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://openmp4file.com/av1.html</link>					<tag>OpenMp4File.ocm - VP8, VP9, AV1 Encoding Standards and WebM</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>http://home.simula.no/~paalh/students/DagHaaviFinstad.pdf</link>					<tag>University of Oslo – Master&#39;s Thesis: Multi-Rate VP8 Video Encoding</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.opera.com/</link>					<tag>Opera.com</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/new/</link>					<tag>Mozilla.org</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.chromium.org/chromium-projects/</link>					<tag>The Chromium Projects</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://caniuse.com/?search=vp8</link>					<tag>CanIUse.com - VP8</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://www.5kplayer.com/</link>					<tag>5kPlayer.com - 5KPlayer</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://editor.tips/file/vp8</link>					<tag>Editor.tips - VP8 File Editor</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>http://www.inmatrix.com/files/zoomplayer_download.shtml</link>					<tag>InMatrix.com - Zoom Player Max</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>http://www.codecian.com/</link>					<tag>Codecian.com - CodecVisa</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlReference>					<link>https://developers.google.com/speed/webp#how_webp_works</link>					<tag>WebP</tag>				</fdd:urlReference>			</fdd:url>			<fdd:url>				<fdd:urlGroup>					<fdd:intro>Wikidata.org</fdd:intro>					<fdd:urlList>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1063970</link>							<tag>VP8 (Q1063970)</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q26259220</link>							<tag>libvpx (Q26259220)</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q47303825</link>							<tag>RFC 7741: RTP Payload Format for VP8 Video (Q47303825)</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q47483716</link>							<tag>RFC 6386: VP8 Data Format and Decoding Guide (Q47483716)</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>						<fdd:urlReference>							<link>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q111586188</link>							<tag>ffvp8 (Q111586188)y</tag>						</fdd:urlReference>					</fdd:urlList>				</fdd:urlGroup>			</fdd:url>		</fdd:urls>	</fdd:usefulReferences></fdd:FDD>